it diffused out it diffused out it's almost as if we are solving not the
advection equation but an advection diffusion equation exactly so why why is
it the case let's go back to our numerical scheme and look at when we
discretize this equation using this way we know it is a consistent
discretization to the equation we want to discretize and consistent means as
Delta X goes to zero the the error the error in this discretization in this
approximation goes to zero in first order this particular case but it turns
out the same discretization may be an even better approximation to an advection
diffusion equation
which makes the behavior of the code like that so let's look a little bit
into actually is that the case how do we figure out how do you think we figure out
when we look at an accuracy of a scheme what do we do
Taylor series exactly okay so the only non-trivial Taylor series is this one
right so that's an easy case ui minus 1 is equal to ui which is you are which is
delta x away minus delta x times ui prime so that's a shorthand for first
derivative plus Delta x square over 2 ui double prime minus Delta x cube over 6
ui triple prime etc right so I should just
wrong addition salty unfiltered just a right all tidak top of just uh right o
delta x to the fourth or here that means the rest of the terms the case at least
as fast as Delta X to the fourth now we gave 아주 to use to find out what the
matrix use Islamicик rules product us to test task or work to find as soon as
right so we have this term we have minus delta x to the fourth over here that
means the rest must be case at least as fast as data x to the fourth now with
beginners along the tutorial you're
x ui prime plus delta x prime ui double prime minus delta x cube over 6 ui
triple prime I'll just ignore the rest so so because O Delta x fourth divided
by Delta X how can I write this as O something so if I divide O Delta x
fourth by Delta X it's gonna be Delta x cube right because if this is a term
that decays as Delta x to the fourth if I divide that term by Delta x one
Delta x cancels I get Delta x cube okay this is equal to 0 so now we look at
this equation and factor out this Delta x oh we have a minus on the whole thing
okay
we have a minus on the whole thing because it's minus okay plus u Delta x
Delta x cancels we get our dui DX let me write as partial because now we are back
with the spatial derivatives so that's that's the term that approximates this
equation but then we look at the next term what is it it's a minus Delta x over
of big U times partial square u partial x square right we also have a term plus
Delta x square over 6 u partial cube ui partial x cube that is equal to Delta x
cube very high order so this term is like it's very small when our Delta x is 2 pi over 100
so this term is like it's very small when our Delta x is 2 pi over 100
So this discretization we are using is actually an better approximation so so
this term is also small let's not let's ignore this term for now it's a better
approximation to this equation which if you move this term to the right-hand side
it's a diffusion term what's interesting is that it's a diffusion term so so let's
see
this is the diffusion
üll
byочку
right or some people call it dissipation
because it dissipates like the peak of
any wave signals so this term is
proportional to delta x which means if
you have a big delta x this term is
stronger if you have a small delta x this
term is weaker right so let's test it to
see if that is the case so here we used
n equal to a hundred if you use n equal
to 200 the dissipation is going to be
half as strong
let's see if that is the case so now my
I want to say my x is equal to
0 to 199 divided by 200 and the rest I
think I'll just do the same u0 is the
same I would do od45 the same now it
discretizes a time domain using 400 and
something time steps right and if you
remember the CFL condition we derived in
the last lecture the first order
derivative
delta x
is divided by 2 delta t should also
approximately be divided by 2 that's why
you see slightly more than the doubled
number of teeth
we already held on and let's plot this
solution not using red now but X you
let's do it as green
so less dissipation right so how do we
know it's half as much dissipation let's
solve it for twice that long let's solve
it for full price so that these waves
should be at back to through two times
the domain and he's almost a double so
so let's plot this using we already had
blue green red
let's do huh black hmm okay okay the
black one is almost the same as the red
which means the dissipation is almost
half as large right yes what change did
you make to create the green solution
what does change between initial red I
doubled the number of grid points so
this is the step this is the step is that
of 0 to 99 divided by 100 I did 0 to 199
divided by 200 that's the only thing I
changed and the rest is the same this
step this step this step is the same