Okay, now here I'm only using two grids.
How about more? The way to involve more
grids is on here. So here, instead of only
performing iterations on the cost grid
calling Gauss-Seidel, I'm going to make a
decision of whether just to Gauss-Seidel
or call multigrid further on. So what I
will be doing is that I still initialize
du to zeros and here I have a condition.
If the size of RC, let's see the first
dimension, is less than what? First
dimension, if I have a 2 by 2, I mean the
only thing that makes sense for me to do
any iteration would be the size
would be less or equal to 4, right? So
if the size is equal to 3, that means I
have a single grid point in the middle I
want to solve. So then I do that. Else I
do du equal to multigrid of du and RC.
So I'm calling this the same function recursively.
So now let's see what we get.
Okay, u is equal to u0 again. For i goes
1, 2, 5. Let's do another five iterations.
u is equal to multigrid ue. Okay, I'm
done and let's make figure. I am show u
title multigrid.
Here is what I get. So this is
this is like the true solution that I
have on here and the solution is not
new folder. I want to view the folder. The
solution is coming from an image.
Solution is coming from image airplane dot
outside of. So this is the image and
this is the image I copied for the
solution from and made my right hand
side according to this as an exact
solution. And we see like after five
iterations of multigrid, we get pretty
much the solution right. So if you think
of how many regulations is equivalent to
First of all, the cost grid iterations is
a lot more cheaper and I'm performing 10
iterations on every grid level. So 120 English digits.
means there are 10 levels right so 10 times 10 means each multi-grid iteration
is like a hundred iterations including from the closest to find it's great and
if you didn't have multi-grid and you just performing 500 Gauss-Seidel
iterations first of all it will take longer because all of this 500 is gonna
be on the finest grid and second if I am show the U title 500 Gauss-Seidel okay
it still hasn't finished but once it finishes you can see that
not finished but it's still going to be on the finest grid and then you can see
the only slower but the effect of 500 Gauss-Seidel is not nearly as good as
five iterations of multi-grid still going on okay right 500 iterations of
Gauss-Seidel we only get this and with multi-grid we have a cheaper 500
iterations we get almost the exact solution