Find a volume on non-uniform grid.
Still we have a single spatial dimension, but the space is now divided by a non-uniform set of grid points.
So we have x0, we have xn, and we have x1, x2, and the spacing between the axes are no longer going to be uniform.
If you think of the way we formulated finite volume, there is practically no difference between how we are discretizing a uniform grid and a non-uniform grid.
We are still going to define a u1 here.
So let me rename the grid points to be x of half, x of 1 and half, x and 2 and half, 3 and half, etc.
And this is going to be n and half.
So we still have our volumes being named integers.
Particularly, we define ui as the cell average.
Now the cell size is x of i plus half minus x of i minus half.
We no longer have a uniform delta i.
So let's call this delta x of i, the size of the ith cell.
So we have integration over x i minus half to x i plus half of u times dx.
We have a volume average like that.
Remember, the integral form of the equation applies to any interval.
So if we apply the integral form of the equation, we get dui dt would be equal to 1 over delta xi.
The derivative of...
the total amount of quantity inside that volume.
The derivative of that is the flux at i minus half minus the flux at i plus half.
Right?
Now, we still are going to use finite volume approximation to approximate these fluxes.
And the approximation would work in very similar ways.
Okay?
And that is going to give us the same kind of finite volume solution as we had before.
So, for example, let's work it out for a very simple scheme.
So let's copy the same DTT burgers we worked on in the last lecture to the DTT of a non-uniform grid.
Okay.
Let's try it out.
So we need to get this very simple.
Okay.
We're gonna name it now uniform.
So the input of that we need to make a grid.
So let's make a worst possible grid for ourselves.
Let's make n equal to let's say 100 and let's just make x to be a random.
Is it rand or random?
Rand maybe?
Okay so x is basically a random set of points within 0 and 1.
Actually I want to make it n-1 because that's the interior points and I want to append 0
and 1 in the beginning.
So x I would make 0 in the beginning.
I want to sort x in the middle and I put 1 there.
So if I plot x it's basically a pretty non-ideal set of points.
So let me plot x and 0s 101.
Plot it like that.
So this is gonna be our grid points.
In some places it's terrible, some places it's white.
Okay so let's try it with that.
Let's make x to be globals.
So that I can use this in the function.
So let me make global x.
n is still gonna be a length of u, that's right.
And dx is now x of 2 to n minus x 1 to n minus 1.
So this is my dx which is no longer a constant.
But a length of 1.
Okay.
So I'm gonna make this a length n array.
So we are gonna be performing the reconstruction.
So for simplicity let's make our reconstruction to be, let's make our limiter to be 0 for
now.
Okay.
Because when we have a non-uniform grid we need to also adapt our limiter with the different
x, i's.
For example when we compute our slope.
So we have a non-uniform grid.
Okay.
So that means we need to also adapt our complete grid, so we have 2 large and common
and single units.
Okay.
So we need to also adapt our complete grid.
And also the slope needs to be, the slope needs to be considering half of the delta
x in 1 cell plus the half of another delta x in another cell, right.
So because if we have a non-uniform grid, the slope from here to here needs to be taking
half of the slope, half of the grid size, into adjacent cells.
But let's avoid that complexity for now.
So, if we avoid that complexity, we are going to reconstruct basically our U plus half left
is going to be the solution, the cell average on the left of the interface.
U plus half right is going to be the solution cell average at the right of the interface.
We are still going to apply good enough scheme and this is going to be dot divide.
So everything else is going to be pretty much the same.
So in MATLAB, let's compute x center to be x1 to n minus 1 plus x2 to n divided by 2.
And let's say our U0 is sine of x1.
So we have 2pi times x center.
If we plot x center, U0, this is still our initial solution, the same as what we had
last time.
So now let's solve it using ODE45, DDT non-uniform, 0 to let's say 0.5, using U0 as initial condition.
We have a solution.
So let's plot x center and U to see what the solution looks like.
Right.
Okay.
So that's what the solution looks like.
It's still a first order accurate scheme.
And because we have a non-uniform grid.
We have a non-uniform grid.
So the amount of dissipation we are experiencing depends on where the sharp feature of the
solution lies.
If the sharp feature of the solution travels through a bigger cell, we experience more
dissipation error.
If it travels through a smaller cell, we experience less dissipation error.
So the solution goes not...so the dissipation no longer acts as if it's a constant amount
of dissipation.
It's a little bit weakly, but like we still get a solution that looks pretty good.
All right.
So this is how we can apply finite volume schemes in the non-uniform grid.
Really minimum change to what we have to do on uniform grid.
The limiter would require you to do a little bit more work adjusting the different grid
sizes, but still minor change.