right so let me make let me make a title 100 iterations okay and let's compare
with with the original solution you exact I should be dividing by 255 also
okay so this is my original solution title exact solution so I have the exact
compared to a hundred relations what do we see darker right somehow the solution
is after hundred regions is darker than the exact solution so that hasn't
exactly converged yet and let's look at what is
the exact solution so let's look at what is the exact solution so let's look at
what is the exact solution so let's look at what is the exact solution so let's look at the
which we have been marking the approximateintelectual as a
comes from the differences so
okay so
after the 100 iterations
as long as really
I have an answer
so
that means
after the
centacking
it seems that
the
dimension must agree. So my uexec after expanded, I call it uexpanded.
Right? Okay. This is my solution error. That's interesting because it's like, of
course we know that if you subtract, if you add these 100
iterations with the solution error, I get the exact solution. That's just the
definition of the solution error. But there is something interesting that the
100 iteration solution seems to be picking up the contours pretty well, like
all the sharp features, right? While the solution error seems to contain a blurred
image of the original solution. So let's keep iterating. Let's do this equal, let's
look at what's the solution after a thousand iterations.
Now,
I did the thousand iterations. Let's make another figure.
I am sure you divide by 255.
Title, a thousand iterations. Now it's a lot better in that there it's not as
dark as 100 iterations, right? A thousand- a hundred. A thousand is
not you.
now a lot brighter but it's still not as bright as the true solution exact
solution a thousand iterations and if we start to look at where's MATLAB if we
look at the the solution error so figure I am sure you expand it I will change
this to solution error after thousand iterations that's what I get so now
it's not even a blurred image it's just completely blurred so I
basically get a very smooth white blurb of light okay right so now now what
I can see is that because the solution error contains completely smoothed
features
so I can change this to solution error so that
what I can expect is that the solution after a thousand iterations should
already contain all the anything that is not as smooth as basically a smooth
hill right on the solution. Now let's do more. So we know it'll finally converge.
So let's just brute force it, make two other zeros. It may run for a while, right,
but after it finishes we know it should converge pretty much to the right
solution. Now the question as it is running is can we know a priori what we
were observing? Can we know how the convergence is going to happen? What
modes converge is faster, what modes converge is slower?
So we know that the convergence is going to happen. What modes converge is faster, what modes converge is slower?
So why after many iterations I still get a solution error that is like a very
smoothed blurb of light? Yes? Right, remember our eigenvalue eigenvector
analysis on the error equation? The error is going to decay to zero, right, which
now we have finished.
So let's do the solution exact I am sure.
Solution, okay, solution after now it's 100,000 iterations.
Expanded. So now this is the solution error which is completely dark now, which is a
good sign.
Figure I am sure you title.
So this is my solution after many, many iterations and comparing this to the exact solution we
can't see any difference, right? So the solution converged, but it took a lot of iterations.
So right, so the Jacobi iteration converges for this problem, but not particularly for
this problem.
So what does that mean if we look back into this error equation?
We know that after every iteration, the exponent on this lambda, on this eigenvalues are going
to be increased by one.
So lambdas that are close to zero.
So lambda that are close to zero.
Would be taken to zero very fast if you take power of k, right?
So if, I mean it doesn't have even to be close to zero even if lambda has an entry that is
point nine.
After a thousand iterations it's going to be pretty much zero, right?
So point nine to a thousand is like 10 to the minus 64.
Basically even after a hundred iterations if I have an eigenvalue equal to point nine
it'll be pretty much zero.
So anything that is away from one with a sufficient distance is going to be zero.
So even after a thousand iterations we still have some mode there.
Means that has to be very close to one, right?
So point nine nine it's also going to be pretty much zero after a thousand iterations.
Point nine nine nine would still have something there.
So we probably have an eigenvalue in the matrix that is as large as point nine nine nine,
right?
We know it wouldn't exceed one because if it exceeds one it'll diverge.
So but it must have an eigenvalue that is almost one.
And can we guess what the corresponding eigenvector is?
What is the corresponding column in V look like?
Is the eigenvector corresponding to the very close to one eigenvalue representing a smooth
feature or an oscillatory feature?
After .
Yes, the error was smooth after many iterations.
That means the remaining part, right, after you take K to be large, the remaining part
would correspond to the column of V corresponding to a large eigenvalue.
By large I mean close to one.
Not .9 but .999.
So that is a way we are going to analyze the behavior of these iterative methods starting
from next lecture.
And then we are also going to be talking about what can we do to accelerate it.
And that's going to be our multigrid method.
Yes?
I have a question about your code and why we don't need to use f in the formulation
of u k plus.
Yes.
You used the previous guess.
But in that figure right there.
Here?
Yeah.
Why don't we need to use f?
f is added here.
So I can, so here I can either initialize u k p plus one to be zero and add the f into
here.
Here I just took the alternative approach of initializing this to the f term to this,
I initialized the next iteration to this term.
Okay.
And then added this term in the loop.
Right.
So it's this line that added the f term.