So the weak form in general, we only did the weak form for Poisson's equation, but there are also weak forms for many other equations.
So in general, the weak form contains two elements. One element is what's called a bilinear form.
And we write it as a of u and v.
So an example of the bilinear form we have before is minus integration of a to b, the derivative of x times the derivative of v.
It is equal to...
So this is the...
Bilinear form.
It has to satisfy a certain number of criteria.
First of all, a times any c1 times u1 plus c2 times u2, v has to be equal to c1 times a of u1, v plus c2 times u2, v.
So this is simply...
So this is simply a linearity in the first argument.
It also has to satisfy a similar linearity in the second argument.
It's equal to c1 times a of u, v1 plus c2, there is an a here, a, u, and v2.
Right.
So this is the standard.
definition of what is linear and the reason it's called bilinear is that
because it is linear with respect to both its arguments. In this example it's
pretty clear why each of them are linear. If you perform linear combination
of u, you can pull these linear combination coefficients out of the
integral. Alternatively, if you perform any linear combination of v,
you can also pull these linear combination coefficients out of the
integral. And in our example this bilinearform has a particularly nice
property. It's symmetrical, right, so if we exchange u and v in these two
arguments, the value doesn't change. And this, if you remember, has
an intimate relationship with the symmetry of the matrix A we got out of
discretizing using finite element. okay but
But like this, it's only vodka.
And this one is also a complete example. mentions and use to each idle.
for other equations, for example, if we have odd derivatives in the equation, in the differential
equation, then the bilinear form we're going to get is no longer going to be symmetric.
Okay, the other element we need in defining the weak form is a linear functional.
We call it L of v.
So L of v, in our previous example, we have this integration of f times v dx is equal
to our L of v.
So L of v has a single argument because f is predefined.
f is a known function, is a given known function.
So L of v is a single argument because f is predefined.
So L of v has a single argument because f is predefined.
So another example of a linear functional is L of v simply equal to v at 0.5, right?
Our previous example of like when f is a delta function.
So that's also a linear functional.
The linear functional has to satisfy a very similar criterion as the bilinear form.
It has to satisfy L.
So L of c1 v1 plus c2 v2 has to equal to c1 times L of v1 plus c2 L of v2.
That's why it's called a linear functional.
Now, once we define the bilinear form and the linear functional, the weak form
also requires a space.
So actually,
the bilinear form and linear functional, they both require a certain space.
So u and v are in a certain space.
And this is v in a certain linear space.
I mean, they should have a...
In the simplest form of finite element, the u and v should be in the same space.
Then we've got what's called a Galerkin method.
And in more advanced treatments, u and v can belong to different linear spaces.
But no matter what you do, the v in the bilinear form and the L in the linear functional has to be in the same linear space.
So the weak form is to find u within x.
So let's actually make it clear, make it more general by saying that u is in a certain x u.
This is in x v.
So find u in x u such that a u v plus L of v equal to zero for any v in this space x v.
And a special case is u...
It's x u.
It's x u is equal to x v.
That's called a Galerkin method.
Well, Galerkin method also requires the space of x u and x v to be the same.
And we are also discretizing x u and x v in the same way.
When we go from this infinite dimensional space to a finite dimensional space,
we are also selecting the basis.
And this is also in the same way.
All right.
So this is a general form of the weak form of differential equation.
And for a lot of differential equations out there, we can find this kind of weak forms that represent the differential equation,
but gives more general solutions, even if the right-hand side of the differential equation or some coefficients in the differential equation is no longer well-defined functions.
Okay.
An example I can give is the following.
An example I can give is in structural mechanics,
people often solve some kind of equations for structural elements like a beam.
And the simplest form of...
Basically, all the beam equations involve fourth-order derivatives.
But the simplest beam equation, the Euler beam equation,
has a form like that.
So the fourth-order derivative of the solution plus f is equal to zero.
And here, u describes the bending of a beam, and f is the loading on the beam.
So f and u is the...
f is loading.
And u is the...
So f is loading.
And u is deflection.
All right.
So...
And...
We can derive the weak form again by multiplying a test function u
on this equation.
So let's say this is a, this is b, dx is equal to zero.
And because u involves a fourth-order derivative, we need more comprehensive boundary conditions
than what we have for the Poisson's equation.
So the boundary condition for the beam can be a simple support can be clamped.
A simple support means the value of u has to be a certain value, which means the position
has to be fixed.
And also, it has no bending moments, which means the second-order derivative of u has
to be zero.
I mean, second-order derivative is like...
Second-order derivative is like the curvature.
Or it can be clamped, which means the first-order and...
The u and the first-order derivative has to be zero, which means, like, the slope has
to be fixed.
So, so let's, let's, for example, give a used example of u and u derivative both equal
to zero at zero and one, or at a and b.
Then, during the integration by parts...
Okay, so, so if we have this, of course, when we define a u , u also has to satisfy,
satisfy these boundary conditions.
Okay, and, and then what, what is u ?
u is going to be...
So, x u, sorry.
x u is...
x u is actually the Sobolev space in between a and b of two, because in this case, u is
taking a fourth-order derivative.
And when we derive the Sobolev space, we're going to find out that although we won't require
that the solution and the test function to have a fourth-order derivative, but they need
to have a second-order derivative.
Okay.
So, what we're going to get over here is that...
We integrate by parts once, so a and b, v of fourth derivative of x.
If we integrate by, by parts once, we get a minus sign, we get a derivative of v, and
we get a third-order derivative of u.
And we integrate by parts twice, the negative sign is gone again, and we have a second-order
derivative of v and a second-order derivative of u.
Okay.
So, we have the может if y equal to plane distance.
And this is going to be a product of the first-order derivative of u.
So, let me maybe give you a little bit more of a sense of the meaning, of физene usually.
This is our assertion in here.
We have a product of u.
So, we're going to use this condition.
And we'll take our position of becomes theets and that's the solution.
Okay.
and what is our linear functional it's gonna be the same right integration of
V and F so that completes our derivation of the weak form so the ingredients of
the weak form first of all we need to define the space of the solution and the
test function in this case both can be H2 we also need to define a bilinear
form in this case the product of the second derivatives we need to define a
linear functional in this case the product of the test function V with the
known function F okay and we can use find elements to solve this we can
construct a in this case we are going to notice that
P is the same as the test function so we need to define the product of the second
derivative and of course to use a bilinear function the Appозiter will
stop the math so we are going to Chinese easily爽z Professor
so,Where do you replace with this tableни에 f
so,We need to free hey
we are going to solve the same matrix equation,
A U equal to B,
to get the linear combination coefficients
of these piecewise quadratic basis functions.
And then the solution has to be reconstructed
using the linear combination coefficients
on these piecewise quadratic basis functions.
All right.
So this is just another example
of what the weak form can be for other equations.