I'll give you an example. So let me say if I discretize the time derivative using forward order
and I assume everybody at least know what forward order is. So it basically takes two time steps.
So k plus 1 and k are two consecutive time steps. One is at t, one is at t plus delta t.
So this is approximation to dEI dt at t equal to tk.
This, let's write down the numerical solution.
ek of i plus 1 plus ek of i minus 1 minus 2 ek i plus tau i.
OK.
If you look at this equation, there is a condition for which the solution would not self-amplify.
The condition is delta t has to be less than delta x squared.
Do I need over 2? No, I don't need over 2. So delta t has to be less than delta x squared.
OK.
All right.
Because otherwise, because otherwise I'm going to derive a matrix equation.
I'm going to say e to the k plus 1. I'm going to define it as ek plus 1 1, ek plus 1 2, etc.
ek plus 1 n, let's say minus 1.
This is going to be a matrix times e to the k.
e to the k is the same vector.
e to the k is the same vector at k plus this vector tau, which is also tau 1, etc.
tau i, tau n minus 1, also at time step k.
So if you look at the matrix, what the matrix is, OK, you probably need to rearrange the terms in this equation.
And this is this is multiplied by delta t.
So what you need to do is you need to write down ek plus 1 is equal to eik plus delta t over delta x squared times minus 2 eik plus ei plus 1 k plus ei minus 1 k plus delta t tau ik.
And the matrix is going to look like very similar.
To the kind of matrix we derived in the last class, but a little bit different because I have this term and I have a delta t term.
So the diagonals, for example, is going to be 1 minus 2 delta t over delta x squared.
Right.
The off-diagonals is just going to be delta t over delta x squared.
So this is the same and the lower diagonal is also the same.
You can take a look at this matrix and you can particularly look at what's called the norm of this matrix.
OK, so let's say this matrix is A.
The norm of the matrix.
The norm of this matrix defines the norm of the matrix.
Defines the maximum possible ratio of A times E divided by E.
OK.
And here both the numerator and denominator are the norm of a vector.
So, for example, norm of the vector E.
So E is a vector.
OK.
And here the numerator is defined as the length of the vector.
So EI 1 squared plus E2 squared plus etc plus EI minus 1 squared.
So this.
By the way, there are many different norms.
This is one of the most commonly seen norm.
It's usually called the 2 norm because of the squares are power of 2.
And if I'm using 2 norms for the vectors,
the matrix norm is also called the 2 norm.
The matrix norm is inherited from the vector norm.
OK.
So now if the norm of the matrix is less than 1,
I'm fine because E is equal to A times E plus a truncation error.
If the truncation error is small,
then the E would be the same order of magnitude as the truncation error.
It would not self-amplify.
If the norm of the matrix is greater than 1,
no good.
Even if I have a small delta t,
even if I have a small tau,
my E is going to amplify to infinity.
OK.
And the norm of a matrix in MATLAB,
you can just type norm.
All right.
So that's a good way to look at the norm in a matrix.
MATLAB.
Is it for any vector E?
So the definition of the norm is for any vector E.
And the maximization is for any vector E.
So the maximization is for any E not equal to 0.
You are right.
So the maximization is over all possible E's.
So we are going to,
for some of you this may be the first time we introduce norms.
And if you studied linear algebra,
you probably also have encountered norms before.
But like in MATLAB,
whenever we have a matrix,
let's say if our identity matrix,
the norm of a is going to be what?
So if a is an identity matrix,
what is the maximum possible ratio of aE over E?
1.
1, right?
Because aE is going to be equal to E.
So norm of a is going to be 1.
All right.
If a is equal to 2 times identity,
what is the norm of a?
2.
It's 2, right?
Because this is going to be 2E over E.
So it's going to be?
You need to learn it.
Huh?
Yeah.
Absolutely.
Oh, yeah.
Right.
I have a norm equal to 2.
Yeah, thank you.
I was freaking out.
Yeah.
So,
so,
So this is going to be.
Oh,
yeah.
Okay.
Yes?
To get e here,
like,
do we need to know ua first?
So I think the derivation assumes that we,
like,
already know u sub a for us to be able to
find the matrix for E.
Is that right,
or,
I mean,
if we ...
So is...
Go back one slide.
Yes.
So to find the equation for E,
we assume that we know u sub a,
i,
the plus 1,
and u sub a,
i,
1.
u sub a minus one and so on and so forth.
But in most cases, we don't know what's,
we want to solve for u sub a.
You're right, we don't know what u sub a is.
It's an analytical solution.
Most cases, we don't have it.
And luckily, in this error equation,
although u sub a appears in the beginning,
so in the green part, you see u sub a appears, right?
But once we get to the red equation,
the e's has no u sub a.
The only u sub a appears in which term?
Appears in the tau, right?
So only the source term, only the tau,
has analytical solution in it.
And although we don't know what tau is,
because the exact value of tau depends on analytical solution,
we did tailor series analysis to know how fast
does tau go to zero, as I refined that.
So we can say that the error equation is equal to delta x.
And that is the good thing about the error equation,
is that we don't know what tau is,
but we know the order of magnitude of tau
through tailor series analysis.
And all the other terms does not depend on
the analytical solution.
Right.
Any other questions?
Yes?
So if you have a stable name matrix,
because I'm like, like, client-like,
I'm not going to be able to do that.
Right.
There is a steady state solution for E.
If I have a, if we have a stable A,
can I make the claim that I have a steady state solution for E?
Yes.
This, the answer is yes if tau i does not depend on time.
All right.
So, so tau remember is the difference between the operator,
the discrete operator and the continuous operator,
operated on the analytical solution.
So if the analytical solution reaches a steady state,
then yes.
If the analytical solution doesn't reach a steady state,
for example, in the project when you are controlling the U
and you make U sometimes bigger, sometimes smaller,
then the analytical solution does not reach a steady state.
And your E also would not reach a steady state.
But you can bound this magnitude if you can bound the magnitude of tau.
All right.
Okay.
So, so the norm of A is going to be something that,
that you can use to analyze stability of the solution.
And this particular matrix, for example, we can,
we can call this,
dT dx2.
Let's call this as dT over dx square.
If this is equal to 0.5, okay, we are going to be making a matrix A
that is equal to 1 minus 2 times dT over dx square in the diagonal.
So this is 1 minus 2 times dT dx square times identity of,
let's say, 100.
Okay.
So,
A is that thing.
Oh, it's actually, this is actually 0.
And for I goes from 1 to 99,
we are going to say A of I, I plus 1,
is equal to dT dx square.
A of I, I plus 1 and I is also equal to dT dx square.
So A is this matrix.
If you type norm of A,
you get something smaller than 1.
But if dT dx square is equal to, let's say, 1.5,
you are out of luck.
Because you take A equal to this and you do the same thing.
Norm of A is going to be 4.99.
And you are going to get,
so every time E is amplified by a factor of almost 5,
you are going to get infinity.
You are going to get infinity after a pretty finite number of time steps.
Yes?
Did you say the condition for stability was A less than 1?
Yes.
I'm sorry, norm of A is less than 1.
Right.
Norm of A has to be less than 1.
All right.
Any other questions?
Okay.
So why is the norm larger than 1 still being unstable?
Why is it going to be unstable?
Because if the norm is greater than 1,
that's actually a good question.
I forgot to mention that.
If the norm is larger than 1,
that means there exists an E.
That makes A times E to be larger than E.
Right?
And no matter,
so if you look at the solution,
the truncation error tau,
tau may have maybe a linear combination of many components.
But only if there is one component that lies along that solution,
that component is going to be amplified.
And over many time steps,
if it keeps being amplified,
you get an unstable solution.
So we'll discuss more about that later.
So the norm of A to be less than 1 is a sufficient,
but not necessary condition for stability.
Okay.
There are actually some cases where the norm of A can be larger than 1.
You can still be stable.
You need an eigenvalue analysis of A
to figure out exactly if the scheme is going to be stable or not.
You need the maximum eigenvalue to be actually less than 1.
So in some cases,
even if your eigenvalues are all less than 1,
the norm can still be larger than 1.
But usually the norm is,
if you can make sure the norm is less than 1,
you are sure you get a stable scheme.