What's remarkable is the same thing applies for PDs.
So remember, we have a differential operator discretized in both space and time.
So let's say this is going to be replacing my time derivative here.
This is discretized using forward Euler.
And my right hand side is still the same.
Delta x squared.
And because it's forward Euler, this is u k.
My right hand side is expressed as the differential operator operated on the known quantities.
Or the quantity at the previous time step.
If it's backward Euler, the whole right hand side would be k plus 1.
So now, I'm going to apply the same Fourier transform but still only in space.
Because in time, we don't know if we can do that or not.
So we still...
Only apply this in space.
Oh, I think I messed up with my k.
So let me don't use k plus 1 here. Sorry.
Let's use something like m.
Oh, anyway.
So this is the stability region.
So let's use m.
Okay.
Once we use m, we can say that...
u m of i is equal to summation of k goes from minus n over 2 because of aliasing.
And I have u hat m of k.
Now this u hat is not a function of continuous time but a function of m, the discrete time steps.
u to the j k i delta x.
Everything else is still the same.
So when we plug this in,
the time derivative or the discrete time derivative is only applied to here.
So after doing the same thing we did before, we get...
u hat of m k...
k m plus 1 minus u hat of m k divided by delta t is equal to kappa times...
my 2 cosine delta x minus k...
Sorry.
k delta x minus 2 divided by delta x squared times u hat of m k.
Alright.
So now...
Oh, sorry.
This is delta t, not delta x.
So this comes from here.
This comes from here.
Now, how can we analyze...
Can somebody tell me?
In what cases is this equation stable?
In what cases is the space-time discretization stable?
Right.
If you look at the previous one, we are doing pretty much the same thing, right?
So...
Except for we have something more complex over here.
Okay.
Somebody tell me how do I analyze the stability of this PDE now,
discrete in both space and time?
Right.
So this is the same as our lambda, right?
So we want to analyze that...
We want to analyze 1 plus delta t times this kappa...
2 cosine k delta x minus 2 over delta x squared.
This thing has to be less than 1.
Less than 1.
Alright.
But what about the k here?
There is still...
I cannot decide about this unless I know what k is.
Right.
So kappa is given.
Kappa is from the differential equation.
Right.
But k is something we invented by doing the Fourier series.
So how do I deal with the k?
Yeah?
So...
That's a good point.
Choose the worst case k.
Right.
That's what you are saying, right?
So in other words, this condition has to be valid for all k.
So for all k that goes from n over 2 minus n over 2, etc.
to n over 2 minus 1.
Alright.
So that's actually the difficult part
about making sure a...
partial differential equation is stable.
That is, you have a lot of different modes mixed in the Fourier series.
Right.
So if you have a...
Let's say if you have an initial condition.
The initial condition is usually not just containing a single Fourier mode.
It usually...
If you use any function except for sine and cosine functions,
almost any other function contains all the Fourier modes.
It's just that the magnitude...
It's basically a linear composition of many Fourier modes.
And as soon as one of your k is not stable,
that component is going to be exponentially magnified
and make your whole solution garbage.
So in analyzing stability of partial differential equations,
you need to make sure that all the modes
that can exist in the solution are stable.
Okay.
And now let's figure out what this condition needs, actually.
So let's copy what we had in the last slide.
So delta t kappa delta x squared
to cosine delta x times k minus 2
has to be less than 1.
And now let's try to plot them
as a function of...
Um...
Let's plot them as a function of k delta x.
Okay.
I remember...
So let's plot this as a function of k delta x.
And I think let's use this here.
So this is...
So let's just plot this
as this 2 cosine delta x k minus 2 here.
And we know we need to multiply this thing by that.
Right?
So that's a constant.
So let's define this constant c
as kappa delta t over delta x squared.
And we're going to know later on
this number is called the so-called CFL number.
So this...
Ah...
Move this to here.
Okay.
So this function...
Or this constant times this quantity plus 1
is going to be the decision...
deciding factor in the stability analysis.
So let's look at what this is.
And remember k delta x,
because delta x is equal to 2 pi over n,
and k goes from minus...
minus...
n over 2 to n over 2 minus 1.
So the range of k delta x is bounded between minus pi and pi.
Right?
Okay.
Now 2 of cosine minus 2.
A cosine of k delta x ranges from 1 to minus 1.
So 2 times this minus 2...
Or again, I can write it 2 times cosine minus 1.
Is going to range from...
Basically the maximum is going to be 0.
The minimum is going to be...
minus 4.
Right?
So I'm going to have a function that looks like a cosine,
but goes like that.
And at the bottom, this is minus 4.
Which is equal to 2 times...
cosine of minus pi.
This is achieved when...
when k is equal to minus n over 2.
Minus 1.
Right?
So cosine minus pi is minus 1.
Another minus 1 minus 2 times 2.
It's minus 4.
Alright?
Now...
Once I multiply a number...
Once I multiply this number,
which can range from minus 4 to 0,
with the CFL number,
and add by 1,
I want to make sure this number stays within the range of the circle.
The circle goes from minus 2 to 0.
I mean, also...
Also, this is always a real number, remember?
So I want to make sure that the number lies within that range.
Okay?
So I want to make sure this number,
which now I can write as 1 plus c,
times something that ranges from minus 4 to 0,
has to be less than 1.
So, the less than...
So we're taking the absolute value here, right?
So that means, without the absolute value,
it has to be less than 1 and greater than minus 1.
The less than 1 part is automatically satisfied
because... as long as c is positive.
Because the maximum of this number,
2 times cosine delta x k minus 2,
is going to be 0.
But the greater than minus 1 part is not going to be automatically satisfied.
Because when this takes the value of minus 4,
my c has to be less than... what?
c has to be...
first, greater than 0,
and less than what?
For this to be greater than minus 1.
It has to be less than half.
Right?
Make sense?
So, this is called the CFL condition.
The c and f and l is just the first letter in the last name
of three people who almost simultaneously discovered this law.
Alright, the CFL condition is...
Let me write this down.
It's kappa times delta t over delta x squared
has to be less than 1.