Remember elliptic equations is almost like a special case for the heat equation, x squared,
except for two differences.
One difference is that I'm going to add f of x onto the right hand side.
The other difference is I'm going to make this term equal to zero, which makes it equilibrium.
So I'm going to make it equal to zero.
We already discussed how to discretize this term, and do we know how do we add a function
of x onto the discretization?
Okay.
So we already discussed this term.
If the left hand side is equal to zero, we get a vector of zeros, which replaces d u d t,
d vector u d t, equal to a matrix, let me just call it a, times the same vector u.
So u1, et cetera, to u n minus one.
And if we have boundary conditions, we're going to say that we're going to have a vector
u 1, et cetera, to u n minus one.
going to be adding, we are going to be adding let's say a b1 0 and b n minus 1.
Right? So how do we add this f of x onto this equation? Yeah?
It's just a vector with the sampling point of f.
Exactly. It's just a vector of the samples of f at delta x, 2 delta x, 3 delta x, etc.
So we are going to be discretizing f using the same way.
f is defined as f at i delta x.
So now this, instead of an ODE, what we get?
We get a linear equation.
Right?
Ax plus, if you call this just a vector c,
ax plus au plus c equal to 0.
In MATLAB, how do you solve it?
Backslash.
Backslash, right.
So for example, in MATLAB, before I used a lot of, I used ODE45,
it went through thousands of time steps to solve this equation.
Right?
But instead, I can just solve the same equation using what?
u equal to a backslash b, actually minus b.
Right?
Because I want to solve au plus b equal to 0.
Here I don't have any right hand side.
Okay?
If I close all.
If I plot u, I get the same thing.
I get the same thing.
All right?
So that's how we solve elliptic equations.
Question?
Yeah, but only in the case that you're interested in the final steady state.
Only when I'm interested in the final steady state.
Exactly.
So that's what characterizes elliptic equations.
I'll tell you a little bit, like, what's the difference between hyperbolic and elliptic,
sorry, parabolic and elliptic equations.
So, so when you don't have any time derivative,
you can solve the equation by backslash.
And if I define some right hand side, let's say I have an f that is equal to 1,
n minus 1, 1.
So I have a right hand side f is equal to constant 1.
What I'm going to be solving is au plus b plus f equal to 0,
which makes minus b minus f,
which is the same as the time derivative.
So I can solve the equation.
I get plus b minus f to be the appropriate right hand side.
If I plot you again,
here's what I get.
We get a slight curvature.
Get a slight curvature.
Is that what we should have?
I think...
Sor the second derivative plus one
equal to zero which makes the second order derivative to be negative right
which makes the line go that way all right so that's what we should get and
if you increase F by a hundred you get something a lot more curvy so that's
that's solving elliptic equations and the difference between elliptic
equations and parabolic equations so remember what we had is the domain of
dependence so I'm not going to be talking about the meaning of elliptic
and parabolic because it relates to some analytical partial differential equation
theory but I'm just going to tell you in terms of behavior how do they behave
differently
so elliptic equation works in space and time that's the physical interpretation
of it in mathematics mathematicians may not care about the difference between
space and time right because for them they are basically independent variables
of a function but when we talk about difference in different types of
equations we can think of for parabolic equations there is one special coordinate
we can just call it time and that special coordinate has such a feature
that if you introduced a perturbation to the differential equation to the
solution either to the solution or to the differential equation itself at a
particular space in time that perturbation is going to change the
solution not before that particular time but after that particular time right and
Basically that makes sense if you solve the heat equation for example. If you add
heat at a particular point in space at a particular point in time, the solution,
the temperature field is going to be changed not before you add that heat but
after you add that heat. And because heat, according to heat equation, it diffuses
instantaneously. There is no speed of diffusion for heat. The solution is going
to be changed immediately after the time you add the heat. The change is
going to be very very small, far away from the heat source, very recent after
the addition, but it'll be different. So parabolic equation means that there
exists such a special coordinate, a special independent variable for which
that it behaves like time. If you put up the equation at a particular point in
time, the solution later is going to be different. Elliptic equation does not
have that special coordinate, so that's why we usually call it x. Instead of t we
call it y, think of just that two spatial dimensions. And, for example, the more
general case of this is, we also have two spatial dimensions, facelift atizza
arson. The second load derivative in X and second
low- issue in two over R. and n один dados. And now it's two morequin dive in f.
the derivative in y. That equation does not have neither x nor y is a special
coordinate. If you change, if you put a change in the in the equation, let's say
plus, if you change the f at a particular x and y, the solution is not only going
to be different after a particular y, but it's going to be different everywhere.
It's going to change globally. So elliptic equations are the ones without that
special time-like coordinate. Yeah, this is parabolic, this is elliptic. All right.
So if you think physically, it's
pretty easy to distinguish an elliptic equation. It's one basically without time,
a steady-state type of solution.