So there are three elements in here, three things we need to calculate. One is the area of each triangle.
And what is the gradient of each of these basis functions on the triangle.
Okay, so let's figure out how to calculate the area first.
So to make it easier, let's make a script.
Go to script, find element 2D.
Okay, I'm going to assume I already have the P, T, and IB calculated.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to first try to calculate the area.
Area is going to be zeros, the number of elements.
So let me first...
Okay, so number of elements is equal to the length of the triangles.
So it's triangles, the second dimension.
So any is the number of triangles.
So A...
Let me reserve the big A for the matrix.
So let me call it small a to be the area.
So let me see.
So this is the area, small a.
Okay.
So small a is equal to any at 1.
And I'm going to go over all the triangles.
Okay.
The area is going to be equal to...
It's really...
So I need to figure out two of the edges and do a cross product between the two edges.
That divided by 2 is going to be the area.
Right.
So let me first compute the vertices.
So v1...
Okay, so let me say v is equal to zeros, 2, 3.
So I have a vertex array.
The first dimension is x and y.
The second dimension is the three vertices of the triangle.
So v1 is equal to my p of...
Okay.
My p of column and my t of 1 and i.
Right.
So this is the location of the first vertex.
So my second vertex...
To make it a little bit clearer, let me just call it v1.
Let me just call it v2.
Let me just call it v3.
So 2 and 3.
All right.
So these are the three vertices.
Each one is just two numbers, x and y.
So ai is the cross product, which is really the dot product of v1 minus v2.
And basically the rotated vector of v1 minus v3.
Right.
So let me here...
I'm just going to make it a matrix times...
The rotated vector is 0, 1 minus 1, 0.
Right.
So it's this...
You basically take one of the edges, you rotate it by 90 degrees, and you dot product with the other edge.
That's the cross product.
All right.
So that divided by 2 is going to be the area.
So you want it to be 3.
Oh, yes.
One of them should be 3.
Thank you.
So let's run it to see what I get.
I get an a that is equal to a bunch of things.
And the magnitude seems to match the size of the areas.
All right.
Okay.
Any questions on this?
No?
Okay.
So next we have the area.
Next is to compute the gradients of the basis functions.
Okay.
In order to compute the gradient, let's use the fact that if I have the gradient of phi i,
the gradient of phi i dot with any vector, let's say the vector of v...
The location of the vertex i minus the location of the vertex j, for example.
This should be equal to what?
The gradient of that particular basis function that is equal to 1 at v i and 0 at v j.
What should it be?
The gradient of a linear function dot with a vector should be what?
This should be the value of that phi i at v i minus the location of the vertex j.
So this should be the gradient of phi i at v i minus the value...
Let me say it's x i and x j.
Sorry.
So x is the location of the vertices.
Right?
So if I have a gradient of phi i dot with the difference between the two locations,
this should be phi i at x i minus phi i at x j.
Right?
This should be what?
Should be 1.
Right?
Because unless i is equal to j.
So for any x j that is in the triangle but different from i,
the gradient dot this should be equal to 1.
Okay?
So let me...
Now we have the three x's in the triangle.
There are two independent j's I can use.
So that allows me to form two linear equations whose right hand side are just 1 and 1.
The left hand side is...
The left hand side is a matrix that is formed by...
Let me see.
So x...
x1 minus x2.
So let's call it y1 minus y2.
x1 minus x3.
y1 minus y3.
So these are x and y coordinates.
Dot with the x-directional gradient of the first basis and y gradient of the first basis.
That should be equal to 1 and 1.
Right?
So this gives us linear equations to solve for the gradient as a vector.
So let's form the matrix.
And compute it.
So to form the matrix we just need v1 minus v2.
So that is our first row.
So we need to transpose it to get a row vector.
And v1 minus v3 transpose to get a row vector.
So this inverse times the right hand side, 1, 1.
This is going to be the gradient of the first basis.
Right?
And I can do these three times to get the gradients of the three basis functions associated with that triangle.
So g2 should be 2, 3.
This should be 3, 1.
This should be 2, 3.
This should be 1 and 2.
So each of the matrix is formed by the difference between one vector and the other two vectors on the triangle.
Okay, so now we get the three gradients.
So now we have all the formula we need to compute the value of the matrix.
Right?
But the matrix is a summation over all the values.
So we have the summation over all the elements.
Now instead of going through all the pairs of i and j and figure out all the elements that are shared by the basis function i and the basis function j.
We loop over the elements and accumulate these values of a and j.
So we loop over all the k's and look for whichever pairs of i and j this k contributes to.
We just add it on top of it.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to make a matrix a is equal to 0.
What's the size of this matrix?
Should be the number of points.
Right?
So let's also make it mp is equal to size of p and 2.
So that's the size of the matrix mp by mp.
So this element has three basis functions that it can contribute to.
So what I have to have is let me call it i1, i2, and i3.
And these are just the i1.
Let's simplify it.
i2 and i3.
Right?
So these are computing the three vertex points.
And the same indices is going to, we're going to compute the contribution to.
So i1 and i1 is going to be, is going to be accumulated by something.
Right?
So and we also have, basically we have nine.
Values that we'll contribute to.
So we have i2, i2.
We have i3, i3.
We also have the cross terms.
For example, i1, i3.
i2, i1.
So let's start rigorously.
So i1, i2.
i1, i3.
i2, i3.
And.
Let's do this now.
And when we.
The other side should be exactly the same.
Because the matrix is symmetric.
Right?
So let's only construct one part of it.
For now.
So the formula, according to the formula, this is summed by a of i.
The area.
Times.
The gradient of phi i.
Times the gradient of phi j.
So dot of g1 and g1.
Right?
This is dot of.
g1.
g2 and g1.
g2 and g2.
Sorry.
So this is.
2 and 2.
This is 3 and 3.
3 and 3.
And this is 1 and 2.
This is 1 and 3.
2 and 3.
So here should be dot of g1 and g2.
Here should be dot of g1 and g3.
Here should be dot of g2 and g3.
And let's.
I mean, if we care about computational efficiency, you won't do this.
But let's do this just for the sake of clarity.
So I'm also going to be making.
The transpose of.
The transpose part of the matrix to be.
Adding up on the same value.
Okay.
Any.
Anything.
Any bug in this.
You can spot.
1, 2, 1, 2, 1, 3, 2, 3.
2, 1.
Okay.
Looks good to me.
All right.
Since we have constructed the matrix.
So let's run it.
Okay.
Looks like it ran.
And we have a matrix A.
So spy A should be.
Something.
Like that.
Most of the A is.
Empty, which means it's 0.
And so for what we see as blue dots.
These are the locations on the matrix that are non-zero.
These are the coupling terms.
These are the neighbors.
Of.
Basis functions.
So.
This.
Is.
All.
Of.
Bases.
Functions.
Right.
So for me.
What I want.
All.
Is.
To do.
To make this.
A.
A value.
So.
I'm going to call this.
tiene.
This.
Bases.
And.
This.