Let's remind ourselves of the difference between finite difference, finite volume,
and finite element. So I'm going back to the illustration I had before. In finite
difference, remember we have... in finite difference, when we draw a function, the
finite difference stores the values of the function on the grid points. Right?
That's finite difference. In finite volume, we draw a function. Finite volume
stores the cell averages. These are completely different ways of
discretizing a function, representing a function. In finite element, let's see if
we draw a function...
For a similar function, how does finite element store the function?
This is how finite element stores the function. It looks like piecewise straight lines, but
can somebody take a guess at what is actually the piecewise linear representation of the
function? How does the... how does the thick red line
relate to the thin red line I just drew on the screen?
List squares. That red line seems to be somehow minimizing the distance, minimizing the average
distance in a certain way between the piecewise linear line and the original thin line. Right?
So this is one way of doing finite element.
And this is the primary way we are going to be discussing this in this class.
But just to give you a little bit more insight into what finite element is doing, I'm just going to give you another...
another demo, also with finite difference.
I'm going to try to draw a very similar function as I did before.
And this is also a different finite element approximation to the same... to the function.
Let's see.
So now you could draw a representation, say, for which the font size and the dark color
are the mult deserve oversize out of the component.
If you draw this!.
Yeah.
One could draw this.
Can you show it?
Yeah, so that would be the Mitt onwards.
M attempting to create a line across a picture over the strictly jon lecturer in class.
What's the%?
We are restricting the approximation in different space of functions.
In the previous case, we require our representation to be continuous.
In this case, we no longer require our function to be continuous, but we are still doing these squares.
And in this case, because we are allowing ourselves to minimize the distance between the original and approximation function over a bigger space,
because we no longer require it to be continuous,
we can get a better approximation of the function, potentially.
We are minimizing the distance between the approximate function and the original function.
And you can see that the approximation function is still doing the same thing.
And you can think of the previous example as performing that minimization under some constraint,
while this is performing the same optimization without these constraints.
And of course, without the constraint, potentially, you can get a better, smaller objective function in your minimization.
So you can approximate the function slightly better.
Of course, another way to get a richer space or a bigger space
is just to divide every cell by a factor of two.
Any function that is piecewise linear in the bigger, in the coarser discretization
is going to be a piecewise linear function in the finer discretization.
But the finer discretization has a richer space
because there are more functions that does not live in the original coarser space.
So should you move the division by
character質
and
cause
Arctic
is
확
natural
equal
r
with
an
program
for
and
with