There is a very general way to analyze numerical schemes. That is, we want to
have convergence, which is we want to have my u hat goes to u analytic as
delta x and delta t goes to 0. This is what I want, right? Because I want
analytical solution, but u hat, the numerical solution, is all I can
compute. So if I look at the difference between them, I want that to go to 0 as I
invest more and more computational resources. But all I can know is
consistency. So I can analyze beforehand if I'm developing a numerical scheme. All
I know is how does tau goes to 0 as delta x and delta t goes to 0. Tau is
the approximation of all the differential operators
in my differential equation. So this is consistency. So what we analyzed
beforehand is that if I in addition have stability, which in the previous example
means just the norm of a is less than 1, a is the amplification of the solution
error as time increases.
That means if I have stability and I have consistency, when both is satisfied,
I will get convergence.
So when you are solving a differential equation, you want to check consistency, yes or no.
As I increase my mesh resolution, decrease time steps, do I have the truncation error
go to 0?
I want to check stability.
I want to check the time steps. Do I have the truncation error go to 0? I want to check stability.
If I don't have truncation error, would my solution error decay to 0 eventually?
For example, a good case to check is when the analytical solution is 0.
If you put up the numerical solution slightly, would it go back to 0?
And then you should have convergence.