Last lecture we put finite element in a more general and rigorous footing.
We defined finite element as a formulation completely removed from the differential equations.
A finite element starts with the weak form of a differential equation.
And a weak form is defined by a bilinear functional A equal to a linear functional L for all the possible Vs in the test space XV.
And we are finding a solution to this weak form.
The solution U has to lie in a potentially different space, X.
So this is generally a weak form of a differential equation.
And we derived the weak form for the Poisson's equation, a second order derivative.
And we also derived for an equation with a fourth order derivative.
So in both cases, the bilinear functional is the integral of the product of certain derivatives of U and certain derivatives of V.
And the linear functional is the integral of the product between the test function V and a known function F.
So in this lecture, we'll start from this weak form and analyze some properties of our finite element solutions.
So first of all, we want to analyze the weak form actually is stable and has a unique solution.
And we will derive conditions for this.
So we will derive conditions for the weak form that is going to give us a unique solution that is stable.
And then we know on the what assumptions we can continue to discuss our finite element to look at how much error our finite element is making.
The error analysis we are studying in this lecture is quite different from the kind of error analysis we are studying finite difference and finite volume.
Because instead of studying the Taylor series analysis, looking at the error in the Taylor series analysis,
we are studying the Taylor series analysis, looking at the error in the Taylor series analysis,
we are studying the Taylor series expansion.
We are now looking at errors in functional spaces that is removed from like the local type of analysis we have been doing before.
So first of all, let's define the situations in which the finite element, the weak form is actually well defined.
So a weak form is first of all well defined for the when the functional on the right hand side has two functions.
So l of v is continuous.
If and only if, which is the definition of the continuity is that,
l of v if I take the norm, whatever norm we have on this x v.
Divided by the norm of the v,
is bounded. So the maximum or supremum of this over the entire space xv has to be less than
infinity. So the supremum is basically a notion of maximum over infinite possible
candidates, right? So because the space of xv has infinitely many members,
so supremum is basically taking the maximum over that space. Or it says that, or equivalently,
equivalently, there exists a maximum, let's say c, such that the ratio between l of v
and the norm of v is less than that c.
For all the possible v's, right? These two are equivalent.
Okay, so this is what we mean by continuity of a linear functional.
It's also called bounded, right? So it's bounded because this supremum is actually,
can be defined as the norm of this l, right? This l have a norm, it's called the induced norm.
It's induced because it's induced by the norm of the vector it operates on, right? And the l of v,
oh sorry, l of v is a number. So the norm it takes is just the norm of the number. So it can be just
an absolute value. If the result of l of v is a real number, then it's just an absolute value.
So let me make this a bit clearer. So l of v is just going to be
a number. So it's the ratio between the magnitude of l of v divided by the norm of the v, right?
Okay, so let's say, for example, a delta function. A delta function is a linear functional, right?
It's linear because, let's say, example.
A delta function of x is a linear functional in the sense that
I can define l of v being integration over a domain, let's say, minus 1 to 1, delta x times v of x dx.
Is this linear functional a bounded or continuous linear functional?
No, we have different answers and all the answers can be correct.
Because we haven't defined what space, what this norm is, right?
So you can only answer is it a linear function, is it bounded or not, once you define a space,
define a space of v. And if you define different spaces, you can only define a space of v.
So if you define different spaces, the norm on the space is going to be different.
So if we are in l2 space, the norm of a function is the integral of the squared function.
If we are in the sub left space, h1, for example, the norm of the same function becomes different.
You have to add the integral of the derivative squared into the norm.
So let's take the simpler case first. If in the l2 space, is this linear functional or bounded?
Is this linear functional or bounded?
So somebody answered yes and no, right?
Who answered yes?
And in l2 space, do you still hold your yes answer?
You think so, okay.
And can you give me, so what c do you think can you derive? How would you derive this c?
The integral of v times x squared of c.
Is that right?
So c is equal to v at x equal to 0.
Yeah, but this is for any v, right?
We have to get a c, get a bound that holds for any v.
c equal to 1?
Okay, so why do you think c equal to 1 work?
Hmm?
By Cauchy-Schwarz inequality?
Yeah, this is a dot product of two functions.
And so if you use Cauchy-Schwarz inequality, you would get less or equal to the same integral of delta x squared dx,
which I don't know what it is, right?
Times something else.
So I don't think that works.
Actually, if you really look at the square of the delta function integrated,
I think you get infinity.
Right, think of you get a spike, narrower and narrower,
whose integral is equal to 1, and you square it.
You make it like a lot larger than, you make the integral a lot larger than 1.
Okay.
Who said no?
Who said no just now?
Did you say no?
So who said this is not a bounded linear function?
No.
Nobody?
Okay, this is not a bounded linear function of L2.
Why is that the case?
Why is the case is because the value of this linear functional can be arbitrarily large
for a V whose L2 norm is equal to 1.
Okay, so let me construct this kind of V.
So X, V, okay, I was looking at from minus 1 to 1, right?
Of course, I can have a function that is equal to,
let me construct a function that is equal to 1 between minus half and half.
This function, of course, has, if you square it, it will be the same function,
and if you integrate it, you get 1.
So the L2 norm of this function is 1, right?
And the linear functional evaluated on this function is going to be the value of this function at 0.
So the linear function is 1.
But I can do some tricks.
What I can do is I can make the value at 0 equal to 2.
And just by shrinking,
by shrinking the area on which it is non-zero to,
instead of minus half, I have 1 minus 1 eighth and plus 1 eighth.
And this function, if you square it,
you get a value of 4 integrated over a length of 1 fourth.
You still get the L2 norm of 1,
but now I can make the value of the linear functional higher.
And I can keep doing this.
And I can keep increasing the magnitude of the function at X equal to 0
and shrink the support,
shrink the area over which the function is non-zero to,
so the function is non-zero.
But...
Yeah, V equal to delta of X is not a proper function, right?
So basically, you can keep shrinking the support
so that the V goes closer and closer to something like a delta function.
And by doing that,
we are going to get the ratio of L of V over the L2 norm of V
that is going unbounded,
and L2 goes to infinity.
So we have no bound.
The delta function is not a bounded linear functional in L2.
But it turns out the delta function is a bounded linear functional in H1.
So if you define...
So L of V is not continuous
and bounded and continuous
for linear functional is the same
in L2,
but
is continuous
in H1.
Okay?
And the reason is that
all of these functions I constructed,
they are not...
So if you look at...
So first of all, they are not in H1, right?
Because they don't have bounded derivatives.
And even if you try to...
Okay, what if I construct a function that is continuous?
Instead of going from minus 1 to 1 in a sharp way,
we can go to minus 1 that way,
and I can shrink it, go like this.
But the problem is we have derivatives that is going larger and larger
when you make the spike going higher and higher.
Right?
So there is no way you can construct a...
construct a V
whose derivatives are still square integrable
while the value at 0 goes higher and higher.
Okay?
And the proof is a little bit time consuming,
but you can still get a sense of that by the following.
So first of all,
Lv is...
So the H1 norm of V
is the integral from minus 1 to 1 V square plus dV dx square, right?
dx.
Right?
So first of all, the V square term cannot be too large.
So V has to be...
The mean value of V cannot exceed, let's say, 1.
Right?
Okay.
The value of V is not going to be too large.
So if I...
So what I'm saying is if I have a V that is equal to...
The norm of V is equal to 1,
okay, I want to show that the value of Lv cannot be...
go to infinity.
Right? So, okay.
So if I have this to be 1, then the mean value of V,
so this term, has to be less or equal to 1.
And this term also has to be less or equal to 1.
And if this term is less or equal to 1,
then the slope cannot be too large.
So you have a function whose mean value cannot be too large
and slope cannot be too large.
So the point...
So the value of the function at 0 also cannot be too large.