Another thing is if you sum up A over one of the dimensions, it should be zero everywhere.
And that's just because if you look at the formula, if you sum up over all the i's,
if you sum up over all the i's, over each element, a, k, the sum of the three gradients should be what?
So if we have three basis functions that lie on a triangle,
every basis function is one at one of the vertices.
And zero at the other two vertices.
If you sum up these three basis functions, what do you get?
The sum of the three basis functions should be equal to what at every vertex?
Should be one, right?
So the whole basis function should be one.
The whole summation should be one across the whole element.
Therefore, the gradient, the summation of the three gradients should be what?
Zero, right?
Because the summation of the gradients should be one.
The gradients is equal to the gradient of the summation, which is a constant.
So if you sum over the gradients, it should be one.
So therefore, when you sum over each row, you should get exactly zero for the matrix A.
And that also, of course, means the matrix is singular.
We haven't defined boundary conditions yet.
The matrix without the boundary condition is going to be singular.
All right.
So now let's figure out how do we set the boundary condition.
So now we have here, remember we figured out all the boundary indices, IB.
So let's define a logical array that is true for all the interior points and false for all the boundary points.
So let's say, okay, interior is equal to one's number of points, one.
Okay.
Interior is equal to, okay, so let's say we already have IB, right, being the boundary points.
IB, is it IB here?
IB, yes, is equal to zero.
So interior is going to be one in the interior and zero on the boundary.
And let's convert it into a logical array.
So that instead of one and zero, it will be true and false.
That will allow us to index the matrix with that logical array.
So my A is going to be A interior, interior.
Interior.
Okay.
So that will reduce the dimension of the matrix, get rid of the boundary dimension, the boundary grid points that I don't need in the matrix.
So if I run that.
Uh-oh.
IP.
Okay.
MP here.
Thanks.
Okay.
It ran.
And so my A, I think, is going to be, yeah, its dimension is reduced.
It's no longer 406.
It's reduced by 70, which is exactly the number of boundary grid points.
And now if you plot the side.
So if you plot the side, you get the sum of A.
It won't be zero anymore.
It will be occasionally non-zero for.
So if you have any basis function that neighbors a boundary grid point, the summation won't be zero anymore.
Okay.
So let's also.
So plot the eigenvalues of A just to make sure we get.
Yeah.
So the eigenvalues of A, they are positive.
So you shouldn't get anything that is zero.
Okay.
That's good.
So we get a positive definite matrix.
Question so far?
Seems like it's working so far.
Now we have the matrix A.
The next step is to figure out the right-hand side.
So B.
So this is going to be the integral of the whole domain of phi.
So we have the integration of phiJ is equal to integral over the whole domain of phiJ times F.
And we set our F is equal to 1 in this case.
So it becomes the integral of phiJ dx.
Again, we split that up into into the elements.
It's going to be integration of phiJ at the element k dx.
integral is only non-zero in a small number of elements, right, 5 or 6. And on
each element, phi j is a piecewise linear function. So on each element, let's say
each element is, we have the triangle, the function is like that. So this is
phi j, and we have x and y. So phi j is gonna be a linear function. If I draw
the contours, it'll be like that. The integral of phi j over this triangle
here is gonna be the volume of this tetrahedral, right. The height of this
tetrahedral is equal to 1, the base is calculated as the area of the triangle.
So this is equal to what? The integral, which is the volume of the tetrahedral,
is equal to what?
Yes. Yes, 1 third times the base, which is a k times the height, which is 1. Right, so
it's a k over 3. Let's code it up here, a k over 3. The right-hand side is gonna be
also 0 of m p 1, right, and after I compute the matrix, I compute the right-hand side.
So the first is equal to a n divided by 3, with the configuration ofchts to be
equal to m r logging over m-1 and the function that an & brings us to .
For the value in the batch, we're gonna to meet the length of the bin a-1 and
we want to avoid this. So the norm of the gradient space outside is about 1,b-1,
and theối of the potatoes tells us how much it is, so each of them are equal to 1.
the three basis functions on that triangle is going to be the same.
So now we have a B, but the dimension of B is still too large.
We need to remove also all the boundary points.
So B is going to be B interior.
Right?
Let's run this.
Okay, so that seems to work.
We get an A 336 by 336.
We get a B 336 by 1.
So let's also define a U. U would have to be covering...in order to visualize U, U has
to be 0, MP, and 1.
But then we're going to set U of interior to be the solution.
It's going to be A backslash B. All right?
So that gives me the solution, the height of the interior basis functions.
Okay.
So the boundaries are going to be left to be 0.
So after this, let's run to see if that works.
Oops.
Zeros.
Okay, that worked.
We get a U. We get a U that is a bunch of zeros.
That's probably boundary.
Yeah, we get a bunch of non-zeros.
So let's visualize that.
Let's use the twice serve again.
We use the...T should be the same, this should be the same, and we just use U, right?
Okay, that's our solution.
So this is our boundary, and we are just solving the Poisson's equation with the constant right-hand
side.
Which means the curvature...or the Laplace...
Right.
So the Laplace-ing of the solution should be negative 1.
Right?
So it bumps up the curvature in the x-direction plus the curvature in the y-direction should
be equal to minus 1.
And that's the solution we get for the two-dimensional Poisson's equation.
And the boundaries are 0.
Okay.
So that completes our demo of what...how do we solve the...how do we use finite elements
for...
A two-dimensional problem.
Any questions about the procedure?
Yes?
I thought you showed that shape like that's...
Something like 5 or 6 inches.
Mm-hmm.
Why was it not a triangle?
Oh, yeah.
So each triangle is shared by three basis functions.
But each basis function doesn't neighbor only three triangles.
Okay.
So let me try to draw it.
So we have a triangle here.
We have a triangle here.
And we have a triangle here.
For example, we have a triangle here.
This basis function, if I draw the contours of that basis function, the basis function
looks like that.
The value of the basis function is 1 over here.
It's 0.
So the contours look like that.
I said it's 5 or 6 because the basis function is non-zero in this case in five elements,
five triangles.
Is that the question you were asking?
Okay.
And you can imagine I can easily have another basis that is non-zero in six elements.
Right?