The final thing we want to discuss for finite element is how to solve time-dependent equations using finite elements.
We have previously focused on mostly steady-state equations, including Poisson's equation.
The second derivative is equal to a known function, and we also touched the beam equation, which is again a steady-state equation.
The question today is how do we discretize the time derivative using finite volume, or how do we deal with the time derivative?
How do we transform the PD with DDT unit into an OD as we did before?
We are going to use again a very simple example, just adding a time derivative term onto the right-hand side of a Poisson's equation.
So Poisson's equation would be the second derivative equal to a given function f.
Today we are going to look at a heat equation instead.
Okay, so we remember infinite element.
How do we start in discretizing an equation?
We started by multiplying this equation with a test function, right?
With an arbitrary test function within a certain space, and thereby derive the weak form.
All finite element discretization started with a weak form.
So if we multiply this equation with a V, so let's say, let's use the bracket as inner product in the L2 sense.
So the bracket is going to be integration over the entire space, V times the ODT over the x.
Would be equal to V.
So we have a second derivative for all V within a certain space that we don't know yet.
So let's decide about it later.
Okay, so let's now write down what this inner product is.
So first of all, we have V times the ODT over, let's say, a one-dimensional space from A to B.
Would be equal to the integral from A to B.
V times the second derivative of U.
And if we want to use the same technique we used to deal with Poisson's equation, on the right-hand side of this equation, what should we do?
Integrate by parts, right.
So here we need some boundary conditions.
Let's assume we have a simple boundary condition, U A equal to U B equal to zero.
Then through integration by parts,
we know that this V, or the integral from A to B, is equal to 0.
So we have a simple boundary condition, U A equal to U B equal to 0.
And we also have to satisfy the same boundary condition.
So with integration by parts, the boundary terms get removed through the boundary condition.
And we also are removing the second-order derivative.
And both U and V have a first-order derivative in this bilinear form.
Right?
Okay.
And we also look at the left-hand side.
And realize that we are integrating only in space, not in time.
So the time derivative can be removed, can be pulled out of the integral.
So the left-hand side becomes d dt of a integral U V dx,
would be equal to minus integration of derivative of V,
derivative of U dx.
Now we get two bilinear forms.
One is integration of U V.
The other integration of du dx times dv dx.
Right? Both are bilinear forms.
Except for one bilinear form has a time derivative in it.
Okay.
To discretize this equation, we apply the same type of finite element discretization
on both bilinear forms at the same time.
What is that discretization?
The discretization is restricting ourselves from an infinite dimensional space
to a finite dimensional subspace.
Okay.
So for discretization,
so up to here, everything is analytical.
So now let's switch to a discretized form.
So now, restrict U to be a summation of I goes from 1 to n of U I,
which is now a number instead of a function,
times phi I,
which are the basis functions of the finite dimensional space.
So now we have the finite dimensional subspace.
Here, we can use the piecewise linear and continuous space
as we did before in Poisson's equation.
Right?
Okay.
Where the phi's, if we draw them,
phi 1 is going to be like that,
phi 2 is going to be like that in 1D,
phi 3 is going to be like that.
So these are the piecewise,
these are the basis functions of the piecewise continuous and continuous space.
And these are the continuous and piecewise linear functions.
Well, the continuous and piecewise linear functions.
Okay.
Now we also substitute phi j to our test function v,
because if this is satisfied for v equal to any of the phi j's,
this can be satisfied by the principle of linear superposition
for all the v's.
That can be expressed as linear combination of phi j's.
So what we have is d dt of integral a to b.
u is now a linear combination.
v is now phi j, phi x,
is equal to minus of now the derivative of v,
which is phi j,
and the derivative of u,
which is a summation.
So we have the integral of ui,
the derivative of phi i.
The right hand side is exactly the same as we dealt with in Poisson's equation.
We pull the summation and the ui out of the integral,
thereby getting summation of i goes from 1 to n,
ui times the integral of derivative of phi j,
times the derivative of phi i.
This is exactly the matrix we call A.
And this is the j-th entry of the matrix A
we used before to discretize the Poisson's equation.
Right?
Okay.
And the left hand side is a little bit different.
The left hand side, we still pull all of these out.
But the left hand side, we still pull all of these out.
But remember these ui's,
they are individual numbers at every t.
But these ui's are what makes the solution u time dependent.
So ui's are actually functions of t,
while the phi j and phi i,
they are not functions of t.
Therefore, we can pull the summation of ui
out of the integral.
But we cannot pull it out of the time derivative.
What we can pull out of the time derivative
is the remaining integral in space.
So let's write it down.
d dt of...
And the summation can be pulled out.
Right?
Summation can be pulled out,
but like,
d ui dt has to be put onto the time derivative.
And then we have integration of
phi i,
phi j,
d x.
And these are not in the time derivative
because they are not functions of time.
Now,
this is another,
this is the discretization of a different bilinear form.
This bilinear form also is discretized into a matrix.
And let's call it mj.
Equating the left hand side to the right hand side,
what we get is m,
the matrix m,
okay?
Think of mj,
I multiply it by d ui dt.
This is m times d u dt,
where u is now the vector of u1, u2, u3, etc.
So this is a vector times a matrix,
being the left hand side.
And the right hand side is equal to
minus a matrix times the vector u.
Interestingly, we get,
when we discretize this equation,
we don't get a d vector u dt equal to a matrix times u.
We get another matrix,
we call the math matrix.
You find the element.
Times the time derivative of u equal to,
now this is something we call the stiffness matrix,
minus a.
Times the vector u.
So in finite element jargon,
this is math matrix.
This is stiffness.
The reason for that is,
in the days even without computers,
people are trying to simulate complex structures.
Not by using computer simulation,
but by connecting a bunch of math
with,
with springs.
Okay, to study the vibration of buildings,
bridges, for example.
And that is when,
when you have some mass,
represented by a math matrix,
and the stiffness of the springs,
represented by the stiffness matrix.
And people used to solve these equations by hand,
until about the 1940s,
when finally there are electronic computers,
when people start to solve these equations using computers.
And they are now able to solve huge equations,
coming from structures.
But they still use the words,
math matrix and stiffness matrix,
to represent the discretization
of what is multiplied on the time derivative term,
and what is multiplied,
to get the,
multiplied on the,
on the state.
And what you can imagine is that,
if you have a wave equation,
so instead of a first order derivative on t,
you have a second order derivative on t.
Right, so then instead of heat equation,
you get wave equation.
Everything follows exactly the same way.
This is because it doesn't matter in the,
in what we pull out and pull in,
the derivatives and integrals.
It doesn't matter if the time derivative is first order or second order.
If it's a wave equation,
we have exactly the same math matrix,
exactly the same stiffness matrix.
Except for the dU dt becomes d square U,
dt square.
Right.
Then we can use,
just a different method of time integration for the ODE,
to solve the wave equation.