So let's first discuss what is iterative methods for solving steady state equations.
Okay, so iterative methods have been developed pretty early.
They are developed because of a simple reason that when the matrices get large enough,
it is very hard to solve these matrix equations.
And again, going back to the age when people don't even have computers,
they started using iterative methods.
So let's say somebody wants to solve a structural equation,
and they want to figure out what are the deformations of various elements under a certain load.
How they do it?
Is how they started doing it.
When the matrix is very large, when the system is too large to be solved using Gauss elimination.
Remember at that time there is no computer, so if you want to do Gauss elimination,
there is a huge amount of numbers just to be calculated by hand.
So what they started doing is to relax, is to move one element at a time.
And figure out.
If you go through all the elements, just make each individual element into equilibrium.
If you go around a few times, although the entire system may not achieve equilibrium yet,
but it may be a good enough approximation if you iteratively make individual elements into equilibrium.
So that is one way of thinking about iterative methods.
Okay, so I'm going to introduce iterative methods using the Poisson's equation.
So if you have a Poisson's equation, du squared dx squared equal to f.
And if you are not allowed to use any matrix solvers, let's say, let's assume.
Okay, or let's see, let's say, how do you solve this equation?
One way to solve this equation if you are not allowed to use backslash or any matrix solvers,
is to solve an unsteady equation instead.
Right?
So I can change this equation, I can change my problem.
To that, I want to solve the heat equation, du dt equal to partial square u partial x squared.
And what should I add on top of that?
If I solve this equation, what I get at the end is, so let's say boundary condition again, very simple.
u z.
u zero equal to u one equal to zero.
And again, u zero equal to u one equal to zero.
So if I solve this equation, I will get zero at the end.
Right?
So how should I modify this equation so that I get a solution to the equation I want to solve at the end?
Minus f, right?
So if I solve this equation, and assume myself,
that the solution procedure is stable,
then at the end, when I converge to a steady state solution,
the du dt term becomes smaller and smaller as I iterate, because of stability.
What I get at the end is a solution to the equation I want to solve.
Right?
And remember, by solving this unsteady equation,
we don't actually have to solve any matrix equations.
Even if, let's say, we discretize this equation no matter using finite,
so okay, so let's not talk about finite element yet.
So let's talk about finite difference.
If we talk about finite difference, what we get is du dt, where u is a vector,
being equal to matrix A times u minus this f,
where A is a finite difference approximation to the second-order derivative.
Right?
So,
in order to solve this equation, for example, using forward Euler or Runge-Kaede method,
I don't need to solve a matrix equation for A.
What do I need?
How do I use this matrix if I solve this equation with forward Euler?
Multiplication, right.
I only, iterating method in general only requires explicit operation with the matrix,
for example, multiplication.
Okay, multiplication is a very,
it's basically sometimes the only requirement you have on the matrix
in order to apply iterative methods.
So, for example, if I want forward Euler,
I'm going to be saying u of k plus 1 minus u k divided by delta t
is equal to A times u k minus f.
Right, so k here is the time step.
And it makes sense for me to choose delta t to be as large as this method is stable,
so that I converge to a steady state as fast as possible.
So,
so you can,
I'm going to be talking about Jacobi iteration method next,
and you're going to see a very close analogy to the forward Euler method of solving an unsteady equation,
the iterative method of solving the steady state equation.
And in general, you can think of iterative method as a generalization
of solving an unsteady version of the equation,
so that you obtain a steady state equation,
a steady state solution,
when k here goes to infinity.
k can be considered as a pseudo time,
in this case,
or a iteration number,
rigorously.
Okay.
So the first type of iterative method we are going to be talking about is the Jacobi iteration method.
So the Jacobi iteration method starts with,
so all the iteration methods start with a matrix.
So we want to look at the solution A u equal to b.
Okay, so,
so iterative methods for solving linear equations start with the linear equation.
They don't usually start with the,
the PDE.
But sometimes you have to use the properties of the PDE.
Okay.
So, but Jacobi iteration requires just the matrix.
So you have A u equal to b.
That can be,
that equation can be split into many parts.
When the matrix A can be split into a diagonal part of A,
plus the lower diagonal part of A,
plus upper diagonal part of A.
And Jacobi iteration works very well if the Jacobi,
if the diagonal part of A is dominant,
at least not zero.
The diagonal part of A cannot be zero,
and it works,
the larger the diagonal part of A is compared to the off diagonal parts,
the better.
The better usually Jacobi iteration is going to work.
Because how it works is when you have a splitting that way,
you can write the equation as d times u plus l times u plus u times u.
So this u and this u is different.
This u is the upper diagonal part,
and this u is the solution equal to b.
And what we do is,
we move all the off diagonal components to the right hand side.
And thereby getting d u is equal to b minus l u minus u u.
So up to now this is just an algebraic manipulation.
But then something is going to be different.
I'm going to put a superscript,
k plus,
k plus one on here,
and a superscript k over here.
So this is saying that,
okay, first of all,
let's look at what if I started with the correct solution.
What if I have an initial guess?
So u zero is called the initial guess.
In general, it is just a guess.
It doesn't have to be accurate at all.
But if you started with the correct solution,
if u zero is equal to u,
what is u one going to be?