It can have some small problems in some rare cases.
One of the rare cases is what we call an inversed shockwave.
So in our solution, we have seen a shockwave that looks like this.
So this is u, this is x, this is u equal to 0.
We have seen a shockwave like that.
So the inverse shockwave is a shockwave that goes the other way.
So if this is 0, it's negative here, jumps to positive here, and then that.
So let's take an example.
So this is x equal to 0, and this is u equal to 1, this is u equal to minus 1.
Okay, clear?
What this solution is?
It's basically a Heaviside function.
Minus 1 when x is less than 1, plus 1 when x is greater than 1.
Okay.
If you put this initial condition in the solver we just did, the solution here is going to
stay stationary.
D U D T is going to be 0 for a solution like this.
And why is D U D T equal to 0?
The only reason D U D T can be 0 is all the F interfaces are the same, right?
Because D U D T is the difference between two fluxes.
So if all the flux values are the same, then D U D T is of course 0.
Why am I claiming f is going to be the same?
Because, well, other than the two boundary conditions.
So let's see if we get rid of the boundary conditions.
So why is f interface the same?
That is because all the f's are the same.
All the f's are the same because u is either 1 or minus 1.
So when you square this solution u, either 1 or minus 1 is going to get you half.
So all of this vector f is going to be half.
Therefore, all of this f interface is going to be half.
Therefore, du dt is going to be 0.
Any questions?
No, right?
So let's say here we don't have a periodic domain.
So let's, for example, if we have a periodic domain, it goes like that.
Then the solution is going to stay the same forever, right?
We have one normal shock over here and one inverted shock over here.
But the inverted shock should not stay there.
It should not exist.
So let me answer the question why it should not exist.
Why this shock wave should exist and why this shock wave should not exist.
Mathematically, there is nothing that says this shock wave shouldn't exist, actually.
If you look at the differential equation, look at, I mean, when shock wave exists,
you shouldn't look at the differential form of the equation.
You should look at the integral form, right?
If you look at the integral form, there is nothing that says that this shock wave shouldn't exist.
A stationary solution is a perfectly valid solution.
But you will never see that perfectly valid mathematical solution in real world.
Because the differential equation we are solving is just an approximation of the limit of a viscous process as that viscosity goes to 0.
Okay, again, it's a limit of...
A differential equation with very, very small viscosity.
The Burgess equation we are solving, we actually don't want to solve the Burgess equation.
So let me just write as f of u.
We want to solve the Burgess equation with the infinitesimal epsilon times the second derivative of u with respect to x.
That's a viscous term.
That's actually why we want numerical viscosity when there is a shock wave, right?
This is the physical viscosity that is there.
We're just taking the limit.
The velocity of epsilon goes to infinity.
Now, if you consider this equation, what is the effect of this epsilon term on the shape of the discontinuities?
Okay, so if you just think of the heat equation, right?
So just don't think about the nonlinear term yet.
Let's just think of the effect of this term.
What is the effect of this term?
It's more of a...
It smoothies out non-smooth features, right?
So actually near discontinuities, this term is going to be infinitely larger in magnitude than the first-order derivative term.
So the effect of this is going to make the shock wave not exactly like this, but like that, right?
So it'll be smoothed out a little bit.
The slope of the shock wave is no longer going to be infinity.
Maybe it's still going to be 10 to the 18.
It's still going to be 10 to the 18.
Maybe the first-order derivative is going to be 10 to the 18 or something.
It's going to be very, very large.
But it's not going to be infinity.
Now, if you look at the xt diagram, and zoom into this region where on the left hand side it's minus 1, on the right hand side, let's zoom into this region.
At the left hand side, the characteristics is minus 1 going this way.
At the positive side, it's going that way.
But in the middle, there is a very tiny range.
Okay.
of solutions that are between minus 1 and 1, what direction would the
characteristic go within that very very small range? So what you're going to see
in a physical solution is there is going to be a fan out there. There is
going to be a fan out there that comes from an infinitesimal small range of
solutions. Okay, so that's why when you look at a solution later on, you will no
longer see an inverse shock lying over there, the solution should become like
that after a while. Does it make sense? So if you, if you cut the solution over here,
the solution over here is still minus 1, the solution here is still plus 1,
okay? So if you cut this both over here, the solution over here is still minus 1,
So if you cut this both over here, the solution over here is still minus 1,
But in between, there is going to be a wider and wider range of solutions that lies in between 0 and 1.
So this slope is going to be shallower and shallower.
Numerically, we are not going to capture that with the upwind scheme.
We just code it up.
But the fix is not very difficult.
Do you all understand what the problem is here?
What is the problem we are dealing with here?
So the solution to this is to always compute a numerical flux that is physical.
And by physical here, there is a way to look at the entropy of the solution here.
So even if you have an infinitesimal amount of viscosity, the entropy should not decrease.
It should increase.
Well, if you have a solution that is unique.
If you have an inverse shock, the entropy actually would decrease.
So let me say what is the non-physical solution.
Non-physical solution is you have an inverse shock sitting over here.
And the characteristics emerges out of the discontinuity.
So the entropy condition says that whenever you have a discontinuity,
for example, this one, characteristics can disappear.
And when things disappear, it's an increase of entropy.
But you cannot have any new information coming out of nowhere, coming out of a discontinuity, for example.
So you should not have any new characteristics emerging out of a discontinuity.
Okay, so things can dissipate, can disappear, but it cannot come out of nowhere.
So that's the so-called entropy condition we need to satisfy.
When we are using a numerical method to solve the differential equation.
Okay, so this is not allowed.
And this is okay.