And boundary condition in general is difficult.
So today let me illustrate some of the very basic ways to handle boundary conditions
for equations that exhibit wave-like behaviors.
Okay.
We're going to start talking about boundary conditions for scalar PDs.
And the simplest type of equation we want to look at.
And again, we are looking at the linear advecting equation.
Since we started talking about conservation laws,
this is simply an equation of a scalar conservation law with f of u, the flux, equal to what?
What is the flux in this equation?
If a conservation law, conservation...
Oops.
If a conservation law is written as partial u, partial t, plus partial f of u, partial x, equal to zero,
what is the flux in this case?
Yes?
Big u, lower u?
Big u times small u, right.
It's a linear function of u.
What is the characteristic speed of this equation?
Big u?
Hmm?
It's just a big u.
Remember the characteristics?
They are df d small u, which in this case is equal to big u, exactly.
And if there are shocks, what is the speed of the shock?
Or speed of discontinuity?
The speed of discontinuity is equal to f on the left minus f on the right divided by u on the left minus u on the right.
Or it's delta f over delta u.
In this case, if f is a linear function of u, what is delta f over delta u?
Again, it's u, exactly.
So all the wave and all the discontinuity, everything propagates at the same speed u.
Now, in this case, what is the proper way of setting the boundary condition?
So let's consider two cases.
First case, u, big u, greater than zero.
And we no longer consider an infinite domain or p.
We consider a periodic domain.
We consider the domain between zero and l.
So this is x.
This is u.
Imagine I have an initial condition like that.
What is a proper way?
So let me first ask the hard question.
What is a proper way to specify the boundary condition at l?
At x equal to l.
Remember when big u is equal to zero, everything continues.
And the solution, discontinuous solution, the arc propagates towards the right with the positive speed.
So can I set a derivative boundary condition at x equal to l?
Let's say u equal to zero, can I do that?
No, I can't.
So what are the type of proper boundary conditions I can set on x equal to l?
Can I set a Newman boundary condition?
Can I set the derivative boundary condition?
derivative of u at l equal to zero, for example, would it allow the waves to probably propagate
out of the domain, maintaining the shape? No. No boundary condition can be set at x equal to l.
So this is something I want to emphasize, is you should not set any boundary conditions.
So no boundary condition at x equal to l. Okay. At x equal to zero, on the other hand,
you can set Dirichlet boundary condition, you can set Newman boundary condition, you can do
a lot of things, you have a lot of flexibility at x equal to zero, right? So at x equal to zero,
you are free to choose
a
boundary condition. Your boundary condition, bc is boundary condition. All right. And the
second case, you should be able to use the same logic, is u less than zero, what is the
proper boundary condition at x equal to zero? In this case, the wave propagates towards
left, right? So what is the proper boundary condition for the, at the boundary where the
wave is coming out of the domain?
No boundary condition. No boundary condition, right. So there shouldn't be any boundary
condition if the waves are going out of the domain over here, because information goes
from inside the domain to outside the domain. There shouldn't be any information coming
from outside the domain. And the boundary condition is supplementary, it's basically
information coming from the boundary, from outside the boundary. That's what boundary
condition gives you.
It gives you information from outside the boundary. So here, at x equal to L, we are
free to choose boundary condition. So these are a scalar conservation law, a scalar and
linear vector equation. So we can generalize, of course. I won't write it down here, but
like we can generalize. For a nonlinear PDE, if we have a characteristic of x equal to
zero, then we can generalize. We can generalize. For a nonlinear PDE, if we have a characteristic
that are not a constant U. How does the bounded condition work? It works the
similar way. It just depends on locally is the characteristics going towards
outside the domain or it is coming into the domain. Okay so in that case if you
code up a solver which you will do to solve a nonlinear scalar
conservation equation, I mean nonlinear scalar conservation law,
the proper boundary condition to set at the boundary may be time dependent.
So you have to adapt your bounded condition, actually adapt whether
you should set a boundary condition or not depending on the solution U at the
boundary. If the solution U at the boundary at that moment turns out to be
allowing the characteristics to go into the domain that is when you should set a
bounded condition. When the solution U is such that when you evaluate the F of that
U, you find the solution to be going, you find the characteristics to be going out
of the domain, then you know this is not the right time to set a bounded
condition. The bounded condition, what we mean by bounded condition is you're
setting the values
at a particular spatial location for a range of time. Here you need to, for
example, if you set a Dirichlet bounded condition, you need to set the
value of U at x equals 0 for a range of t. The bounded condition you should give
is a function of t only. For example you can set it with a constant 0 is a
perfectly fine function of t or you can set it to be linearly increasing as a
function of t either way. For example if you set a function of t as a function of t,
for example if you set this to be equal to 0, you would see the wave going towards the
right and whatever is left over, so you see the same shape adverting towards the
right and the range becomes 0 once the wave shifts away from x equal to 0. What
if you set this to be a function of t? What if you set it to be equal to just t,
for example?
The value increases as time increases and you're gonna see a wave that is not
0 but you're gonna see the same wave going towards the right but on the left
side, it'll be that... because the value here... here is from the
bounded condition at an earlier time. Here is from the bounded condition at a later
time and here is from the bounded condition even at a later time. How do you do
stability analysis when the domain is not periodic? So first of all you need to
make sure the discretization if you don't have any boundary condition if it
is periodic it is stable once you have the boundary condition you can do when
human stability analysis anymore you need to look at the matrix again so you
need to form the matrix and look at whether the matrix has any eigenvalues
or that let so I'm just going to slightly touch what you have to do if
you have multiple dimensions okay a multiple dimensions you have a domain so
let's say this is Omega and you have when you do characteristic speed
analysis for example if you have partial u partial u partial T plus this case you
has to be a vector right or let me just write it clearly big UX partial u
partial X plus big u y partial u partial
y partial u partial t and then you can write this as a vector so you can write
this as a vector so you can write this as a vector so you can write this as a vector
if you write this big u vector equal to ux u y then the same equation can be
written as partial u partial t plus u vector dot with the gradient of u equal
to 0 right and in this case the flux is a vector is equal to the ux u and u y of
u which is equal to this big u times small u
this is my flux and of course you can still analyze the characteristics the
characteristics is partial f partial u which in this case is this vector big u
now you have a vector big you that goes that has a that you can draw on the
boundary and in this case it's again it's very clear which part of the
boundary
is appropriate for specifying boundary condition can tell me in this case which
part of the boundary is appropriate for specifying boundary condition yes the
part where the velocity goes into the domain so I can specify boundary
condition over here here maybe not and over here so this is the range where it
is appropriate to specify the boundary condition and the rest of the boundary no
boundary conditions all right any questions this is the scalar equation
case which generalizes to the system of equation case