Okay, so now I defined my basis functions that way. Let's start to derive the linear form.
So I'm going to represent my solution u h being a linear combination of i goes from 1 to n, n being the number of interior grid points of u i times phi i.
Okay, phi i are the piecewise linear and continuous functions I was just visualizing.
So what we need is the bilinear form on a h and v.
And here I can substitute v by any of these basis functions v j has to be equal to l of v j.
If I have this satisfied, then I can make any linear combination.
Let's say.
Of these equalities and get the same equality for any v in the same linear space.
Okay, so for j goes from 1 to n.
So the left-hand side, I can use the bilinearity of u and expand this by pulling the summation and all the coefficients out.
So it's going to be a summation.
Over i u i times a of phi i and phi j is equal to l of phi j.
Right.
So then our tasks, our task is to evaluate this and call this a i j and evaluate this and call this b j.
Then what I get is the matrix a times my solution u u 1.
And then what I get is the matrix a times my solution u u 1.
And then what I get is the matrix a times my solution u u n.
Is going to be equal to the vector b.
That allows me to solve for the linear combination coefficients u i.
Which turns out to be the height of these basis functions.
Right.
Questions so far?
Okay.
Now let's figure out how to evaluate these a i j's.
So.
Phi.
So a i j is equal to a of phi i phi j.
Right.
Which is equal to the integral of the domain of the gradient of phi i dot product with the gradient of phi j.
Again, this is going to be a very sparse matrix.
Because let's just go back into MATLAB.
And.
Visualize this one.
And let's hold on.
Let's make a v also equal to the zeros.
Let's make a v into an arbitrary other.
Let's say a hundred is equal to one.
Let's do another choice of.
Of this with v.
Okay.
Right.
So I get two basis functions.
One is the blue one.
One is the yellow one.
So if i and j are equal to one hundred and two hundred.
What is a i j in that case?
It's going to be zero because if we look at the formula for a i j.
It is the integral integral of the entire domain of the gradient of phi i times the gradient of phi j.
And the gradient of phi i and phi j has no overlap in the areas where they are non-zero.
Okay.
So for example the yellow one is only non-zero in.
One two three four five elements.
Five of these triangles.
The blue one is less clear.
Maybe six.
Yeah.
Blue one I think is six.
But like they are.
Each one is only going to be non-zero in the triangles that shares that particular point.
Okay.
So now it's a little bit more complex than the one dimensional case.
In one dimensional case.
And a basic function is only non-zero in two areas.
Okay.
So.
It's going to be non-zero in two elements.
Right.
Left and right.
In this case each basis function is going to be non-zero in a small number of elements.
But that small number is no longer going to be a constant.
It depends on.
The yellow one has five.
The blue one has six.
Okay.
So but anyway.
These are going to be equal to.
Integration.
It's going to be.
Split that up into summation of elements.
So elements.
So.
Let's say k.
In the elements.
Integration over omega k.
So omega k is the kth triangle.
Gradient phi i.
Gradient phi j dx.
This is good because.
Over each element.
Both.
Phi i and phi j are linear.
So.
The.
Gradient phi i and the gradient phi j.
They are.
What.
Constant.
Right.
So.
Then I can write this as.
Summation of k in the elements.
Gradient of phi i.
In that element.
With gradient of phi j.
Times the area.
Of that element k.
Okay.
So.
But.
Up to now.
All calculus.
Is.
Gone.
Only thing left is.
Geometry.
And algebra.
Alright.