Let's see another equation.
Let's say we want to solve the Helmholtz equation.
This is the equation we want to solve.
So what we do next is, OK, what's the boundary condition, and then what is the template?
Now this is the template.
Now we just compare, OK?
We're trying to fit this template with the other equation.
What do we have?
We don't have all of those terms, right?
And all we have now is C is equal to the same thing.
And then K, the wave number, we have that in the absorption term.
But that's it.
But these are now C and A and F are the only terms that we have.
Now all these things in the template are just...
OK.
So this is standing for some value, but for you, depending on the physics you are trying
to solve, they could mean one thing or another.
So this C, for example, for chemical problems, it's concentration.
For heat transfer problem, I mean, it's diffusion coefficient.
For heat transfer problems, it's convection coefficient.
If you were solving a one-dimensional elasticity stress analysis problem, that's the same thing.
So this is a two-dimensional elasticity stress analysis problem.
That would be your Young's modulus.
They can stand for different things.
But still you just find it and fill the template.
So it's really something like this, right?
You have things you want to fit in into a template and you're like, oh, where do I fit
in this?
Put this here.
like it might not fit.
So how can now we do this?
Yeah, so for example, forget that we're working with
equations.
I just want to fit this circle and find them which are
upside-down rectangular into those open areas.
You need to cut, exactly.
So you need to cut.
So this is for the cutting.
This will fit in.
But the other ones, you need to cut them and modify them.
So let's see an equation where we have to do this.
We want to do, let's say, Voxel's equation for finance.
Now, this is the equation that we want to solve.
Then we will compare it with a template.
And this is the template that we have.
Now, we can easily see that we don't have those terms.
We don't have the math terms.
We don't have a source term.
dA is 1.
Now, what is the problem with using C is equal to half sigma
squared x squared?
So C looks like it could be half sigma squared x squared,
right?
Beneficial for that.
For x, right?
They're going to have a . . .
So what's the derivative with respect to x out of sigma squared x squared?
Because it's going to be inside the divergence.
So when that happens, what can I do?
OK, I'm going to do this.
But then, since I have this extra derivative, I will move it, right?
This term, sigma squared x, that comes out of this term here, next to last.
That comes out of the .
I will just move it and try to fit it somewhere else.
So I'm going to move it.
I'm going to move it.
And balance it so that the end of the rate is the same.
I convert it to a form that I understand, and it's the same format.
Then there are more than one ways to do this.
I could have put it there, or I could also have moved it to the source term.
But in any case, it is in a format that at first doesn't look like x squared.
Just try to convert it into a familiar form and fit that.
OK.
Is that clear?
So there was this .
I don't know if you guys heard about this, but there was this mathematician who lost
his job.
And he goes to the fire department to get a job.
And he had an interview.
And the first question was, assume you are working in a certain neighborhood and one
house is on fire.
What do you do?
And he says, OK, I'm going to call 911.
And until I get that number, I'm going to call 911.
And I'm going to tell 911.
And until I get help, I'm going to find a hydrant and do what I can do in the meantime.
And I'm like, okay, that's a very good answer.
Second question.
You are working in a neighborhood.
Everything is fine, no problem.
What do you do?
First, I put one house on fire.
After that, it's a social problem, right?
You know how to handle that question.
So a lot of times in mathematical modeling, when things look strange,
the first thing is can I rewrite this in a form that is familiar?
Then I know how to handle it.
So that's how these templates work.
So when you are working with this, then you need to sometimes access the derivatives of certain quantities.
So here are some operators in console to give you derivatives.
If the solution field was u, for example,
then ux, uy, uz will give you special derivatives.
And then you can add them.
It will give you a second derivative, mixed derivative.
If you are on surfaces, we have this solution field uppercase T special direction variable,
which will give you a tangential derivative on boundaries.
Now, that only works if you are differentiating the solution field.
But other times,
you want to differentiate other quantities.
For example, this would mean that for a heat transfer problem,
these operators will work if you are differentiating temperature.
But if you are trying to differentiate flux or another quantity, they don't work.
But the operators which work irrespective of the quantity you are using
are this d, quantity, comma, what you are differentiating it against with operators.
So those give you partial derivatives of any quantity with respect to x, y, z.
Or r of z in a cis-emitter component.
And time.
In the reference manual, you can find more differentiation operators.
So you will use this operator sometimes when you need access to the derivatives.
Yes?
Can we get normal derivatives the same way?
Is that going to happen or something?
I have to check.
I don't think it's available.
Yeah.
Because mostly the way you can do is,
the way I evaluate normal derivatives is,
the derivative itself is available.
And the unit outward normal on boundaries is also available.
So you can take a dope product.
Yeah.
But the tangential derivatives are important because a lot of times,
you might want to, if you have a surface, some equation only valid on the surface.
If you have surface chemistry, for example, you might want to have access to the tangential derivatives.
But yeah, you get the derivative and you can dot multiply them with a unit outward normal.
Other questions?
Is it clear so far?