Sounds great. Let's solve it a little bit more.
Solve it for 0.5.
Plot it again.
Ah, something bad is happening, huh?
So let's take a look at the last solution.
bar at u at the end.
No.
Okay, u end and the column.
Yes. So this is my solution.
So I do see I get something similar to what I'm supposed to get, right?
So as things run into the shock wave, this part further flattens and I get a shock wave over here.
But what about this?
I have artificially generated oscillations.
Right. So why is that the case?
So let's analyze the central flux scheme.
A little bit more.
So first of all, one obvious thing we see is that
it doesn't seem to be conserving or decreasing the
what's called the total variation, right?
So we have the total variation. We see it is diminishing all the time.
But over this region, when these oscillations are created,
you get a lot of total variation.
Out of nothing, right?
So this is a problem we need to address.
And this is a particular problem about the central flux scheme.
And the reason for that is we can do a different analysis
about the central flux scheme
where the du bar dt
is equal to 1 over delta x.
times f that's basically
half of f plus f plus 1 minus
oh, this is f plus f minus 1, right?
minus half of f plus f plus 1.
So this f gets cancelled with this f here.
So we have 1 over delta x.
Actually, 1 over 2 delta x.
f minus 1 minus f plus 1.
And we're going to find the central difference scheme
both in finite difference and in finite volume.
They conserve a certain high order statistics.
Let me tell you what that means in a moment.
And f is equal to
the Burgers flux evaluated at u bar i.
So f is equal to
the Burgers flux evaluated at
u bar of i minus 1 square
minus u bar i plus 1 square.
Right?
So this is the
after all the substitution of the Burgers equation
and the central flux,
what we get.
Alright?
So,
a trick I'm going to do is
I'm going to multiply
both sides of the equation by
u i bar square.
So the left hand side is
u i bar square times d u i bar d t.
The right hand side of the equation is
1 over 2 delta x
half of u bar i minus 1 square
u bar i square.
Right?
Because I multiplied u bar i square on both sides.
Minus u bar i square
u bar i plus 1 square.
A little bit interesting,
but let's make it a little bit more obvious.
So the left hand side is d d t,
a third of d d t.
u bar cube i d t.
The right hand side is
the difference between
u i minus 1
u i 4 delta x
minus u i square
u i plus 1 square
over 4 delta x.
Okay.
So,
this number is exactly
this number with index i
shifted by 1.
Which means
if I sum up
the left hand side
over a range of i's,
if I take the d d t
of a summation of i
goes from i 0 to i 1
of u i cube over 3,
this is going to
equal to only two numbers.
All the interiors get cancelled.
This is only
would it be equal to
u of i 0 minus 1 u i 0
bar square bar square over 4 delta x
minus u i 1 square bar
u i 1 plus 1 square bar 4 delta x.
We don't get any summation
on the right hand side
because all the interiors
once gets cancelled.
Okay.
So,
if you look at here,
I have to do,
I have to multiply
by this u i square
because otherwise
if I multiply by u i,
for example,
I wouldn't get any cancellation
on the right hand side.
The u i bar cube
satisfy a certain conservation law
discreetly.
Right.
So,
which means
if you look at a large range,
if you look at a large range of i's,
if you look at a range of spatial indices,
the total amount of u cubed
over these indices
stays conserved.
The time derivative is
only equal to what goes in.
It's equal to a certain flux
that goes in from the left of the domain
minus a certain flux that
goes out on the right of the domain.
That is a problem
because
it does not allow
the solution to diminish.
Remember if we have,
for example,
a simplest way to analyze this
is in a periodic domain
where we don't have any boundaries.
So,
if I have periodic domain
and if the summation over all,
over all indices,
then I can find out
the time derivative
of u i,
bar cubed over three
is equal to zero
because all these things cancel
over a periodic domain.
So, I have exact conservation of
u i cubed summed over the entire domain.
And that simply does not allow my solution
to become zero as it should
when I have a Berger's equation,
when I have everything runs into a shockwave.
We can run this further, right?
So, we already have something running to the shockwave.
This thing should diminish.
The shockwave should become zero.
It's smaller and smaller.
But if we run it further and further,
we can see that it would never diminish
because the cube is conserved.
So, let's run over five.
Ah, failure.
Okay.
The discrete has probably become very bad.
Plot this.
Right.
So, we get wilder and wilder oscillations
because the equation has to conserve
the total amount of u cubed.
All right.
So, it doesn't allow the solution
to become a nice form like this,
which it should be.
Right. So, what we get is...
Ah...
What we get is...
So, while what we should get is this
after a while.
So, starting from the initial state,
starting from the initial condition,
we should get this.
But actually, we are getting something like this
because we have to conserve
the total amount of u cubed.