I want to still make it more even more obvious that like do not use one of the
differential forms when you have shock waves okay so so we just compute the
speed of the shock wave to be essentially FL minus fu so this is FL is
f of ul fu is f of f if you are so this is ul minus you are right so so instead
of D F D U this is Delta F over Delta U
and so let's try it on the burgers equation we already know that on the
burgers equation
we have the speed of the shock wave being ul plus you are over 2 right so
that's what we derived but there is a contradiction here if we multiply both
sides of the equation by U and Monday and many manipulate using your calculus
skills we can get something pretty interesting
so let's try it again.
So first of all, the time derivative term, there is a classical trick that actually is
very useful in stability analysis, they call nonlinear stability analysis of differential
equations, that when you multiply u with du dt, it is actually equal to partial t of u
squared over 2.
So this is the same kind of chain rule we use to go back and forth between the differential,
between the primitive form and conservative form of the Berger's equation.
There is a similar trick you can use on the spatial derivative term.
u times du squared over dx squared is equal to something times du squared over dx squared.
du cubed over dx.
And that's something, let me derive it.
So du cubed dx is equal to the derivative of u times u squared over dx.
And now you expand it.
This is equal to u times dx.
And then you multiply that by the derivative of u times u squared over dx squared.
So you expand it.
You can do it once again.
And then we're going to do the same thing.
Now that we've done this exercise, we're going to do the same thing.
u squared dx plus u squared times du dx and the same thing can be represented as
derivative of u times u times u which can be represented as u squared times du
dx times 3 right so you can move one of the u out move the you can move this u
you can move this times this out of the differential and you can move this and
this out of the differential and you can move this and this out of the
differential so that that like works like that so so the same so the same
thing is equal to 3 times this or it is
again enseñ statistik Geschichte und volume um gesehen um so if you can see
equal to this plus this. Okay so let me let me do a derivation. So u squared
times partial u partial x is going to be equal to one third of partial u cubed
partial x. And now we substitute this into that we get partial u cubed
partial x is equal to u times partial u squared partial x plus one third of
partial u cubed partial x which means u times partial u squared partial x is
equal to two-third of partial u cubed partial x. So this is going to be two
third. So this is the whole derivation of this. Right okay so with
this we can do the derivation. So we can do the derivation of this. So we can do the derivation of this. Right okay so with
this two substituted into this equation what we have and of course we have over
two here so this is going to be a one-third if we divide by two here. So
this equation therefore becomes partial partial t of half u square plus partial
partial x of a third of u cubed equal to zero.
Right, so those two are one third of partial u squared partial x plus one and
that is u squared is equal to partial t over two. So we have to Pass more Kanad yes
but we have
so we have the S grilling out of the logic bag then the other side too this
is called parallel values and we given a slight one this S g going to be
partial t but yes also called partial t times partial t so the Brock equation
here in because there's a three times partial here so now we can see it and
that we decrease the mean by sin you oyster.
We actually want to be
You enidious know that bitch answer how to which far so understand when I'material
3 half power divided by 3.
Right?
So this is nothing but writing the same equation,
Berger's equation, into a different form
by doing a bunch of manipulations of the derivatives.
But with that alternative way of writing down the conservation law,
we have a different shock speed.
The shock speed in this case is going to be equal to delta FV over delta V.
So it's going to be equal to delta of this 2V,
3 over 2 over 3,
divided by 2V,
divided by delta V,
which is different from half of UL plus UR.
So these two only agree when UL and UR are infinitesimally close to each other,
and they don't agree over a finite range of UL and UR.
It's not obvious, but you can do the derivation and see that.
So what does that mean is,
what does that mean is,
all this derivation we did down here
only hold over an infinitesimal range UL and UR.
All the derivation we did only holds for the differential form of the equation.
It does not hold for the conservative form,
for the integral form of the equation.
So when you choose a discretization,
we can never base the discretization
on some differential manipulation.
For example, the Taylor series.
Right?
The Taylor series is a manipulation of the differential form of the equation.
And that is no longer a reliable way of
manipulating the differential equation into another form to solve it.
Right?
We should rely on something else.
And this lecture, I'm just going to show you what that something else is.