So we have two cell averages here, we have two cell averages over here, we want
to reconstruct the solution here and the reconstruction cannot be linear.
So u of i plus half left is equal to a nonlinear function, has to be
equal to a nonlinear function of ui and ui minus 1. And u of i plus half right
has to be a nonlinear function of ui plus 1 and ui plus 2. So the question
here is how do we achieve that nonlinearity? What kind of nonlinearity
is it required. And through this process we can also see an aspect of the order
barrier theorem, why we need a nonlinear scheme.
So let's start with a nonlinear scheme.
start to look at several cases, several very representative cases of how we want to reconstruct.
So this is U, this is Ui, this is Ui plus 1, and this is Ui plus 2, and this is a case
where the solution is very smooth locally.
The solution increases almost in a linear fashion.
This is when you represent the, if you compute the cell averages of a linear function, this
is what you're going to get.
So in this case, this special case 1 is Ui minus Ui minus 1 is equal to Ui plus 1 minus
Ui is equal to Ui plus 2 minus Ui plus 1.
So this is a special case.
We are considering.
In this case, second order accuracy means that when we perform a reconstruction of the
solution, if we reconstruct the solution of a linear equation, to get second order accuracy,
we need an exact reconstruction.
So first order accuracy means.
If we reconstruct a constant function, we should get the exact reconstruction.
And second order accuracy means if we reconstruct a linear function.
Doing Taylor series analysis, linear function has the second order derivative, third order
derivative, everything else is equal to zero.
So if we want a second order accurate reconstruction, we need to have exactly, I want my U at i plus
half left over.
Right?
All right.
Both equal to Ui plus Ui plus 1 over 2.
So that's my first case.
All right.
The second case is a completely different scenario.
This is a scenario where my Ui is a local maximum.
When this is a local maximum, can somebody tell me what should the value of Ui plus half
left?
What is the constraint on this value?
Can the value be a half?
Yes.
Okay.
All right.
So the value of Ui plus half is higher than Ui itself.
If we want to preserve monotonicity of the total variation.
Remember that monotonicity of total variation is not creating new extremers.
If you create a new extremer, if you push the maximum, if you push the local maximum
of the function above Ui, which is the current local maximum.
Okay.
Now we are increasing the total variation.
Right?
Yes?
It should be the value of Ui?
Yes.
So in this case, the reconstructed value should actually be the value of Ui.
All right.
Okay.
So here we start to get a sense of why this value is greater than the value of Ui.
Right?
Yeah.
So you can see that the value of Ui is greater than the value of Ui.
Okay.
So in this case, the value of Ui is greater than the value of Ui.
Right?
So why the reconstruction cannot be linear?
Because in the first case, in case one, in order to get this value and in order to represent
this value, in order to represent Ui, let me use blue to distinguish the two cases,
in order to get Ui plus R half at left, only as a function of Ui and Ui minus one.
How can we perform that representation?
Remember here interpolation in the linear function is the same as extrapolation.
Right?
So we can use Ui minus half of Ui minus Ui minus one.
Okay.
So here let me rewrite it a little bit.
So if I divide this by delta x, that's the slope.
And if I multiply that by delta x over two, it is saying that I am computing the slope
using Ui and Ui minus one here.
And I'm applying the same slope over this range, which is delta x.
I think it's plus.
Sorry.
Right?
So this is the slope.
And delta x over two is this range.
So the width here is delta x over two.
So this is the slope times the x distance, which gets me this.
And if I add that to Ui, that's exactly this.
Add that to Ui, that's exactly the value at the interface.
Does it make sense?
So here we are constructing, reconstructing a solution using Ui minus one.
If Ui minus one increases or decreases, the value here is going to change.
While in the other case, when the function is not smooth, when the function achieves a local extrema,
the reconstructed value should not depend on Ui plus one.
Yes, we are trying to reconstruct the value of U at the interfaces and left and right
interfaces, so that we can apply the Godanoff scheme to compute the flux at the interface.
So once we can have U left and U right at the interface, applying what we studied in
the last lecture is going to give us a numerical flux.
So what we have is the following.
In the first case, when the solution is locally smooth, we have Ui plus an influence from the next cell.
In the other case, when the solution is not smooth, we have just the Ui without influence from the last cell.
So we can write that, we can write the second case as plus the same slope.
So this is, all right, exactly what I can write.
Voltage, delta x times 0, right, and this is like times 1, right.
So this 1 or 0 is like turning on and off a slope indicator.
That's something we call a limiter, right.
0 or 1, right? And this phi is equal to 1 for smooth solution and 0 for local
extremer. So how do we construct this phi? So phi is going to be a sensor of whether
the solution is locally smooth or not. So phi depends on what? The best way to sense
whether this is a local extremer or locally smooth.
Is the ratio between this and this. If the ratio, in this case, the ratio is equal to
1. When the ratio is equal to 1, we know it's locally a very linear function. In the other
case, the ratio is what? It's negative, right? So again, depends on the ratio, let me call
R.
R being Ui plus 1 minus Ui divided by Ui minus Ui minus 1. So again, this is equal to 1 if
R is equal to 1. And for local extremers, either minimal or maximum, R is going to be
less than 0. Okay. So the flux limiter.
The flux limiter is this phi of R. And let's figure out what are the conditions that this
phi of R has to satisfy in order for us to have a second order monotonic scheme. Yes?
Which one should be Ui minus 1 here?
The first term before that.
Here?
Yeah.
Here should be Ui because this value is Ui, right? Let me use this.
Okay.
So this is the black color here. This value is Ui, right? And the distance between Ui
and this appropriate reconstruction is delta x over 2 times the slope. Right? So this value
is Ui plus the slope times delta x over 2. Right? Yes?
So for this V?
Yeah.
So for this V function, like it's not all inclusive. Like should it just be R greater
than 0 for smooth solution?
So we have a proposal that should phi of R be greater than 0 for smooth solutions?
Or sorry, phi of R equal to 1 for all R greater than 0? Is that what you are proposing?
Yes.
Okay. So we have a proposal that phi looks like that.
Okay.
So we have a proposal that phi has a function of R. So this is 0, this is 1. We have a proposal
that is 0 here and 1 here.
Okay. We'll take a look at if the proposal works. All right? Okay. So let's figure out
the appropriate...
Let's first figure out if this part of the proposal is equal to 0.
Okay.
So we have the part of the proposal works. Yes?
In the green figure, the cell to the left is it equal to Ui plus 1 as well?
Oh, sorry. The left should be Ui minus 1. Yeah.
So they don't have to be...
They don't have to be equal. Yeah. They only need to be both smaller than Ui. Okay. So
let's first figure out the left side of this proposal works. The proposal is phi should
be just equal to 0 when I have this part of the data.
Okay.
whenever r is less than zero.
Does that give us the desired solution
whenever we have a local extrema?
Yes, right?
Whenever we have a local extrema,
we want a piecewise constant reconstruction
because any slope is going to give us new extremas.
Any non-zero slope is going to make
the reconstructed solution go higher or lower
than the existing extrema.
So this part of the proposal is correct.
So phi of r should be exactly equal to zero
whenever r is less than zero.
Okay, let's then figure out
if the positive part of this proposal works.