The way to satisfy the entropy condition is a contribution by a person called Godunov.
So he first constructed a numerical way to calculate the flux,
which is a modification to the upwind flux
that guarantees that the solution satisfies the entropy condition.
So what is his solution?
His solution, it's still, remember like in the upwind scheme,
we are thinking of approximating the solution as piecewise constant.
Here we still do the same.
So here we are explicitly considering that we are storing the solution averages,
but then we are reconstructing the solution as piecewise constants.
So let's say this is our numerical solution.
Okay, so this is my...
domain, this is my u, and this is delta x,
2 delta x, etc. So in between every two grid points, the solution is a constant.
Of course, that's a first-order approximation, right? So we are going to get a first-order scheme.
But like this is going to get us at least a
entropy satisfying solution, and then we can talk about later how to extend that to second order and higher order.
So with that piecewise constant approximation,
we want to compute the flux at every interface.
Now,
computing the flux is an interesting question because
previously, we are considering that if this whole thing
stays as a shockwave,
what is going to be the flux?
Right?
So we have been using upwind, and to determine which side is upwind, we are using the speed of a shockwave,
which implicitly assumes that this discontinuity is going to stay as a discontinuity after some time.
In reality, we just looked at it is no longer the case,
right? In some cases, this discontinuity is going to be no longer discontinuity,
almost immediately after you start evolving in time.
So, good enough insights is really from that.
It's really
analyzing for each, every interface, analyzing
is that discontinuity going to be, if you solve the equation exactly,
for infinitesimal amount of time, is that discontinuity still going to be a discontinuity after a while, after this infinitesimal amount of time?
And then,
after that analysis, you should be figuring out,
after this infinitesimal amount of time, what is the flux over there?
I'm just going to give you an example of the same
thing we did before. So that is, if we have two cells, one cell being minus one, the other cell being plus one,
okay, and the cell interface lies over here.
According to the upwind flux,
the speed is equal to zero. So it's okay to either choose the flux on the right or flux at the left.
Either way, the flux is going to be half of u squared, which is equal to half.
But, use good enough insight.
What is going to be the flux at this point after an infinitesimal amount of time?
Think of that.
What is the shape of the function after an infinitesimal amount of time, if you are solving the equation exactly?
So you should, after infinitesimal amount of time, you should have an infinitesimal range of solutions
between minus one and one that goes linearly. That's right. Now, what is the flux at
the interface
after infinitesimal amount of time?
Zero!
That's right. Why is it zero? Because the value of the function,
at this point, is going to become zero very soon, right?
It'll stay zero for a while.
And so the correct way to say the flux at this particular interface is the flux is equal to zero, not half.
It's not, you shouldn't choose either the left side flux nor the right side flux. It is zero.
Zero is the right flux to choose at this point.
So, of course, this is a special case.
What is the Moore general case? The Moore general case is exactly thinking like that.
If you solve, if you
analytically solve the differential equation
in a very tiny region around the discontinuity for a very tiny amount of time,
what is going to be the flux value? What is going to be the solution value at that discontinuity, at that, or not discontinuity, at this
location where the discontinuity is at t equal to zero, but maybe not
after a small amount of time. And then figure out the flux of that u value.
Right?
There are many different cases.
For example, if I have a discontinuity originally like that, and it has advected towards the right,
I become like this.
Then I should choose f of u left as my flux, right?
If I have the flux towards the right, I become like this. I should choose f of u left as my flux. Right?
If I have the flux towards the right, I become like this. Then I should choose f of u left as my flux. Right?
if I have a discontinuity like this,
and after a while it stays as a discontinuity
but advected towards the left,
then my correct f at this point is f of u right.
Do we agree?
Okay.
And there are other cases if originally I have a discontinuity.
I mean, we always originally have a discontinuity
if we approximate the solution as piecewise constant.
But later on, it becomes no longer a discontinuity.
Let's say it goes like this.
So it no longer becomes a discontinuity,
but it goes towards the left or towards the right.
I still should be having f of u right.
And if I originally have a discontinuity
and it becomes no longer a discontinuity
but advects towards the right,
I still want to use f.
So I choose f of u left.
And the very last case is I have a discontinuity in the beginning
and the discontinuity becomes like that.
While the right hand side of the solution goes towards the right,
the left side of the solution goes towards the left.
Then I should choose f of u,
the particular value of u that stays stationary.
Okay.
Do we see all these cases?
Yes?
The final case is when the left and right are equal but opposite sides.
The last case is when the left and right have different characteristic speeds
and they go towards different directions.
They don't have to have equal value.
The minus 1, 1 case is a special example.
But even if you have minus 2, 1,
you're still going to have the same problem.
You still compute the wrong flux
if you just use r.1.
So the first case is the discontinuity.
The discontinuity crosses the horizontal axis.
Oh, yeah, okay.
So for Burke's equation, that's right.
For Burke's equation,
because my characteristic speed df is equal to u,
yeah, that's right,
it only changes sign when u changes sign.
So for Burke's equation, this would only happen if
the value of the solution is positive on i plus 2.
So we just let u choose here to get the solution of way back from wherever
which is fta where the one-eighth?
We get 2, 2, 2x.
And the solution, i, 0x
equals feet at in a want and
it can't just satisfied when it's sorry.
Well, that's true.
But this is not wholly true.
No, that's not true.
It should go from negative to positive as u increases, right?
Yeah, that's right.
So df du has to go from, let's say 0, from negative to positive, which means f has a
watt over here, has a local maximum over here, right?
So if you look at f, it has a local maximum over here, and the value we choose to evaluate
in this particular u is actually the maximum of f, is the local maximum of f at this location.
Do you get it?
Like, this is actually...
Okay.
So this is max of f for u that is greater than ul and less than ur.