partial square u partial x is approximated by the finite difference
operator ui plus 1 plus ui minus 1 minus 2 ui divided by delta x square. And then
we worked out the truncation error and if you remember we wrote down ui plus 1
over delta x square ui minus 1 over delta x square and the minus 2 ui over
delta x square and minus partial square u partial x square. So this formula if I
put a plus over here is the error of that approximation. Right so this is
equal to tau
and how do we figure out how large or how small tau is? We did an expansion
over Taylor series. Right we expanded what is the term that contains ui. So for
example this is just ui this is also just a ui this is minus 2 ui over delta x
square this is 0 so that cancel out to be 0.
So this is minus 2 ui over delta x square this is 0 so that cancel out to be 0. So that cancel out to be 0.
We also have a ui prime part which is the first derivative and that turns out
to be that and this turns out to be minus that. There is no square because
one of the squares cancel out and 0 0 we get 0. And so we also use Taylor series
to expand this part this part this is also going to be 0 this is
going to be just itself and we also get 0 and this one we also get 0 and only
in the in this term we get something that is proportional to delta x to the
fourth. That means our approximation error I think sorry delta x to the fourth
also divided by delta x square which gets to delta x square right that means
our approximation error is equal to delta x squared. So this is our approximation error.
is we write it as big O times delta x to the fourth to the second sorry to the
second because the fourth cancels with the second. What this big O notation
means is that as delta x goes to 0 the rate of decay of this truncation error
is delta x squared.
Okay this means this is equal to a constant let me write down as c2 times x
squared plus maybe another constant times delta x cubed plus maybe another
constant times delta x fourth etc. But we don't really care that much about c3 c4
etc. because when delta x is small enough all of these we call high-order terms is
going to be negligible.
Compared to the delta x squared term right. So if you look at this truncation
error we'd like usually to plot it in a log-log plot. In this log-log plot the x
axis is our delta x. The y-axis let's say here we used to denote the truncation
error tau.
Okay and let's say our delta x is 1 over here is 0.1 over here is 0.01 over here
10 to the minus 4 over here actually 3 over here 10 to the minus 4 over here 10
to the minus 5 over here. If when delta x is equal to 1 the truncation error is
over here.
When delta x decreases to 0.1 maybe the truncation error is over here but at
some point
tau is going to decay when delta x is small enough.
Tau is going to decay like delta x squared. That rate of decay in a log-log
plot
what would it look like? What is going to be the slope? It's going to be 2. Yes
which means let's say if the decay the correct decay
rate starts from here then when delta x becomes 0.01 what is going to be the
error? What is going to be tau? So if you go over a factor of 10 over here you
should go over two factors of 10 in the y-axis right so you should get to here.
So your decay rate should be like that.
All right. So that is that is the correct line for tau
being Big-O delta x squared
Okay.
A similar analysis can be used to look at the solution error
and for example you are a project
you
compare a numerical solution with analytical solution. And the difference
the difference between analytical and numerical solution can also be
quantified in a similar way as you refine your grid. And if for example you
know your scheme its second order and your solution is second order, then as
you refine the grid, as you increase the n decrease the delta x, you should find
your solution error to decay in that rate. And if you are careful you should
actually plot it using MATLAB and see if the slope is actually 2. If your slope
is 1, that means you probably have a bug somewhere that makes your scheme not
really second order. It's going to be a first order scheme.
So that's the first order scheme.
Alright, for example, an example of a first order scheme can be seen as
discretizing the first order derivative. Let me say the most intuitive
way to discretize it is ui plus 1 minus ui divided by delta x. I mean one of the
intuitive way to discretize it. Now if you look at the
ability to discretize a derivative, the first order derivative is actually 1 for the derivative, so it's not 2 for the derivative. So if you look at the
approximation error, we have ui minus ui over delta x plus ui plus 1 over delta x,
and we subtract this numerical approximation from the analytical
derivative it tries to approximate. This is equal to tau. We do Taylor series and
this term is just itself. This term is ui over delta x, plus ui over times delta x
divided by delta x. So nothing. just a ui prime. Alright and we also have
a second order derivative. It is going to be half like 2 factorial which is 2
delta x times ui double prime. and plus
...
and we subtract all the Vid przygot Anyways, the nulls, theals and the putims, all are the same.
Delta x squared over 6, that's 3 factorial ui third derivative, etc.
And here is 0.
Any questions about the Taylor series of ui plus 1?
And I'm writing down very quickly, but once you start going into this class,
you should be able to do Taylor series analysis as quickly.
Once you exercise it, it becomes really natural.
This is 0, this is just a minus ui prime, so this is at xi, and 0, 0, etc.
So if you add them together, look at tau, the first term cancels, 0, as it should be.
The second term cancels, 0, as it should be.
The third term no longer cancels.
So that is going to be the leading term.
The leading term in the truncation error.
That is ui double prime times half of second derivative of u.
Alright, so in this case, my tau is all what?
Just delta x, no square.
Alright.
And if you look over here, if I have a truncation error that decays like delta x,
what should I have?
If I have truncation error decay like delta x, I should have a line that is of slope 1.
If it's here, then as you decrease by a factor of 10, you should become,
the tau should also decay by a factor of 10.
So you should get a line that is shallower than the red line.
Question?
If you approximated ddx,
you did a good job.
Yeah.
If you were estimating ui plus 1 minus ui minus 1 by 2 delta x,
wouldn't you get more cancellation if you decrease it out?
That's a good point.
Right.
So the question is, if I discretize this using, instead of ui plus 1 and ui,
if I approximate using ui plus 1,
if I approximate using ui plus 1 and ui,
then I divide by 2 delta x.
If you do the Taylor series again, it's a little bit more involved.
You're going to find I'm also going to cancel a u delta x term.
I'm going to get discretization error that is proportional to delta x squared.
You're right.
The exercise is left at home.
All right.
So, yeah.
If you want second order scheme in your project, for example,
this is probably what you should be using.