Now I want to spend the last little time discussing what we can do with non-Numan
boundary conditions, what's called the natural boundary condition. So natural
boundary condition is quite interesting because it's something unique to finite
element. We don't have this infinite volume or finite difference. It turns out
what if I have a boundary condition that is du dx at 0 equal to 0? Okay, I still
have u1 equal to 0 being Dirichlet boundary condition. So I have
N on the left and Dirichlet on the right.
So that is, I'm looking for solutions like that. On the left has to be flat and on the right it has to be equal to 0.
I'm looking for these kind of solutions. So let's use the Poisson's
equation as an example. So how should I deal with this kind of boundary conditions?
It turns out I don't need to do anything for this boundary condition.
That's why it is called a natural boundary condition.
What do I mean by I don't need to do anything? So to parameterize a function
like this, I need to define my x u to be all the functions f within a Sobolev
space and f1 is equal to 0. So I only need to enforce the right-hand side
boundary condition.
Okay, and I'm going to define my x v to be the same as x u. So what happens is
that when I derive the weak form, the weak form is going to be integration of
a and b. v times the second order derivative of x plus a and b f times v.
Δ had b times 2 buses because all those Totals are in Koblenz.
So when Iع perform it with my partииo an the on the first term we no longer
because because we no longer have you Ovi to be equal to 0 on the left side
boundary we have to start considering the boundary terms at the left. It's no
longer going to be the same as what we have before. so when we integrate by
parts we get V times the
derivative of u at so so when x equal to 1 we get when when x equal to 1 V is
equal to 0 so this is gone we only have this equal to 0 we have a minus sign
here minus the integration of partial V partial X partial u partial X DX plus
integration of F times V equal to 0 right okay so here this is what becomes
very interesting this has to be satisfied for any V whose value at the
left boundary can be anything right and in order for me to satisfy this for any
V
this becomes 0 so so so for the solution u to satisfy the weak form for any V
that doesn't have to be 0 which can be anything at X equal to 0
right so this becomes 0 so so for the solution u to satisfy the weak form for
we have to have partial u partial X at 0 to be 0 so the bond the condition of
the derivative of u at the F-bond is equal to 0 comes naturally from the weak
form okay so that's why we call it a natural bond the condition it naturally
falls out of the weak form now perhaps we have a question
now perhaps we have a question
What if I want to enforce a Newman boundary condition that is not exactly equal to 0?
What if I want it to be 1?
How can I design it?
Does it still come naturally out of the weak form?
I can still make it come out of the weak form by modifying one term.
The term I need to modify is this.
So what if I set this not to be 0, but if I remove the 0 and add another term, that is v at 0.
Remember, we just discussed that the linear functional doesn't have to be the integral of a function times v.
It can also be.
The value of v at a particular point.
So in this case, what if I set the linear functional to be the summation of an integral with a known function and the value of v at a boundary?
What turns out to be is that we are going to have a v of 0 here.
And now v can be anything at 0.
Because the weak form has to be satisfied for any v within xv, which can be anything at x equal to 0.
So for this to be equal to 0, we have to do the same thing.
So if I do this, the derivative of u at x has to be, in this case, minus 1.
And of course, if I want the derivative to be plus 1, I just set this to be negative v.
And I have a negative v.
If I want the derivative to be 0.5, then it's negative 0.5 of v.
So by modifying just the weak form a little bit,
particularly the right-hand side of the weak form, which is the linear functional a little bit,
we can have the boundary condition naturally satisfied.
Remember, this is very different from the Dirichlet boundary condition.
The Dirichlet boundary condition, we actually modify the space of xu.
And we also reduce the dimension of the space xv to satisfy the boundary condition.
We actually force the solution u a priori.
And we also reduce the dimension of the space xv to satisfy that boundary condition.
Any possible solution that is in the space has to satisfy the Dirichlet boundary condition.
But for the Newman boundary condition, it's natural.
We only modify the weak form a little bit.
And it turns out the boundary condition is going to be naturally satisfied once the weak form is satisfied.
So these are two types of strategies for enforcing boundary conditions in finite element.
Yes, so I already got the weak form.
There is no problem.
No violation to the Poisson.
I mean, this is assuming.
So I can derive the weak form from the Poisson's equation.
Because if any solution satisfies the Poisson's equation, it also satisfies the weak form.
It's just the other is not true.
So if I have a function that satisfies the weak form, it doesn't have to correspond to any particular Poisson's equation.
I mean, if you try to derive it, you get something that is not a function on the right-hand side.
So I went through this procedure to derive the weak form.
It's just the boundary condition is going to fall out as an additional term on the right-hand side.
You can still do the same derivation.
You can still integrate by parts.
And we are still going to get the same form.
It's just that if we have a non-zero boundary condition, then this boundary term becomes something non-trivial.