So we're going to look at these equations individually, but before that, let's take MATLAB
and look at the evolution, the behavior of this equation as we draw it.
So do you see the fonts clearly enough?
Do you see what I'm typing clearly enough?
Okay.
So first of all, I need two parameters, u and kappa.
So this is to help you understand the behavior of this equation when the right-hand side
f is equal to zero.
So let's look at our first case when u is equal to zero and kappa, let's say, is equal
to one.
Okay.
So let's look at it.
Let's look at this, the behavior of this equation.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to ask one of you to come over here and draw a particular
initial condition on the screen.
And this is going to demonstrate how the solution is going to evolve as a function of time.
So initial condition is t equal to zero.
And after you draw the solution, you just draw it from the left to the right or from
the right to the left.
And this is periodic.
So the domain is periodic.
Whatever is here should also be here.
And you should see how the solution evolves as time increases.
So can I have somebody, brave person, to come over here to draw an initial condition?
Please.
Thank you.
What's your name again?
Happy.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thank you, Happy.
And the solution you draw, what happens?
Can somebody describe to me what happens after Happy draws the initial condition?
It's smooth out.
It's smoothies out very quickly.
Right.
So the solution, Happy went, Happy was drawing the solution.
Some people was smiling, laughing because he was drawing a very jaggy, very non-smooth
solution.
And as soon as he pulls the hand, you see the solution is going to be smooth.
And you can see that the solution is going to be smooth.
Right.
So the hand, as time starts to increase, the solution becomes smooth very, very fast.
Okay.
Very good.
So, Happy, I want to ask you a question.
If I don't want that to happen, if I want the solution to decrease, to smooth out in
a much slower rate.
Okay.
What should I change over here?
I think you should lower the value of kappa.
I should lower the value of kappa.
That's exactly right.
So because kappa is multiplied on this second order derivative term, and we are going to
see later, it controls how much diffusion or how fast, how strong this term is in smoothing
out the solution.
All right.
So let's change it dramatically.
By a factor of a thousand.
And can somebody else come and draw a different solution, initial condition, and see how the
effect is?
Please.
I almost got a cramps here.
So I'm going to start with this one.
Okay.
So this is the initial condition.
I'm going to start with this one.
So I'm going to start with this one.
And then I'm going to start with this one.
So this is a 커 exploit in terms of the spiritual URL system.
So I'm going talk about Lao's
Star using .
Sorry.
This is a
sou Yummy egg the
oy
Or the
Great.
Yes.
I mean, I can open this today.
I can open it and I can have the following.
It says,
And that's what I'm doing.
and if you look very carefully you should see for example if you observe
here you should see the solution is smoothed out very very slowly right so
this here it is increasing slowly and here for example the peak is going to be
dropping very very slowly so that's the effect of copper when you make copper
smaller the strength of the diffusion gets a lot smaller so let's analyze that
using what's called a Fourier series