So when you are talking about verification and validation, there are two topics, right?
There is the validation, which is, are we solving, is the equation actually representing the physics?
This isn't something a software can decide or a numerical system can decide.
It's something you decide based on your experiments or something physical.
Whereas the verification is, am I solving that equation accurately?
So basically you go from a physical model to a mathematical model to a numerical solution or to an analytical solution.
So the verification part is, did I make the right transition from the physical model to a PDE or a mathematical model?
But what we focus now is the verification, the last step.
And that we compare with exact solution, with benchmark solutions.
But what we can do is when you don't have exact solution, when you don't have experimental data,
there is this thing called the method of manufactured solution.
It's pretty cool. Actually, I was very psyched when I first found out about it when I was doing the grad school project.
Google is method of manufactured solution.
There is a big document from the Sandia National Lab that explains every detail.
They use it for their nuclear testing.
So the idea is maybe this equation is nonlinear or coupled, so you don't really know how to derive an exact solution.
You assume a solution.
You start with a solution.
You start with an assumed solution.
You're going to say, hey, let's assume U is equal to this in terms of F and in terms of whatever space and time.
You make that assumption.
Now, plug it into the ODE.
What do you get?
Into the PDE.
If you plug it into the PDE, you get a source term.
And then if you evaluate that solution at the boundaries, you get boundary condition.
And if you evaluate that at T is equal to zero, you get initial conditions.
Now, what you are going to ask is, if I now take this source term, initial condition,
and boundary condition that I derived out of the assumed solution and put it into my numerical solver,
will it give me back the assumed solution?
Do you get the idea?
And here, the only thing is that you should assume uniqueness of your solution, right?
If within a certain boundary condition and initial condition you can have multiple solutions, this may not work.
But otherwise, it's a very convenient way of testing.
So, the homework problem is in the booklet, Comsolve Mathematics, you got that on Monday, maybe?
Let me give you a booklet with exercises.
There, there is this exercise, the BASMA exercise, where in that case, you are going to solve it using the Newton physics interface.
There in the booklet, it gives detailed instruction about the BASMA exercise.
There is also a section about using the electric current and the heat transfer.
And then for the coupling, to use the electromagnetic heat source to model this.
Your homework is to do that problem using equation-based modeling.
Using PDs directly, not using heat transfer or multi-physics.
So first, you know you can click on this physics and see what the equation is.
So find the equations from there and the boundary conditions from that booklet.
Then, solve it using PD interface.
So basically, two PDs and then you need to couple them.
So you need to know what the equation for the joule heating is and add it.
Is the exercise clear?
Yes?
Could you send us a soft copy of the booklet? I don't think everyone has got it.
Okay, if you haven't, I will ask Mian to send you a soft copy for everyone.
Who wants a hard copy?
The last guy there, great to be signed.
Any questions? Anything all clear?
Alright, thank you for coming.
Do you all write your names in here?
Do you sign in?
Anybody who didn't sign in?
Check your names here.