Let's look at the Burgess equation for example.
Burgess. My speed of the shock would be equal to
ul squared over 2 minus ur squared over 2 ul minus ur.
And this only works for the Burgess equation, but if you express the difference in squares
in terms of the summation times the difference, right?
So, we are going to get a half of ul plus ur, ul minus ur.
And ul minus ur, that cancels out. That gives me ul plus ur over 2.
So, again, it only works for Burgess equation. Don't generalize this.
It's that the speed of the discontinuity is equal to the average between the speed
of the shock and the speed of the shock.
So, again, if you look at the characteristics on the left and the speed of the characteristics
on the right, okay?
So, for example, again, if you look at here, the merge of the two shocks, you basically
get the speed of the shock equal to the average between the characteristics to the left and
the characteristics to the right.
So, the characteristics to the left has a positive.
The speed goes to the right.
The one at the right has a negative speed almost of the same magnitude.
The result?
The discontinuity moving at zero speed, going vertical.
All right.
So, why is it curved?
Why does it change slope?
Yes?
Yes.
U and UR can change.
For example, when you are at this segment, okay, UL is the same as over here, but UR
has changed.
In the lower part of this shock, UR is this value almost equal to zero.
But once you go up to here, UR has changed to this very negative region.
That is why the shock...
Suddenly turned.
Over here, the slope of the speed of the shock is equal to the average between the speed
on the left and a zero speed.
While here, it is the average between a positive one and a negative one.
That's how it changes speed.
All right.
I can also manufacture cases that is...
That have the shock turn continuously.
Okay.
So, how do I do that?
How should I manufacture a case where the shock is going to turn continuously?
Let me do that.
Let me manufacture a shock that...
I get a shock.
Okay.
So, this shock should move towards the right because both left and right has positive values.
But let me do something like this.
Okay.
So, I can see the shock is going to turn.
And see how the shock is going to turn.
Initially, I'm sure it is going to move towards the right because if you look at the solution
on both on the left and right of the shock wave, it is positive, right?
But you can see also these characteristics.
They are less than the positive.
Okay.
They are less deep and they are going to run into the shock wave in no time.
And as they run into the shock wave, the value immediately at the right of the shock
wave is going to change.
It is going to become higher or lower.
Okay.
Can you say it again?
The top part is moving right.
Okay.
The bottom part is moving towards the left.
Yeah.
I'm just focusing on the discontinuity here.
So, initially, I have this discontinuity that moves towards the right.
But as these continuous characteristics run into the shock, the value immediately on the
right of the curve is going to change almost continuously.
I mean, to the right of the shock is going to change almost continuously.
Right.
So, if you zoom in into here.
Okay.
So, you see this one runs into the shock.
Another one runs into the shock.
I mean, these characteristics go into the shock everywhere.
As things run into the shock, the value at the right side of the shock changes.
It decreases, right?
Originally, this is almost yellow.
Now, it's almost blue.
And as the value on the right of the shock changes, the value on the left side of the
shock decreases.
The speed of the shock should decrease.
So, that's why you see this obvious curvature towards the left.
Does it make sense?
And now, I don't know what's going to happen because the left side is also starting to
decrease.
So, I think both sides, so both value at the left and value at the right is decreasing.
That makes the whole curve a little bit more difficult.
That makes the whole shock should curve towards the left pretty fast.
I think pretty soon, so right now, the positive side is still a little bit higher than the
negative side.
It has a larger magnitude as the negative side, but pretty soon, we'll have a zero speed.
Right now, it's probably have a zero speed now.
It's almost vertical.
And the shock is going to turn towards the left as the negative side wins over the positive
side.
All right.
Any questions?
So, when we first derive the speed of the shock, how do we know there will be a shock
when the UL and UR doesn't change?
I think we assume they don't change value and then calculate the speed of the shock.
Yes.
We assumed the left and right doesn't change value over infinitesimal time step.
Right?
Yeah.
And...
So, the question is a very good question is what is...
Why is it appropriate to do that?
So, let me stop the MATLAB and going to do some more analysis.
All right.
Right.
So, let's go back to our original derivation.
So, the question is a really good one.
So, why is it appropriate to assume UL and UR doesn't change much over the...
The delta T?
The answer is it does change, but the magnitude of influence of that change to what I'm deriving
here is at a higher order in terms of DT than what I've written down here.
So, imagine UR and UL are also changing in a continuous fashion.
So, UR instead of at this value, it changes.
At this value, it increases to over here.
UL instead of this value, it has maybe decreased to over here.
So, the question is what is the contribution to the change of the integral from this part
and this part compared to this original box I was drawing here?
Okay.
So, the contribution of this part and this part is on the order of DT times epsilon,
where DT...
The reason I said DT is the magnitude of this change is on the order of DT.
And so, the vertical side of this box is on the order of DT.
The horizontal side of the box is on the order of epsilon.
The contribution to this is going to be epsilon times UL.
Okay.
So, this is going to be epsilon times DT over DT, which is epsilon.
This is why I chose this interval, A and B, to be a very small interval around the shock.
Particularly how small I can choose it is determined by the fact that the shock cannot move outside of the interval.
So, the size of epsilon should also be proportional to DT.
That is why the contribution of this changing UL and UR to the difference is on the order of DT squared.
And here, to the derivative is on the order of DT.
So, when you choose DT to be small enough, this contribution can be safely ignored.