We're trying to decide.
We have a couple of integral equation problems,
short ones that we're going to talk about in evening settings,
which we'll do next week.
And then there's also, I guess, some discussion
about the final project.
I don't know if you all have opinions about this.
You should express them to Professor Lang.
We will take them under advisement.
But we'll try to.
I work very mindful of not packing a lot of work
in the last week of classes.
So for today, I'm going to talk about quadrature
and the video from yesterday's Monday's lecture.
It's getting there.
I have to compress it, I guess, before I can post it.
But it should be up by tomorrow.
I just have a little video for this one, too.
The camera is running at the moment.
I haven't officially asked for any of you
for signed disclosures.
I don't think anybody showed up.
Do you show up?
I don't think anybody showed up on the video.
Your voice might play on the video.
If you have objections to this,
certainly feel free to mention them to me
and we'll figure out something.
Okay, so we're going to talk about numerical quadrature.
And many of you may have seen Gauss.
How many of you have used Gauss quadrature?
How many of you have seen an analysis
of how the formulas are derived?
A couple.
Okay, so for those of you...
For those of you who have seen this before,
this won't be new.
And for those who haven't seen it before,
I guess it won't be,
which is not exactly a very informative statement,
but there it is.
So we're going to...
I'm going to go through a little bit of it.
And the reason we're going to talk about quadrature
and the ways in which you derive quadrature formulas
is it will really lead into the next lecture,
which is how you take these ideas from quadrature,
which you may or may not have seen before,
and how you can use them to develop
the next lecture.
So I'm going to go through a little bit of it.
And I'm going to talk about the idea of quadrature,
which you may or may not have seen before.
So you can use them to actually come up with methods
for solving integral equations.
And give you a method that's really extraordinarily effective
in two space dimensions.
And doesn't necessarily generalize that easily
to three dimensions,
although there have been some recent improvements in that.
So part of the reason we're talking about quadrature
is to fill in some background in case you're missing it,
but partly because it's going to lead us right into
a very effective way,
one of the most effective ways of solving it,
is to use the idea of integral equations
in two space dimensions.
All right, so what do we mean by quadrature?
And that is we're going to approximate an integral
by, which is of course just the area under a curve,
and we want to do it with some formula.
That is we're going to use values of a function and weights.
So if you're doing an integral from zero to one,
which we'll probably do,
we don't have the integral in that because
I'm just going to integrate this out to the x,
and I'm trying to get the area under the curve.
I'm doing one.
And I'm going to approximate it with this box card
of height f and I'm evaluating it at x.
So that's not a very difficult quadrature scheme.
It's an approximation,
and we can come up with better approximations,
and the obvious one is, well,
if it doesn't work to approximate your function
with one box card, maybe two will,
box cards would be better.
So I'm sure all of you have learned this in calculus
that it would be better to use more box cards
when you do the Rubin sum.
But before we do that, let's talk a little bit about
just this box card and what it's accurate for.
So the extraordinary thing about that one box card
is of course it's exact for a function that's a constant
on the integral 0 to 1.
It's also exact for anything that's a constant or a linear.
So it's actually a single point quadrature scheme.
It's a lot more powerful than you think it is,
and in fact it's more powerful than if I use one point on the x.
So suppose I look at these functions that are linear,
and I want to get the area of the curve,
and I have three choices about how to approximate it.
I could use a point at the beginning of the integral,
so I could use f of 0,
or I could use, for that same linear function,
f of 1.
And what can I say immediately about both these methods?
Do they work if the function is constant?
If f of x equals a constant,
are these formulas exact?
All three.
So we can sometimes call this one the midpoint,
and both of these are called endpoint methods.
The endpoint methods are exact.
If it's constant, what if f of x is equal to a x plus a p?
Which of these formulas are exact?
The midpoint and the endpoint?
Midpoint only.
So we could sometimes, if we want to be formal about it,
we could say the endpoint methods are good for polynomials of order 0,
and the midpoint methods are good for polynomials of order 0 and order 1.
That, in fact, that idea, the simple idea,
thinking about what kind of polynomials, functions,
you could exactly integrate the error out of the curve of,
is the heart of everything you're going to learn about quadrature.
So everything else I'm going to tell you is an extension of that idea.
We look at quadrature formulas,
and we're going to ask questions about how high an order of polynomial
we can exactly integrate.
And that's going to tell us some way of comparing these methods.
So in this very simple setting,
we're going to start talking about a lot of things about these polynomials.
But just keep in mind that simple idea.
We're going to try to come up with methods
that can accurately integrate higher and higher order polynomials,
and that's how we're going to assess which method is better and which method is worse.
So, if we want a method that's more accurate than the midpoint method,
if our function is not a constant or a linear function,
it's not a zero-th or first-order polynomial,
then we could break it up into two box cards.
Does that accurately integrate a higher-order polynomial?
That is, if I use two box cards in the midpoint method,
can I exactly integrate any quadratic?
What about if I use, instead of the midpoints for these two box cards,
what if I used endpoints?
Would that exactly integrate any quadratic?
So, what about a linear function?
If I use two box cards, will the midpoint method exactly integrate
a zero-th or first-order polynomial?
If it's a straight line and I write this up into two box cards,
will the midpoint method still integrate the linear case?
Exactly.
What about if I use the endpoint method?
Will it integrate a linear one exactly?
No.
So, breaking up into more box cards, more sections,
doesn't necessarily get you a higher-order polynomial
unless you try to arrange for it.
So, that's another thing you're going to worry about,
which is, what should we do if we use lots of points?
And just using equal weights on the two points may not be the best thing to do,
although, surprisingly,
in important cases, it is, in fact, the best thing to do.
All right.
So, but this is going to be our general problem.
We're going to imagine, well, we can evaluate the function.
Presumably, you can evaluate the function.
You don't want to evaluate the function too much
because the function may be expensive to evaluate.
It might be the result of some complicated calculation you're doing.
It may be something as simple as evaluating 1 over r, 1 over distance.
But usually, you want to minimize the number of evaluations you have to do.
And get the best answer you can get.
And you have two degrees of freedom.
And I want to keep in mind these two degrees of freedom.
So, we have, well, I should say, two types of degrees of freedom.
The first type is
the weights for each point.
For each of the box charts, how much do you weight that point?
And the second type is where to put the points.
And in looking at the midpoints of these two endpoint methods,
we pick the weight of 1.
We only have one point.
So, weights, the freedom to pick weights doesn't really come into it.
But we can see already, even in a one point quadrature scheme,
that degree of freedom of where to put the weights,
where to put them, that's an important degree of freedom.
And if we use something like a midpoint rule
for each one of a set, a collection of n boxes,
we would put 1 over n as the weights, all weights being the same.
And each of the test points would be in the center of each of those box charts.
So, that's a general midpoint formula.
And you might ask the question, is that the best thing to do?
Could you put the points in different locations?
Could you use different weights?
So, if I have an endpoint scheme, how many degrees of freedom do I have?
So, I've got n box charts.
I can pick n points to, n places to put the,
I can make the box charts thicker, thinner, so I can put the points anywhere.
I've got n points to place.
What about the weights?
Do I have n degrees of freedom in the weights?
How many degrees of freedom do I have?
What do I know about the weights?
They all have to sum to 1.
Why do they have to sum to 1?
Suppose f of x were a constant of 1.
Then that formula should produce exactly the right integral,
which would be 1.
So, that's why the weights have to sum to 1.
But that idea doesn't exist.
The idea that the weights have to sum to 1,
when you think about that, yeah, of course,
because it's got to integrate the constant function exactly,
but that's like saying the weights have to be such that the 0th order polynomial gets integrated exactly.
We get another condition on the weights,
so that we exactly integrate a constant and a first order polynomial.
So, we're going to think a little bit about that.
So, there are three different methods we could look at.
We could use one method, which is an endpoint method.
We use the beginning of each of these box bars.
A second method, the one we've been looking at mostly,
is a midpoint method.
We pick up points in the middle.
And the third one is sometimes referred to as the trapezoidal rule.
And why is it called the trapezoidal rule?
Because you can't see it here, because it's not clear enough in the picture.
But each of these things are trapezoids.
They're straight line approximations for whatever that function is.
Which is the best one to use?
Is the trapezoidal one better, or the midpoint one?
Midpoint.
Say again?
So, it turns out the midpoint one is better.
The trapezoidal rule is, it's putting a straight line between points.
So, I'm going to draw a picture of that so you can see why.
So, imagine I have a curve like this,
and I deal with the trapezoidal rule,
and I just exaggerate it.
So, these are going to be my trapezoids.
So, I've got two trapezoids.
And I have an error.
For that same curve, what would the midpoint rule do?
I have my two box cards.
What does the midpoint rule do?
It's going to use the point square.
If I use the midpoint rule, what value am I going to use?
A middle.
And I'm going to pick a middle point.
And that means,
my midpoint rule looks like this.
So, by looking at these two pictures,
it should be obvious to you that the midpoint rule is going to be better.
Right?
Is that obvious?
Is the terror smaller?
If I drew a slightly different curve,
could I get a different answer to this question?
Maybe.
If I happen to pick a piecewise constant curve,
my curve is this, the rooftop,
then trapezoidal and midpoint will both get exactly the right answer.
After that?
Alright, so,
it can be a little difficult to decide some of these questions,
even in this simple setting, about error.
And so, we need some more formal methods to think about it.
And it also turns out we need some tricks.
Well, numerical insights.
It will help us actually come up with ideas about where to put points
and how to set weights.
Alright, so,
for the moment, we're going to worry about
a general, positive formula,
where we think of picking the weights
and picking the evaluation points,
and that will give us 2n degrees of freedom.
Where the way you normally think of the weights,
I can double the weights up to sum to 1,
that's a constraint.
And we're going to see if we want,
that's a constraint to make sure that we get the exact answer for a constant.
But it's one of a whole family of constraints.
So, we're going to think about having these 2n degrees of freedom,
but we're going to very quickly see that we're going to need to put some constraints on it
to try to get good accuracy.
So, we're going to pick the evaluation points,
and we're going to pick the weights.
So, how should we do that?
So, we already started talking about the key idea.
What I said was the key idea.
The polynomial.
We are going to say I have this function,
and I'm going to say I can approximate it well with a polynomial up to Lth order.
And what we're going to try to do is to pick the points and the weights,
so that it accurately integrates any polynomial up to as high an order as possible.
So, we can, by picking the points and the weights,
because we have 2n degrees of freedom,
we can actually come up with points and weights
that will exactly integrate any polynomial up to the Lth order,
where the Lth order is 2n minus 1.
Why 2n minus 1?
What does the minus 1 tell you?
So, how many coefficients does an Lth order polynomial have if I write it this way?
Well, because I wrote it from a0 and a1,
all the way to aL.
If you're a programmer and you write software a lot,
you count from 0, then of course you know that's L plus 1 coefficients.
That's where the 1 is coming from.
The Lth is the order, but the number of degrees of freedom is L plus 1.
So, we can get to an Lth order polynomial means we have L plus 1 coefficients
of that polynomial, and that we're going to match to the degrees of freedom
in our quadrature scheme.
So, we have 2n coefficients we have to find,
and that means we can match 2n coefficients of a polynomial,
and that means L plus 1 is equal to 2n, or L equals 2n minus 1.
So, that should be easy.
So, how are we going to do that?
I've got points and weights,
and I want to make sure that we pick the points and the weights,
so we exactly integrate any polynomial of order up to L.
How do I figure out where those points and weights are?
Can I write down a system of equations and solve it?
Can I just go ahead and do that?
We're going to talk about that in a little bit.
But I wanted to say something about the error estimates,
because these methods, when you do this,
doing the midpoint rule with boxcars,
or doing something like this, where you pick the points and weights
to exactly integrate as high an order polynomial as possible,
they have very different convergence properties.
The Gaussian quadrature, or any quadrature scheme,
based on trying to match as high an order polynomial as possible,
has what we call spectral convergence.
So, normally, when you refine a discretization,
you figure, alright, if it's in a cubic order method,
you might expect that if I half the number of the step size in my discretization,
then maybe the error goes down by a factor of 8.
Or maybe I have a second order method,
and in this case the error goes down by a factor of 4.
Or a first order method goes down by a factor of 2.
You have this idea that it is the refinement.
I take the discretization, I use twice as many points,
I get twice as much accuracy,
if it's first order, 4 times as much accuracy if it's second order,
8 times as much accuracy if it's third order.
What do you think you get with Gaussian quadrature?
So, what that formula means, although it's a little hard to tease out from the factorial way,
it's usually, it's formally presented.
It says that for every point I add,
the accuracy increases by a factor of 2.
So, it's not going down like 1 over,
it's not going down linearly or quadratically or cubically with the number of points,
it's going down exponentially fast with the number of points.
So imagine how many, if you want to get 16 digits of accuracy,
2 points gets you 1 digit,
then 3 points gets you 4 digits.
4 points gets you 8 digits.
5 points gets you 16 digits.
When we're talking about these methods,
we're talking about methods that have extraordinary rapid convergence
when they count on certain properties.
And we're going to come back and talk a little bit about what those properties are,
but unfortunately for the integrals,
in this class, they violate the properties for which that's true
in many of the cases, but not all of them.
And we'll look at some important ones that show up in 2D.
Alright, so, let's look at an example.
So, it's, you know, I'm going to take,
alright, what does spectral accuracy mean,
what does it really look like when we're talking about this?
So, I'm taking the sine function,
I'm going to do the sine function and integrate it with a quadrature scheme
because we can exactly integrate the sine function with it all.
I'm going to try to do that in calculus.
And what's true about the sine function?
Why do you think I picked that function?
So, do any of its derivatives go to 0?
Is there any polynomial that,
that exactly describes the sine function?
Now, if it did, then I could differentiate the sine function
a certain number of times,
and at some point the derivatives would go to 0.
But that never happens, right?
If I differentiate the sine function,
and differentiate, I get sine, cosine, sine, cosine, sine, cosine, sine, cosine,
derivative never goes to 0.
So, it's not described exactly by a finite number of polynomials.
And it gives us a chance to look at the convergence properties
of a method for which we actually know the exact number.
So, let's look at the answer.
So, this is the error analysis,
and this is looking at the point,
the log-log plot of error versus number of points.
And if you look at this scheme and say,
well, what happens when I increase the number of points
by an order of magnitude?
What happens to the error in this plot?
So, an order of magnitude increases the number of quadrature points,
meaning I break it up into an order of magnitude and one section,
and an order of magnitude, more evaluations.
How much does the error go down?
Well, you look at it,
an order of magnitude on the bottom curve looks roughly like,
how many orders of magnitude on the side?
So, we're looking at a plot of error versus number of points.
Two looks sort of like,
and that would be a second-order method.
You increase the number of points by a factor of 10,
and the error goes down by a factor of 100.
That seems pretty good.
It means that, you know, with 1,000 points,
10,000 points, we can almost get machine precision.
So, that's not a quadrature scheme.
That was, which of these three methods do you think was the midpoint rule
or the endpoint rule?
Yeah, it turned out it was the midpoint,
because the endpoint rule doesn't have such rapid convergence.
Now, I'll come back if there's time
and talk a little bit about the Taylor series of values,
but I just wanted to make a point about it,
because it's the heart of why the methods that we're using work.
If I do a Taylor series expansion of a function,
as long as it has, it's infinitely continuously differentiable.
So, sine functions are infinitely continuously differentiable.
Then I can write down the Taylor series expansion
for f of x at every point x.
And that means up to a Taylor series residual,
I can write down a polynomial representation of f of x.
And when I do a,
a quadrature scheme that's exact for that polynomial,
it means we'll pick up that order for Taylor series,
but we'll miss out on the remainder term.
And the remainder term for the Taylor series expansion
is this thing that has a coefficient in front of it
that goes like the factorial,
and also is the derivative.
So, looking at this Taylor series expansion, it says,
if we're going to do something that's exact for polynomials,
for progressively higher-order polynomials,
we want something towards the Taylor series
remainder theorem works.
It means we want something that's infinitely differentiable,
and one has to be true about the derivatives.
These derivatives are going off to infinity
as you differentiate more and more and more.
That's not so good.
If they go up, if the derivatives go up faster
than the factorial goes down,
then these methods aren't going to be very good.
So, we want things that are smooth
and for which the derivatives don't go up.
And if we do that, then we get this incredibly rapid convergence,
and then it's worth looking at.
Well, I still need to do this.
I'm going to skip ahead and show you the plot,
and then we'll come back and look at the...
Ah, here.
Alright, so what I showed you in the first plot
was the simple quadrature scheme, the midpoint rule.
I'll come back and do all the slides in a bit,
and I just wanted to show you the result at the end.
Simple quad.
To get to machine precision,
that midpoint rule would take 10,000 points.
For Gaussian quadrature,
in about 11 points,
you can get to machine precision.
So, we're not talking about,
oh, it's two times faster, or it's four times faster.
If you're looking for accuracy close to machine precision,
that is high-accuracy calculations,
you're talking about, instead of having to do
10,000 points with a midpoint rule,
you're talking about doing 11 or 12.
And all you have to do is to figure out
what the good weights and evaluation points are.
And we'll look at those in a little bit,
but I want to go back and talk about how we get there.
So, we have this idea that any smooth function,
infinitely differentiable function,
can be described by a polynomial.
And if we can pick up that polynomial,
then the remainder term is very small,
and the higher the order of the polynomial,
the smaller this remainder term is,
and it goes down really, really fast.
So, how do we do that?
So, we're going to produce this exactness condition,
and we're going to do it on this unit-integral-integral,
just so we have an example here.
We're going to try to exactly integrate a polynomial,
an L-thorough polynomial,
and we're going to try to pick the points and weights
so we exactly integrate that L-thorough polynomial.
And we can use a lot of properties in this integration.
So, let's have a look at this.
I take an L-thorough polynomial,
I write out what that L-thorough polynomial is,
it's this integral from 0 to 1 of a0 plus a1x plus a2x squared, etc.
And I can write it down as this sum of quadrature weights and points.
Remember, we're talking about taking this L-thorough polynomial,
so we have this thing,
PL of x,
on this integral from 0 to 1,
and we're trying to figure out where to put points.
I've got x1 through x sub n.
These are our points.
And then we've also got, for a point xi,
a weight i that we're going to multiply by,
PL of x on it.
And we want to pick out these points and weights.
So when we're looking at the integral from 0 to 1
of PL of x,
dx,
that's exactly equal to this sum from i equals 1 to n
of wi PL of xi.
So we want this to be exact for all polys
up to,
L equals 2n minus 1.
So,
we now need a strategy for figuring out what those are,
and we can start to make headway with that strategy
by just writing down
the polynomial pulled apart into its different, what are called monomens.
So we have the constant monomial,
the first-order monomial, the second-order monomial,
and then all the way to the L-thorough monomial.
And monomial, the mon of n, is the constant.
So the constant there just means there's only one,
you know, if we're talking about the,
an L-thorough monomial,
we're just talking about x to the L.
There's no x to the L minus 1,
x to the L minus 2.
And why should we do that?
Does that help us generate a system of equations for
these points and weights?
Suppose a1 through al were equal to 0.
Does this formula have to work for that polynomial?
It's now a0 times x to the 0th power of 1.
Does this polynomial have to be exact for that?
Yeah, alright. One condition.
I throw away that term, and I throw away all the ones
a2 through a, and a0, and I'm just left with a1x dx.
So that's my polynomial.
I set a0 to 0, and a2 through al to 0.
Does this formula have to be exact for that one?
Yeah, sure.
Because it has to be, this formula has to be exact
for any L-thorough polynomial.
So each of those terms gives us one constraint.
a0, the 0th-order polynomial, the 1st-order polynomial,
the 2nd-order polynomial.
Each of those gives us a constraint
that we can use to figure out the points and weights.
In fact, it gives us exactly the number of constraints we need.
Because we're going to set L equal to 2n minus 1.
So that's a1.
So that means we have 2n minus 1 degrees of freedom.
Or 2n, excuse me, 2n constraints for 2n degrees of freedom.
And then, what we want to be true is that
given this exactness constraint,
we can say then, if we take the monominal,
the x to the L plus 1 monominal,
and take the difference between that,
and integrating the,
with this weights and points,
that that error is going to be something like
the remainder term in the Taylor series expansion.
And so I'm not going to do that too formally here.
It's easy to find in basic textbooks.
But that's the intuition to have in mind.
When we do this, if we match for all the way up to L-thorough polynomials,
what's left over, that remainder term has to be really small.
Right, so, can we do this?
We have 2n degrees of freedom.
We have 2n constraints.
We could just set up the nonlinear system.
Right there it is.
So there's our set of constraints.
And we just have to make sure that the integral of the constant,
the linear term, all the monomials,
that that sum formula works for every single one of those cases.
We have 2n equations in 2n degrees of freedom.
Is that a linear system of equations?
Can we solve that?
What do you think?
I mean, what are our unknowns here?
The ui and x?
Yeah, you've got the points.
What point, where are the points?
And what are the weights?
So it's not a linear system of equations,
because the terms and the equations are products of your unknowns.
This is the nonlinear system of equations.
So what method do you use to solve a nonlinear system of equations?
Fmincon.
Sorry, for those of you who use Math Lab.
I don't know what it is in Mathematica.
It's a Fmincon. You could try it.
You could just stick these equations in there.
All you have to do is evaluate those integrals
and use them and send it in Fmincon.
See if you can come up with points and weights for it.
This is going to have trouble.
To do it this way, to set up the nonlinear system of equations,
so we can write this nonlinear system in a kind of geometric way
that helps us understand what's going on.
We can write it as a matrix of whose columns are these evaluation points
for all the different points.
We can write down the quantities we would get for each of the points,
the x to the l.
So this last row corresponds to dealing with the x to the l polynomial,
and the first row is the constant polynomial.
And if you look at that system of equations,
you should be able to see something almost immediately.
What's true about those rows?
Right?
One of those rows is looking at a polynomial.
So this is x1 through xn.
These are points between the integrals 0 to 1.
And the last row is taking each of those points to the lth power.
The first row is taking each of those points to the 0th power.
Are those rows very different from each other?
So we can solve this system of equations.
We could use Newton's method.
If you've taken 6, 3, 3, 6,
and you've done some with Newton's method,
you can write this down.
But we're going to try to develop some intuition about what's going on
just by thinking about that matrix that involves the x's.
Anybody know what that matrix is called?
You ever seen this one before?
Yeah, this is what's called the Vandermonde matrix.
So since you knew what Vandermonde was,
what can you tell me about Vandermonde matrices?
It's not singular, like the x-thigh of the x.
Say again?
Like the matrix.
So it's not singular, the Vandermonde matrix.
But it gets progressively less well conditioned as l goes up in order.
And a quick way to see that is to think there's the constant polynomial,
the linear polynomial, all the way up to the higher order polynomials.
This is when we get to the Jacobian and Newton's method,
but that's less important than thinking about what those rows look like.
So, if you're going to write a linear polynomial,
you're going to have to think about the x-thigh of the x.
So this is a picture of a plot of the rows.
Just take each row and plot its points from zero.
So this is the x1 through xa along the x axis,
and then the value of the monomial for each of these points.
And let's look at what happens.
The one that's all 1, that's the constant term.
That was the first row.
The second row is the x.
The second row is x1, x2.
The third row is the quadratic.
The fourth row is the cubic.
The fifth row is the quartet.
The sixth row is the quintet.
What's true about those functions?
Do they look like they're looking more and more like each other,
the higher order up in order?
So, in the limit,
as L goes to infinity,
what are these functions going to look like?
We've got the constant, we've got the linear,
we've got the quadratic, we've got the cubic.
What's the linear?
What's the limit as the power goes to infinity?
What will this function look like?
Do you want to know what it will look like, Tim?
Yeah, after a while, they're all going to look like this.
Because all the points that are less than 1,
you take them to a high enough power,
any number that is magnitude less than 1,
you take it to a very high power, it becomes?
It's 0.99, and I take it to the millionth power, it's?
0.
Now, what about this?
These are not all going the same.
This is the first.
This is the last.
about 13 or 14 rows, you run out of numerical precision in
MATLAB. So you can do these things in double precision to
about 10. And then the MATLAB has problems. So I told you
this is great method for getting machine precision accuracy, only
to figure out what the points and weights are, you need to be
able to do calculations that much higher than machine
precision because of the van der Waals. So you know, it was
fun. And I know it's a nice theoretical thing. And it's not
very practical. And, you know, they wouldn't stop early. But
now we can fix this. Why did I use the monomials? Why did I
choose to use my test polynomials? One x, x squared, x
cubed, x to the fourth.
Is that a good set of polynomials here? They're monomials.
It's nice. They're monomial. They look simple. They only have one
term. They're easy to construct. They have a lot of appealing
features. It makes very easy to generate these matrices, for
example. But what property don't they have? Well, they start to
look a lot like each other as you go to higher order. So if I
told you about I have this set of vectors, and they're starting
to look more and more like each other.
And as I get more and more of these vectors, I kind of want to
come up with some way of figuring out how much of each of these
vectors to use. What scheme would you do to try to make to be able
to tease those different pieces apart? So I have a set of vectors
and they're almost linearly dependent. And I want to turn
them into something that is as close to orthogonal as possible.
What scheme would I use? So I have a set of columns of a
matrix, and I want to make a column of a matrix. And I want to
make a column of a matrix. And I want to make a column of a matrix.
So I'm going to call the vector in this case. And when I call the
vector of a matrix, I'm going to call it a set of columns orthogonal
to each other. What do I do? Same person invented this algorithm
invented some kind of cracker, Graham Schmidt. Remember Graham
Schmidt orthogonalization? No. All right, so then we're not going
to worry about when we calculate these polynomials, but let's,
for a moment, assume that we could come up with orthogonal
polynomials.
We're going to pick some other set of polynomials.
We don't like the monomials.
We're instead, because the monomials start to look like each other,
and we're going to decide that instead,
we're going to come up with polynomials that have a certain property.
So instead,
we're going to try to come up with polynomials
that are very different from each other.
And we're going to define very different as something like this.
We have a c i of x, a c j of x,
integrated over the central point from 0 to 1,
and we want it to be equal to x,
and we want that to be equal to 0
if i is not equal to j.
This is orthogonality.
So you've seen how little in trying to construct basic functions of the orthogonal
can give you better conditions.
You can't do the same thing with condition systems
when you do a basis function based discretization of PDEs.
But you also have it in a very much simpler setting.
We're doing the same thing,
if I took these polynomials and sampled them,
I would get a vector,
and then we're still talking about trying to make these two vectors orthogonal to each other.
So it doesn't matter whether you think of this as a polynomial,
two polynomials who want to make orthogonal to each other,
or you think of representing them as a vector,
but you're actually going to be using a function with points,
and we're trying to say the two vectors,
like the picture we drew here.
If we think of these as vectors,
we're now going to end up with vectors whose inner product is going to be 0.
And now how are we going to construct those polynomials?
Well, I'll come back.
Let's pretend we have them first.
Suppose we could construct polynomials.
So here's one, right?
So it's the polynomial 1, all 1s,
and the polynomial x.
Are they orthogonal to each other?
If I take the inner product of 1 and x and integrate it from 0 to 1,
are those two orthogonal to each other?
Not at all.
Can you give me a polynomial that has a first order and a zeroth order term
that is orthogonal to 1?
So I have 1,
and...
So give me a polynomial that involves x,
but is orthogonal to 1.
1 minus 2x.
So I've got to put a sign in the x.
So suppose I wrote down,
if I have x and I'm going from 0 to 1,
and I want its inner product to be 0 with 1,
what am I going to subtract off?
So what you said is exactly right.
You said it.
But I'm going to scale it slightly differently.
I have x. It goes from 0 to 1.
And I now want it to be orthogonal to 1.
And I take the inner product of the constant
with something that's linear.
What do I want to make this linear function do
so that the inner product of these two is a constant?
Excuse me, 0.
What should this function be?
It's got to have the x in it,
because it's got to be in my mind.
What should I do with it?
All I've got to do is shift it somewhere.
Where?
If I take this point at a half,
and make sure it goes through the half,
are these two orthogonal to each other?
So I got this one.
The second one, by taking the 0th order polynomial
and subtracting some fraction of it off the first order polynomial.
So now you can do that scheme.
You can do a second order polynomial
by starting with x squared
and then subtracting whatever it takes
to make the x squared orthogonal to the first order polynomial
and subtracting off whatever makes it x squared orthogonal to the constant polynomial.
So we can construct polynomials this way.
But I'm not going to worry so much about that at the moment.
Let's presume that we can figure out how to do that.
So suppose we recast our exact instance constraint
with these orthogonal polynomials.
Well, we have, we can't just pick any polynomials.
They have to have, the 0th order polynomial has to have
the monomials, the x to the 0 monomials.
The first order one has to have the x1 monomials.
The second order one has to have the x squared monomials.
But other than that, they can have whatever way
to do the combination of lower order polynomials,
lower order monomials,
to make them orthogonal to each other.
So we imagine then saying,
alright, we started out with n monomials.
Or, excuse me, 2n monomials.
Or the 0th order 1 plus all the way to order 2n minus 1 in monomials.
So we have our 2n constraints starting from the complex term
all the way to the 0th order polynomial.
And we're going to replace those monomial constraints
with constraints using these orthogonal polynomials.
It should be, because it should be good enough.
I mean, any set of polynomials, as long as we can guarantee
that we can write down any polynomials
away the combination of this orthogonal set,
which you can, you can certainly, each of these is involving monomials.
And we can put them together in ways to make the,
you know, whatever polynomial we want.
So we have certainly covered our constraints.
But now we're putting it in terms of these orthogonal polynomials.
So, an 0th order polynomial still has to have x to the lth power.
But it could have any of the lower order terms.
And because of that, we can represent any polynomial
with a weighted combination of these orthogonal polynomials.
And we can rewrite our constraints.
Is this going to make our problem any easier?
We still have two n constraints.
Are these now constraints, are they now linear?
Well, you know, because I've got,
I put the x's inside the c functions.
So doesn't that make the problem linear?
No, of course not.
It may be a little more hidden,
but they still have the products of weights times polynomials.
They're just more complicated polynomials.
If anything, it seems like it makes it harder.
Because the original ones might have the,
the Lth constraint had one weight times only a coefficient times x to the l.
And now it's got all these other terms,
the x to the l minus 1, the l minus 2.
It seems like we're making it worse.
All right, so,
if we have these orthogonal polynomials,
and this notion of orthogonal for polynomials is,
we say, that inner product of,
of two polynomials is equal to zero,
if they're of different order.
And we sometimes use this inner product notation,
or we use rectangular brackets, or,
but it's the same idea as taking two vectors
and looking at their inner product.
And if we sampled the polynomials and constructed the vectors that way,
it would turn out to be identically the same thing.
Or, you know, if we did this by quadrature,
well, we'll get to that.
So,
imagine now we do the following.
We rewrite the exactness constraints,
and we do it for the first half of the terms,
what we'll call the lower terms,
from zero to n minus 1.
We'll write those in terms of these n minus 1 orthogonal polynomials.
And then for the higher terms,
we're going to write them a little bit differently.
These are the terms that have to do with cn through c to the 2n minus 1 polynomial.
So we've got the lower terms,
from zero to n minus 1,
the higher terms,
from n to 2n minus 1.
And we're just breaking them in half.
Now these higher order terms,
we don't have to generate these additional polynomials,
the nth order and the 2n minus 1 order polynomial.
We could do something different.
We could instead say,
well, if I want an nth order polynomial,
an n plus 1 order polynomial,
or an nth order polynomial,
I could take c to the n,
and I could just multiply by c of 0.
That's still c of 0 as a 0th order polynomial.
If I multiply it by an nth order polynomial,
it's still nth order.
But when I get all the way up to a 2n minus 1 polynomial,
I could have written it down as the product of the nth order polynomial
times the n minus 1 order polynomial.
Will this product still have a term that's x to the 2n minus 1?
The highest order term in the cn polynomial will be x to the n.
The product of the 2 will be x to the 2n minus 1.
That's all we're using.
And we also know that the products are independent of each other.
Because we know that when we do,
because we know something about cn times c of 0.
So these are different from the lower order polynomials.
So now we're going to look at the product of the nth order polynomial.
And we're going to look at the product of the nth order polynomial.
So now we have yet another way of writing our exactness constraints.
And this is the really amazing thing.
If we write our exactness constraints to the high order polynomials,
and we're using orthogonal polynomials,
then these and their products really should all be 0.
Because if we integrate, these terms are all 0.
Because they're orthogonal polynomials.
I'm using products.
So the actual integral we're trying to match.
But that doesn't mean our quadrature scheme produces 0.
But it gives us a very simple thing to evaluate.
Now the question is, how do we make sure that our quadrature scheme produces 0s?
So we know for the high order terms, the integrals we're using to test all have the integral 0.
Because they're integrals of the products of orthogonal polynomials.
cn times c0, cn times c1, cn times c2.
All the way to cn times cn minus 1.
But we don't know if the quadrature formulas give us 0.
Is there a way we could ensure that those could be 0?
I mean, we've got this 0 there.
Take the points to be the roots of the nth order polynomial.
That is, I have cn.
It's an nth order polynomial.
It has terms from a0 to a0.
a1 plus a1x plus a2x squared, et cetera.
That's what we're going to have to do.
So we want cn of xi to be equal to 0.
Or if you write down what cn is, cn of x is equal to a0 plus a1x plus a2x squared.
All the way to a to the n, x to the n.
And we're going to take this polynomial and we're going to find its n roots.
Or its n xi's.
That's what we're going to do.
If we do that, it means we've satisfied the higher order terms immediately.
We don't have to do anything.
It says, here's our quadrature scheme.
We've got n weights.
It doesn't matter what the weights are.
As long as we use these n points, these roots of the nth order orthogonal polynomial,
as our evaluation points,
then I don't care what the weights are.
I'll always satisfy the higher order and exactness constraints.
For free.
Amazing.
Well, I thought it was amazing.
Remember, learning this from the first time I was a staff member.
Who thought of this?
Gauss.
Who thought of almost everything.
So,
how do we figure out what the weights are?
What's the weight of the sum?
Does it matter what the weights are?
Can we use any weights?
It doesn't matter what we pick for the weights.
We're always satisfying the higher order constraints.
We still have those pesky lower order constraints, though.
The ones having to do with c0 through cn.
We still have those.
But those,
because now we know where the evaluation points are,
we have
evaluation points
because we know we got them from the roots of this polynomial.
And then once we know those evaluation points,
we can set up the linear system
and solve for the weights.
And with these weights,
we'll exactly satisfy the lower order constraints.
So what do we do?
We find
n orthogonal polypolis
and
we
the x i's
equal the roots
the roots of c and of x
and then the weights
are picked at
switch right
weights from
linear solve.
That's it.
That's all we have to do.
Now the question is,
okay, so how do we get these orthogonal polynomials?
And what about this linear system?
Is this linear system well behaved?
What are the rows of this linear system?
The first row is the zeroth order polynomial.
The second row is this
zeroth order polynomial
that formally the polynomial is orthogonal
to the zeroth order polynomial.
So that row is like a
picture of the polynomial.
So the second row
is almost orthogonal to the first.
And you use that to be precisely orthogonal
with these points
but that's more so because
each of these rows now
corresponds to
sampling of an orthogonal polynomial.
of a polynomial that's orthogonal
to the one in the row above it.
So this linear system is likely to be well conditioned.
Sorry, did you have a question?
So, that's it.
Right?
Did we make the problem linear?
I mean, when I started writing down the beginning
I said, well we could set up this non-linear system of equations
and we could use Newton's method to solve it
and come up with the points
and the weights. And I said that was going to be
helpful to get this ill-conditioned matrix.
So where did that non-linear thing go?
Is it still here? Is the problem still non-linear?
Yeah?
I believe that it's off of the roots.
Yeah, it's here.
Alright, finding the root finding
is non-linear.
But what properties
does it have that makes it very appealing
for us to use for
our answer schemes?
Why is this, why is
training in that big non-linear
system to solve for just finding the roots
of a higher order polynomial
a really good idea?
Because this is
someone else's problem.
Right, there's a
you know in MATLAB they have something
that counts roots of polynomials
and we'll find all of them for you.
Yeah, there are all these, that's a little
glib. It's the, what we've
done is to turn our problem of calculating
quadric points in weight into
one for which they know how to numerically
compute solutions. Roots of
polynomials, and we're using that
to solve for our points in weight.
But the non-linear problem hasn't gone away.
It just means
that we have turned it into one
for which there is already a lot of work
on making good procedures.
We're really counting on the fact that somebody else has already
solved that problem. And we just
used it in this case.
So we haven't taken the non-linear
problem out.
We have just decomposed them.
So we have this non-linear part of the problem
is encapsulated with polynomial roots
and then we have a linear solve.
Is it possible that that has complex
roots or would you instruct
polynomials about it?
So the orthogonal polynomials,
you have to have ones for which the roots
are going to be real.
That is an issue.
And if you use polynomials that are orthogonal
over say
an integral from minus one to one,
like the Chebyshev polynomials, those roots are always real.
But yeah,
the orthogonal polynomial.
There are some ways in which when you
set up orthogonal polynomials
you can guarantee that they're real roots.
But that's the idea.
We're going to construct these n plus one orthogonal polynomials.
We're going to compute the roots of the nth
of a polynomial so that
c of n of x i is equal to zero.
We'll solve the linear system for the weights
and then we'll approximate the integral as the sum.
So
it's a great method
and you have a lot of degrees of freedom
about how you do the orthogonal polynomials
because we use just one definition of orthogonality.
But you can come up with all sorts of different schemes
by changing what we mean by an orthogonal polynomial.
So that says the inner product of two polynomials
integrated over the integral is zero.
We could pick different intervals.
We could pick a weighting function
that sits in the middle of it.
And then we can say
that the integral is zero.
So that's the idea.
And you get things like Gauss-Lobato,
Gauss-Chebyshev,
Gauss-Legendre, all these different ones
that have to do with different intervals
and different representations
of the inner product.
But they all come down to the same thing.
You have to find the roots of the orthogonal polynomials
but you get to play with what orthogonality is.
Or to come up with a weighted orthogonality.
So an endpoint
Gauss-Wagner method
is exact for polynomials up to order two n.
is exact for orthogonality up to order two n.
And that means the thing goes
what we refer to as spectrally accurate.
And that's how you get the meaning
that is you add more points.
If we're looking at something like
the simple
Poitier scheme of using the midpoint rule
this one has an error
that's proportional to one over n squared.
If I double the number of points
I'll get something like four times
as much accuracy.
Or four times the reduction of the error.
But these methods are
more accurate.
Now we come back to the point I put up
at the beginning, at the earlier,
which is this is doing the cosine.
This is the Gauss-Chebyshev
is the one I used for here.
Even though Gauss-Wagner
is using Chebyshev polynomials
which look a little like sines and cosines.
And I just remind you
that with 11 points
you can get machine precision out of these methods.
And you can almost see that each time
you add one more point
you get errors that
double on each additional point.
So that's the characteristic
of spectral accuracy.
So any linear accuracy will give you
a straight line on the Y-Law curve
and spectral accuracy means it's going down.
So it's going even faster than a straight line.
There's no straight line with any slope
that will fit.
Then another thing to look at is
well suppose we took this interval
from minus one to one
and looked to see where the simple Poitier points are
which are these intervals
versus the Gauss-Claude points.
You can look at it and say
well, they're not that different.
But they are.
You can see, and this is what's characteristic
of many of these quadrature schemes
notice they're squeezed together at the ends
and spread out in the middle.
So
it's a small, it looks like a small thing
I mean you're moving them around
and the weights are
not that non-uniform either.
But they don't change that much.
When we're talking about these high accuracy calculations
these kinds of small differences
make an enormous difference.
And we're not looking to get one percent accuracy
or point one percent accuracy.
If you are then midpoint rule is fine.
If you're looking for much higher accuracy
close to machine precision
then these things make an enormous amount of difference
and even small changes
like this point placement
and the changes in the weights can make an enormous difference.
Alright, so
I'm going to
So we talked about this Gauss quadrature scheme
and these are great methods
and we're going to see next time
the reason we're looking at them
is because we can actually turn them into a method
for solving integral equations
in some settings.
But not all of them
and not the most common one in 3D
which are these panel methods I talked about in the first lecture.
So remember what our problem was
for a panel method.
We're calculating these panels
under which we're going to assume a constant density
and if we're doing a collocation method
or a Lurkin method
we have to calculate these integrals
of one over distance over this panel
for a point on the panel
which means somewhere in that panel
the integrand goes to infinity.
This is what's called a singular integral.
And we knew from last time
we knew it was an integral singularity
and we did that by carving out a disc out of it
to prove it.
But for this problem
those quadrature schemes aren't going to happen.
So
and I want to
show you what happens here.
So if we do something like one over the
square root of the absolute value of x
and try to do a quadrature scheme
as long as we keep away from the
quadrature points
at exactly x equals 0
we can still formally do the quadrature
no points at x equals 0
so we have to pick up a polynomial
that gives us for whom the root is not 0.
But we don't get very good convergence
that is
and the reason we don't is this thing goes off
and we don't get infinity.
But I want to make a point about the difference
between two types of infinity.
So there's one over the square root of the absolute value of x
versus one over x.
So the one over the square root
of the absolute value of x
that is an integrable singularity.
The area under the curve is finite
even though the integrand goes to infinity.
And the one over x case
in one dimension
that goes to infinity.
Now it doesn't go to infinity in two dimensions
but it does in one dimension.
There's no quadrature scheme
that can give you
that can solve this problem.
If your integral is infinity
here's your integral.
Infinity.
That's it.
If it has an integrable singularity
then
maybe a quadrature scheme would help you
except what's true about that problem?
When we started doing these quadrature error estimates
what thing did we count on?
In order to say something about the error.
We used the
remainder theorem for the Taylor series
which counted on what about the derivatives?
Was the Taylor series expansion derivatives?
Yeah.
Yeah but these
the derivatives of the integrand
are going to infinity.
All those quadrature estimates of the error
they're pretty much worthless here.
So
you might think well okay
we spent a class on these quadrature schemes
and then at the end of the class I tell you
for the integrals you most likely see
when you're doing these integral equation methods
you can't use these schemes.
Well that's not entirely true
because there's only one panel
you have to worry about.
The panel with the test point on the panel.
All the other panels that interact with this panel
you can do those with quadrature
and it works great there.
So if I have a discretization with n panels
then I've got to do n squared interactions
and only order n of them
is problematic.
So you can do Gauss quadrature
and do a great job of n squared minus n
of the panels and the n panels that you can't do that with
you have to do something else.
So
I told you something. So if n is very large
like a thousand
then n squared is a million
and n squared minus n is almost a million.
I'm telling you something that works better than
99% of the time
and that should be good enough.
But of course if you have to solve these problems
they're still stuck with what to do for the self-charge.
So
the problem is that
simple quadrature done on these
problems that have singular
integrands are usually better than
Gauss quadrature.
Doing the special placement of points and weights
doesn't help you at all in setting.
You need to do something else.
So I'm going to take a little time
at the end and I'm going to talk a little bit about what people do
now.
I want to show you some of the
standard things people try.
So here's one way of dealing with the problem.
You say, okay, well, look, I can do Gauss quadrature
so if I imagine I have a panel
and I want to
so
so imagine
this is my panel and I want to integrate
1 over r and the problem is that
the 1 over r, the 1 over distance on the panel
it goes to infinity at the center.
So I'm going to do my
Gauss quadrature scheme
on this region
and then
I'll do something else in the interior.
And I might, you know, because it's hard
to do this region, I could
tear out a square out of it
so it has, you know,
the geometry is nice and I can do
Gauss quadrature on these nice square integrals
where it's
easy to do so.
So, alright, that's
better. I just have to pull out
I just have to figure out what to do with this little square in the center
and I say, well,
okay, but I haven't removed the problem.
I just figured, well, look,
it's a much smaller contribution to the integral
so if I screw it up, it won't have as bad
an impact. You say, well, okay,
but you're still screwing it up.
So you take this one
and you say, alright, well, I blow
this square up into another square and I take
out a little piece. So I start by
taking out one piece and then I
go inside and take out another piece
and another piece. You do that
a few times. These are sometimes
called refinement strategies.
So people do this kind of thing where they
try to deal with the singularity by
taking out smaller
and smaller regions of the domain you're trying to integrate
and do the rest of it with the
regular quadrature scheme and
really just the region right around the
singularity with something else or with
a lower scheme.
So those work alright. They're not great and
often pretty expensive.
The other one that's very
popular is find the change
of variables. So
sometimes if you know what the function is,
maybe the change of variables,
if you put the integral in front of the change of variables,
then you get rid of the singularity.
So that's really popular
too.
Though if you're
functioning and trying to integrate,
if you can come up with that change of variables,
then great.
One over r, one over distance?
No. There's no nice
change of variables that will do that.
But there are some things you can do.
So you
have all these kinds of schemes
and if you go
through the literature you can find
literally thousands of papers
where they say, okay,
we're going to do a quadrature scheme
where we're going to use polynomials with
an inner product where the singularity
is in the inner product definition
and that's going to work for this kind of singularity
and there's some papers that can deal with
singularities that correspond to a point
in the center and one at a point in the
corner and one at a point along the edge.
You have all these different things that you can do.
And it's figured out
that there's something else you can do
in that case.
So I'm going to show you a picture
of what you do.
So let's imagine that we're doing
this integral from zero to one
of one over the square root of
the absolute value of x.
And we know if we plot
that one over the square root
of the absolute value of x
as a function of x,
you know, when x is large
it's fine, you know,
because x gets bigger,
it goes down slowly,
and it blows up near the origin.
So this is our problem.
Right?
So we don't care about the rest of this integral,
we want to do something about this.
So,
the idea is to come up with
so we'll call this f.
And we're going to come up with
a new integral
which is going to be integrated from
instead of from zero to one,
it's going to go from
minus infinity
to one.
Well, actually they usually do ones that go
from minus infinity to plus infinity.
Where you're going to come up with
some function g of t
and we'll use the change of variables one to one
where g of t
is going to be
when t is equal to
infinity
g of t equals one
and when t is equal to minus infinity
g of t is equal to minus one.
So we're going to take this function
and we're going to try to
expand it out
over this infinite domain.
We're now going to have it go from
minus infinity to infinity.
So that we put this thing
that's going off to infinity
out at the infinite interval
and you might think,
well, what the heck
is this going to do?
Well, it's going to go from
minus infinity to infinity.
What the heck is this going to do?
So we now have this problem
we've replaced
this integral from zero to one
with an integral from
minus infinity to infinity.
So you look at that
and you think, well, that can't possibly
be a good idea.
Well, it turns out
and I'll put a reference on it
because these have become
very common now.
If you have a function that looks like that
as long as
this function g prime of t
goes to zero
faster than
your original function goes to infinity
then the product
of f of g of t
times
g prime of t
you can arrange for it to look like this
as we go from minus infinity to infinity.
So if we look at this function
as a function of t
if you can arrange it
so that this thing goes to zero
smoothly
it has to go to zero
fast.
So if you look at this
function
as a function of t
it has to go to zero
fast.
So if you look at this
function
as a function of t
it has to go to zero
and infinitely differentiable.
So you know what these functions look like?
They're hyperbolic sines and cosines
and tangents.
One of those things you learned in high school geometry
and you thought, well, I'm never going to use those again.
They're back.
So you can come up with functions
that will do this
for any singularity you come up with.
So if you look at this function
as a function of t
it has to go to zero
smoothly
and fast enough
so that it will go to zero
faster than f is going to infinity.
You might say, well, wait a second.
Now I have to integrate
from minus infinity to infinity.
So how do I do equally spaced points
from minus infinity to infinity?
Well, I can do midpoint rule.
I can put one at zero.
That's one point.
And then I can dissect the next interval.
So what you do is
you look and say, well,
I don't care about the tails anymore.
And then you just
put points in.
And it turns out you can actually use equally spaced methods
for reasons I'm not going to go into.
When you just put points down
you figure out how much
of the tail you're willing to ignore
and what kind of procedure you need.
And then you spread equally spaced points
over the rest of the interval
or you do your Gauss-Cogitore points
and do whatever you want in that interval
because in this interval
everything's smooth.
Nothing goes to infinity.
And you might think, how could that possibly
be the best way of doing it?
And it turns out
when you try all these schemes
for putting down points and weights
the best thing to do is to come up with
things that are infinitely differentiable.
Things like e to the minus t squared
the error function
or that's the derivative of the error function
or hyperbolic sines, cosines, and tangents
you can use to construct these things.
And that's what most of the good quadruped schemes
to deal with the singularity are.
It seems very counterintuitive at the beginning
which is why only recently
it has become popular
because you think, how could that be the right way to do it?
But when you're done you end up with
methods that use a few dozen points
and you do these singular integrals
and you can do it very visually.
Yeah, my sorry, it looked like you had a question.
No, no, no, I'll correct you.
So, I'm going to stop there.
I wanted to sort of throw this in at the end
because it's only in the last few years
that these methods have started to become popular
and I'm afraid, you know, I fell into that same category
of people who said, no, come on
we're not really going to take an integral from 0 to 1
and turn it into 1 from minus infinity to infinity
that can't be a good idea
but as people have gone through
and made practical implementations of these methods
and you look at the number of points in which
they have to use and how generally they can be developed
you find that they're
quite effective methods
and they're now good pieces of software
that can do these kinds of transformations
and let you do singular integrals
though you do have to arrange
to put the point where the singularity is
at the end of your integral
so if we have a panel
and we have a singularity in the center
we've got to break it up into four panels
so that the singularity can be at the corner
so there's some issues
I wanted to at least show you this
in one of the papers that gives a good survey
of these kinds of methods and pointers to software
so you can see
but I wanted to show you at least at the end of this
that there are ways of dealing with singular integrals
but what we're going to do next time
is look at problems to which we don't get singular integrals
and we'll do that next time
but for this I just wanted to show you
what's the most modern thing
even if we did it vaguely at the end
the big thing to remember about orthogonal polynomials
and this idea of points and weights
where the points are coming from a polynomial
the zeros of a polynomial
and the weights are coming from solving a linear system
these are very powerful techniques
you can often construct very effective
quadrature schemes for yourself
by determining what's a good set of polynomials
to use for your own problem
and as we'll see next time
it also helps you design very good methods
for solving integral equations in 2D
on closed-circuit boundaries
alright
what I didn't talk about is multiple dimensions
and I wasn't going to say too much about that
because we won't be talking about that
but I wanted to show you a few things
I'm not doing much with that next time
but if you ask I'll talk about it a little bit
maybe towards the end of this last week of the term
so let me stop there
the video I know I'm late on
should be up by tomorrow I think
for the class class
and will be up for this class hopefully
the day after that
and there will be a problem set that will be posted
and we're negotiating about what times
to do these evening problem set sessions
but you should come to one or the other of them
and plan on starting
and finishing the problem set
in that session
this is not supposed to be
it's supposed to be a chance for you to try working on a problem
that gives you an idea of how to use these methods
not to
then make sure that you sort of have a sense
of where the material is
we just didn't have enough time in this last part of the course
to give you the opportunity
to sort of let it sink in
so we can do something
we want you to see actual practical calculations
but we don't have enough time
we can't give you enough time to actually think this through
and we're just going to be
thinking about the problem set when it comes out
think about coming to one of these sessions
I think you'll find it's a good experience
and if you try to do it on your own
there are probably things that you needed to know
that we haven't told you
or we assumed you knew
that having come to the evening lecture
would have saved you from frustration
so please as you're thinking about that
and then I think we're going to use the last couple of minutes
I think Professor Wang will talk a little bit about the
the project
so I'm going to hand it over to you
and then we'll get to the video in a little bit
yeah so I think this is the one content we have