If we do flux reconstruction by numerical dissipation, that is, if we have a finite volume scheme, we have multiple u's or a single u's. It's going to be equivalent. We have i minus 1, i and i plus 1 as cell averages.
And we want to compute the flux at i plus half. The flux at i plus half can simply be the average of the flux applied on u i plus the flux applied on u i plus 1.
We know if we just do that, we tried that, the central flux scheme, it gives us parable results.
Once we create a shockwave, it basically blows up.
And we did a stability analysis to show that this scheme conserves the third power of the solution u, and therefore it never allows the shockwave to dissipate the solution.
But if we add something on top of it, if we add something on top of it, that is,
proportional to delta x, first of all, and that is, and multiplied by the characteristics, which is df du.
And here we should be using a sufficient dissipation that is as big as the maximum absolute value of df du within the range u i and u i plus 1.
So let me just say a max of df du times a flux.
First of all, the derivative of u, which is u i plus 1 minus u i divided by delta x.
So why am I taking the first order derivative here?
Because when you plug in this term in a finite volume discretization, remember a finite volume discretization, we have du i dt.
So we can say that the derivative of u i plus 1 minus u i minus 1 is equal to f of i minus 1 minus f i minus half minus f i plus half divided by delta t.
And that is going to give us, first of all, a term corresponding to a central difference in the flux.
So u of i plus 1 minus f of u i minus 1.
So this is the first term.
And the second term is going to give us plus delta x here cancels with delta x here.
And there is one more delta x here.
So what we get is a term that is proportional to u i plus 1.
So this is the i plus half part minus u i.
But there is another contribution of u i from the i minus half part plus u i minus 1.
Times...
Times the df du.
Right?
So by adding a flux that is proportional to the first order derivative of u, we are essentially adding a second order derivative in the right-hand side of this equation.
So here, another way to think about this is...
If...
We want to use finite volume scheme to discretize a second order spatial derivative,
we should be adding a first order derivative in the flux function.
And in this case, we want to, in order to achieve the same upwinding effect,
here is that, without knowing which side the characteristics comes from,
we want to add a numerical dissipation.
That is proportional to delta x times the second order derivative of x.
Therefore, in the flux, we add a term that is proportional to the first order derivative of u to x times the grid size.
It's a very good question.
This term is supposed to be delta x squared.
Yes, if...
If we want to discretize the second order derivative, it should be delta x squared.
But in this case, we want to multiply another delta x here.
Because...
If you remember, the additional dissipation term is proportional to delta x.
So what we want to discretize is delta x times the second order derivative.
Which means over here, it is okay to have divided by delta x.
Right.
Yes?
Going back to the previous page where you were just showing why we use delta x.
The last green line.
Where...
Where did that arise?
So that arises in the Taylor series analysis of ui minus 1.
So let me write it over here.
So ui minus 1 is equal to ui minus partial u partial x times delta x plus half of delta x squared partial squared u partial x squared.
Right.
So if we do that and plug this ui minus 1 into this equation, because we're dividing by delta x, we get this term out.
So this term is going to be here.
And we also have this term, which we have delta x squared divided by delta x.
So we have a term that is proportional to the second order derivative.
derivative. So I think I'm missing a half over here. So half is going to be added to
delta x. And so if that's the case, I'm probably also missing a half over here. So the appropriate
amount of numerical dissipation is half of delta x times the characteristic speed. So
here I would also have half of that times the characteristic speed. So the question
is why don't we apply upwinding to the linear combinations of variables that has just a
single characteristic. The reason that is difficult is because this linear combination
changes in time. So for example, if we have a shock wave, then at the next time step,
even at the same grid point,
the
shock
wave may have sweeped over the grid point. And therefore, before the time step and after
the time step, the particular linear combination, which depends on the matrix, which depends
on the solution, can change dramatically. So the particular linear combination you can
compute before that time step may become no longer the appropriate linear combination
to use for that characteristic after the time step.
Ahand Prof. giving a smallúp
lên
learning CHAESAR oben indulgen empresas
If f is a linear function, can we use this?
That's right. That's right.
if a Retruckeresto a linear function?
why is it important to take the maximum DFTU?
This is because, again, of the entropy condition.
So remember, the entropy condition says that
no characteristics can emerge from a discontinuity, right?
And in this case, because we had a count example
that doesn't satisfy the entropy condition in the Berger's equation.
So if we have an inverted shock wave where on the left u is equal to minus 1,
on the right u is equal to plus 1.
What happens is that the flux on both left and right of the shock wave
is going to be the same.
So that is going to prevent DUT.
DUT to change.
That is, prevent u to change by this difference in the flux alone.
What's going to, in this scheme, in this scheme,
what is enforcing the entropy condition to be satisfied
is actually this numerical dissipation here.
And the numerical dissipation here,
we need to take the maximum DFTU here
in order for the numerical dissipation,
to be sufficiently strong to satisfy the entropy condition.
All right, so for example, the grid point here
is going to be pulled downwards.
The grid point here is going to be pulled upwards
by this numerical dissipation.
Does that answer your question?
Yes.
So in a system of conservation loss,
we can apply the same scheme.
We can compute the flux as the average
between the flux on the left and the flux on the right.
Plus a delta x times the maximum of the absolute values
of different characteristic speeds.
For a shallow water equation,
this maximum DFTU would be the absolute value of u plus square root of gh.
So this term, times u plus 1 minus ui,
is going to be added.
So this is the dissipation flux that you want to add
to your central average flux
to get the appropriate solution.