So remember last lecture we were solving the Poisson's equation, the partial
derivative of u to x squared plus a known function f is equal to zero. What
we did was we integrated this equation with another function, a test function, an
arbitrary function, arbitrary smooth function. We integrate that over the
whole computational domain. So let's say from A to B, that has to be equal to 0
for any V within the certain class of functions. We'll make this certain class
more rigorous pretty soon.We integrate by parts so if we have u at 0 and 1 both
equal to 0 then the boundary term that goes into the integrate by parts
A and b su 무엇 holy well n the boundary terms that goes into the integrate well by parts
is going to be 0. What we have left is a minus sign of the derivative of v times
the derivative of u dx and the other term is v times f is going to be 0. This
is integration by parts and afterwards we represent the u as a summation of
basis functions and we substitute v with also one of these basis functions and
from this we pull the summation out of the integral what we get is minus
f.
The summation ui of integration of a to b the derivative of i, vi the derivative of vj
is going to be equal to integration of v times vj of x dx equal to 0.
And if we call this matrix to be aij and this vector to be bj what we get is a ui
equal to b.
Right? And we solve this and we get the solution as a linear combination of
basis functions. We also started using the basis functions that are piecewise
linear and continuous so the basis functions are these head functions. We
derived the formula of aij and bj and let's now start putting them into
computer to see how they work. So we have a formula of aij and bj and we derived the formula of aij and bj and let's now start putting them into computer to see how they work.
We started with b, and bj, all the way from the basic model is in the terms of the
object.
Before I showed you in the past how to do things in f, we had alreadyrades all the
products, but satisfied requirements of the first method.
So let's also show that by doing this aij will solve all fundamental questions.
This is how aij is blanked.
So we start with b.
something between 0 and 1, which is random.
And what I will do is I'm going to make a 0 at the first grid point
and sort x and 1.
So the result is x is going to be increasing,
but the spacing is random.
All right.
So what I will do is I'm going to construct the matrix A.
A is going to be 0s and minus 1,
only corresponding to the interior grid points.
These are the each AIJ correspond to a pair of basis functions.
And the diagonals of A would be equal to
the diagonals of A is equal to 1 over
1 over
xi minus xi minus 1 plus 1 over xi plus 1 minus xi.
That's the formula we derived in the last lecture.
So it's going to be a diagonal of 1 over x.
It is going to be 3 to n minus x of 2 to n minus 1.
So that's the first part.
That's the second part, actually.
And the first part is going to be the interval on the left of this grid point.
So it's going to be 2 to n minus 1 minus 1 to n minus 2.
I think I'm missing one more bracket.
Parenthesis.
Still.
I put 1 too many.
See.
OK.
Good.
So A is going to be a matrix whose diagonal is filled.
Right?
OK.
Now let's fill the upper and lower diagonals.
To fill the upper diagonal, we need what we need is the interior delta axis.
So from 3 to n.
And minus 1.
Sorry.
X.
So these are the delta axis in the interior.
2 to n minus 2.
And we are going to shift it by 1.
So we are filling out the upper diagonals.
And we also shift the same number by minus 1.
We fill the lower diagonals.
And what we see is that we are constructing a matrix.
Oh, sorry.
I should be.
OK.
So
Sorry
OK.
So
Now you see that you need a November soul
in the reducung system.
Right.
So
Let's do it again.
OK.
So let's also make the number b.
So the bi is a vector that depends on...
Sorry, this should be...
I substitute v equal to this, so this should be f times vj.
So the bi depends on the right-hand side of the equation f.
It's f times vj integrated.
So in the case, let's say if f is equal to 1,
then bj is going to be...
We also derived it's half of xi plus 1 minus xi minus 1.
So it's the average between two intervals.
So that is going to be...
b will be...
b...
Let's see.
So b is going to be 0.5 times x of 3 to n,
which is xi plus 1 minus 1 to n minus 2,
which is xi minus 1.
So we now have a b that is...
size of b...
That is 9 by 1.
So we have the correct shape of a and b to solve for u.
To solve for u,
we simply do u is equal to a backslash b.
So that solves the equation a, u equal to b.
And we get a bunch of u's.
u is going to be...
Sorry.
u is also going to be a 9 by 1 array.
And u is going to be a 5 by 2 array.
These are the linear combination coefficients for the hat functions.
So how do I visualize the solution?
Remember, for the hat functions as basis functions,
the value of the function at the grid points are exactly the linear combination coefficients.
So in order to plot...
solution we simply put X and U with zeros at the ends. So now this is our
solution. This is what our solution looks like. Alright, so this is our solution of
the equation the second-order derivative of U plus a constant 1 is equal to 0
with bounded conditions being 0 at the two ends. And let's make it clearer by
putting the dots. So this is a piecewise linear function and
the circles are where the grid points are. Now let's see how accurate our
solution is. This particular equation with F equal to 1 has analytical
solutions. So for this equation with F equal to 1,
what do you think is the analytical solution? It's a parabolic, yes, and that
both sides are equal to 0. So what kind of parabolic is it going to be? It has a
curvature of minus 1, right? So you need a half and both sides are equal to 0
so it's really X times 1 minus X. The second-order derivative is the second-order
derivative of minus half of X square which is going to be minus 1. And this
also satisfies both being 0 at the two ends. So let's plot it on top of the
solution, numerical solution, to see how it looks like. So we'll do hold on and X
finds...
Let's say link space of 0 to 1.
Let's do 1,000 wrong points.
And the legal solution is going to be 0.5 times x times 1 minus x.
And let's plot x fine and u fine to see what it looks like.
So we do get a pretty good solution on the set of random points.
Right?
The red solution is the analytical solution, and the blue one is the numerical solution.
Okay.
So on the grid points, the approximation is pretty good, but within the intervals, of course, we have piecewise linear approximation.
So we have approximation error here.
Questions so far about this?