Then, the interior of that circle?
Yes, everything interior of that circle is the stability region.
So if, yeah.
If you are exactly on the edge of the circle, then if you look at the error equation,
the error is going to linearly amplify.
Because whatever error you have previously, you have the same amount of error in your next iteration
plus the additional contribution of the error from the truncation.
So that means the worst-case scenario in the growth of the error is going to be linear,
but it's still going to be unbounded.
It's a lot better than the exponential growth you're going to have if you are outside the circle,
but you still can have unbounded growth.
While if you are within the circle, then if you look at the error equation,
the error without contribution from the truncation error is going to shrink
from the exponential growth.
So that's the problem for each time step.
So even with the addition of the truncation error every time step,
your solution error is going to stay bounded.
So the edge of the circle is kind of a boundary, like borderline case.
So this x, when we are looking at an ODE, is just a notation for, like, a single variable of time.
It's the solution of the ODE.
So it's not, yeah, so it's not positioned.
Sorry for the confusion.
Potential confusion.
So when we are analyzing ODE, we can use x as a dependent variable of t.
But when we get to the PDE, x becomes an independent variable.
So that's, yeah, so let's distinguish the ODE case from the PDE analysis.
Yes?
And then we can also get k.
Oh, also again, in the ODE analysis, we use the k to denote time step.
And when we become...
We go to the PDE case, we can no longer use k to denote time step,
and we use m to denote time step.
So let's make this forward ODE analysis separate.
Let's draw a box.
This is x of t, not space.
k is the time step, not space.
Okay.
Make sure, like, when we are looking at ODE,
the set of notation we can use is a lot different,
just because there are so many more variables we have to use in PDEs.
Yeah.
Any other questions?