Questions so far? And it turns out, in this case, there is a very interesting transformation you can do.
There is a very interesting transformation you can do either at this point or even before we start this projection.
Okay, this is the transformation we can do either here or here.
So let's perform the transformation here to see that this transformation, basically integrating the residual of the equation with a smooth function,
is going to help you relax the differential equation, weaken the requirement of the differential equation a lot.
This transformation is called integration by parts.
Okay?
And this...
If you forget about integration by parts, I'm going to remind you here.
So remember, we were trying to integrate a smooth function times a differential equation.
Right?
And let's focus on the first part.
And the integration of parts is going to really...
relax the differential equation in the sense that if you look at the strong form of the differential equation, the differential form, it requires you to be how smooth?
It has to be at least second order differentiable, right?
If you remember last time, we looked at two examples of approximating a known function with a piecewise linear function.
Okay?
Okay.
to integrate the residual of the equation with a smooth function, or at least a piecewise
smooth function.
It is going to relax the requirement on you by integration by parts.
So integration by parts really comes from the following.
It comes from the fact that if you differentiate the product of two functions, in this particular
case, these two functions are g and du dx.
If you take the derivative of a product, how do you expand it?
Yeah, it's the derivative of the first term multiplied by the second term, right?
So this is the derivative of g, this is the second term.
Plus g.
Times the derivative of the second term, which in this case turns out to be a second-order
derivative.
Okay, now when we integrate both sides of the equation over space, the left side of
the equation is an entire derivative, is a whole derivative.
So integrating the derivative of something in space is going to give me just two endpoints.
Oh.
So the question is, d dx of the derivative of u, is it the second-order derivative?
In this case, yes, because in this case, it is actually ODE.
We only have one independent variable x.
So in this case, I should actually be writing du dx.
So everything is just the ordinary derivative here.
So I'm just writing partial here because of the derivative of u.
Okay.
So the derivative of u is just the second-order derivative.
Anyway, maybe because this class is about PDs.
But like the derivative here, taking twice is just the second-order derivative.
Yes.
Any other questions?
Okay.
So if we integrate over the left.
So, this is the first-order derivative of x.
We have a derivative of, of, which is inside the derivative of x equal to 1 minus the same function at x equal to 0.
And while the right-hand side, while the right-hand side, so this is equal to the integration
of 0 to 1, the first-order derivative of g times the first-order derivative of x equals
1 to 1.
Okay.
plus the same integral g partial square u partial x squared.
Now look at this equality here.
One term in this equality, so we have three terms,
this is equal to this plus this.
Only the blue term requires u to be second order differentiable.
So if we can somehow transform the equation using this equality here,
if we can transform this equation using this equality here,
by replacing the term g times second order derivative of u
as the difference between this term and this term,
between the two red terms,
we are going to derive an equation that only requires u to be first order differentiable.
Right?
The only requirement on here is that g is also first order differentiable.
So by multiplying an equation with a smooth function,
we can relax and integrate.
We can relax how smooth the solution has to be.
Okay, this is a tool that has been used a lot.
In functional analysis.
Okay, so let's do that.
Once we perform that replacement,
what we get is integration from 0 to 1,
g times x dx,
plus g times du dx at 0 and 1.
Okay.
Minus integration 0 to 1,
partial g partial x plus partial u partial x is equal to 0.
So all the following up derivation are going to be the same.
Okay.
So we can,
we are going to be replacing g with phi j,
with the individual basis functions,
because this,
this equality has to be true for any g within a certain space.
And therefore this equality has to be true also for the individual basis functions in the same space.
So it is equivalent if we use g or use phi j,
because if the equality is true for all the phi j's,
then any linear combination of the phi j's has to be satisfying the same equality.
We are going to replace the u by a summation of u i,
phi i.
And we collect the terms,
we move the summation and the u i's out of the integrals,
and we are going to derive a u plus b equal to 0,
where the a's,
the a's are almost the same as what we derived here.
It is,
it is going to be the,
minus the integration from 0 to 1,
partial phi j,
partial x,
times partial phi i,
dx,
plus phi j times partial phi i,
partial x at 0 and 1.
So the reason I said the trick can be also applied over here is because if you
perform integration by parts on this one,
you're going to get the same formula as what we have over here.
Right?
This is simply integration by parts if these phi i's are smooth from this equation.
But the advantage of deriving from starting from here is that we know that once we perform that transformation,
we know that the solution u i's doesn't have to be twice differentiable anymore.
And here we can choose the basis functions to be something which does not have to be second order differentiable.
Yes?
Why do you have equal to 0 and the blue term doesn't?
Oh, the blue term doesn't equal to 0.
Sorry, I should be circling the blue term to be,
sorry,
this.
So I'm saying you can replace because,
oh,
okay.
So yeah,
there is not equal to 0.
Yeah,
thank you.
So what I'm trying to say is this is equal to this plus this.
So there is no equal to 0.
Yeah,
thank you.
Right.
So this is derived from this integration by parts formula.
The blue line,
the blue term can be because,
because the left hand side,
is equal to the right hand side,
which is the sum of two terms.
If you integrate both left and right hand side,
this red term comes out of the integration of the left hand side and the red term and the blue term on the right hand side comes from integration of the two terms on the right hand side.
There shouldn't be a equal to 0 here.
Yes?
I think it must be the first red,
the first for the red equation.
Yes.
First term,
what is it?
Should be g times f.
Yeah,
yeah,
sorry,
g times f.
So it comes from,
comes from this equation,
right?
Yeah,
thanks.
Any other questions?
Yes.
Are we sure that we are applying the basis of this school?
In the case of the,
in the case of the continuous sun-Earth space.
Yes.
Are we sure that we are applying phi theta as the first derivative?
Oh, I see.
So, so you are asking,
are you asking in the case that the space is continuous and piecewise linear functions,
can we find a basis that is smooth?
So, yeah, that's a good question.
What do you think?
If we have a space of continuous and piecewise linear functions,
should all the functions within the space be differentiable or not?
No?
And so you are right in the sense that they are no longer differentiable at the grid points,
right?
At the grid points,
you can define a derivative,
but can you still evaluate these aijs by integrating the first order derivatives?
The first order derivative is only undefined at the grid points,
Yes.
right?
And that doesn't affect this integral.
Okay, that's good.
And divide this integral.
Exactly, because we can divide this integral into the integral on these elements,
where the boundary of the elements are the grid points on which the derivative is not defined.
So, yeah, we can, we can still, for any function within that piecewise linear and continuous space,
we can perform this integral.