So then the other form is the general form PDE. This is also a template and the
template is this first equation. So it's shorter, it has fewer terms, but it's
more general. Basically what we specify here is E, D, and gamma,
applicate gamma, and the source term. And then the same templates, you have
templates for boundary conditions. So let's see how this will fit. If you
compare for example the general form template and the coefficient form
template, the coefficient form, if you have a source term, I mean an absorption
term like Au, for example, there isn't really a way
to put that term in the journal form, but what can you
do? You can always move it to the source term. The source
term can take anything.
You can write anything that didn't fit in the template,
you can fit it into the source term.
But either of these two templates, you can use them.
But then in the WIT form, what you get is nothing.
You get blank, and you have to directly specify your WIT form.
So here, you're getting more, basically you're removing the
training wheels in terms of how much control you have, but then
of course when you are working with the WIT form, you need to
be familiar, you need to be comfortable with first taking
the strong form, deriving it into a WIT form, but you get
extreme flexibility.
Since there is no template, you can do whatever you want.
.
I should probably skip this slide.
You have seen this, right?
You start with strong form.
If the strong form was zero, you can multiply it by any
weighting function, and it should be zero everywhere.
If you integrated it, it should be zero for any weighting
function.
Of course, you pick the space of the weighting and the
solution, but skipping that.
So you can use integration by parts, Gauss divergence theorem
to move this to the boundary, and that's what you will have
for the WIT form.
The only thing is now how do I specify the W's when you are
specifying, now when you are typing, so far we were typing
quantities in terms of the dependent variables.
So saying U.
If you are solving for U or T, if you are solving for T.
But now here, we have a second variable, and the way you specify
in console is if you call the variable U, then when you want
to access the weighting function associated with that equation,
you're going to say test of U.
So or if your independent variable was M, then for W, you
will write test M. So the test operator basically
says I am taking the weighting function associated with this
primary variable.
There is a blog article if you are interested in this that
explains in detail how to implement WIT forms.
But you basically have a choice between WIT form, strong form,
and for the strong form, you can have the coefficient form, the
general form, and other forms as well.
Like for example, you can do the classical
PDA interfaces for things like Laplace equation, which are
commonly encountered.