No matter what kind of meshes you have, you can construct a finite volume solver
that works for all of these meshes through a common data structure. So you
don't need to adapt your finite volume solver to every different type of mesh.
So you can have a solver that, given a mesh, you ask for what are my, for example,
interface normals, okay, and what are my neighbors of each cell, and you can
apply the same solver to all kinds of different meshes. How do we achieve this?
We need several data structures in order to make the finite volume mesh work, and
the most important data structures is the interface.
Okay?
So for every interface, every interface must know,
oops, must know its neighbors, its neighboring cells.
Right, so this is the most important criterion,
and so essentially if, let's say, if I have every interface marked as i and j,
okay, so i and j are the index of the cells which lies on both sides.
So in applying finite volume, we first go through, we first go through the
finite volume.
Okay?
So every pair of i and j's compute the f i j equal to f numerical u i and u j.
Because in the computer, you know for every interface what is the corresponding i and
j.
So using the i and j, you can find the cell averages at the cell i and cell j.
Okay?
So you can see that the i and j are the index of the cells which lie on both sides.
So this is the i and j.
With these cell averages, we can compute the numerical flux.
Right?
Okay.
And also for every interface, you must, must store, and that's something that's good to
calculate in advance, the normal of that interface times the size of that interface.
So we can compute the normal of that interface.
Okay?
So we can compute that in advance before we even start solving the differential equations.
So the second step after computing the flux, so this is a vector, we compute the flux dot
with the surface normal times the cell size.
Alright?
Okay.
And then after this.
Okay?
And then after this, we can clear, we can set all dui dt to zero.
So clear the time derivatives.
And that can actually be applied when you start computing that time step.
Right?
So set dui dt to zero.
And then, then after you compute this.
Which you know, if I sum over this for all the neighbors of i, I get the time derivative.
So with this, I simply dui dt is equal to dui dt plus, right, plus is the, so for i,
I think it's going to be minus.
Minus one over vi times fij and ij, sij.
So this is, this is i.
And for the jth cell, it'll be minus, it'll be, it'll be add, it'll be addition.
So this is one over vj.
The same, the same flux.
Is the left hand side and right hand side dui dt, they are corresponding to different
time steps?
No, they are, they are corresponding to the same time step.
I'm just, so imagine this as a variable.
This and this as a variable you have in your computer.
In the beginning, I set all these variables to zero.
And as I go through.
Every pairs of neighboring grid points or every interface equivalently, I am, I'm changing
the values of dui dt and duj dt for these values.
You can imagine after I go through every interface, the value of dui dt is going to be the total
sum of.
Oh.
These quantities.
Right?
As I go over all the neighbors of i.
And the value of duj dt is also going to be the correct value after I go through all
the, all the interfaces.
And the advantage of this method is it doesn't matter how many neighbors does each cell have.
I don't have to do anything differently for neighbors of different sizes.
Of different sizes.
So for cells of different number of neighbors.
So in this case you did that for the t instead of having nji instead of nij.
Since you're taking 7j, the output face is going to be nji.
Right.
The difference between these two are, I'm still using nij here.
Because nij is the normal.
That's the normal.
So.
So that's normal.
That points from the cell i to cell j.
Nij here.
Nij is going to be exactly equal to the minus of nji.
And sij being a scalar is equal to the same as sji.
Right.
So.
So the size is the same.
Ah.
So this is actually what guarantees the discreet conservation in finite volume schemes.
If you.
If you think of.
of quantity, if you track a quantity that is total is equal to the summation of VI
over all the I's, DUI DT, after you iterate over every interface, you added a
certain quantity to DUI DT and you subtracted the same quantity but like
with a different ratio with a different VI versus VJ.
This total is always going to be staying the same this total will
always be the same throughout your iteration over all the interfaces.
So this total is initially 0 because you set DUI DT equal to 0 for all
the I's and after you go through every interface, this total is going to stay
the same unlike Stew.
because if you multiply this with v i and this with v j,
the add and subtraction exactly cancels each other.
That's what guarantees the discrete conservation properties in finite volume.
And to honor it, you must use the same flux for i and for j,
the same flux between i and j for the cell i and cell j.
And you should, I don't see any reason not, to have these properties satisfied.
The interface must be, we call, consistent when seen from the cell i and seen from cell j.
All right.
So this du by dt equal to zero is the initialization state,
the next two equations are the update state.
Yes, yes.
So update is the difference with respect to what?
Each iteration.
Or the design of this iteration.
The update is applied when we go through all the interfaces.
So after you go through all the interfaces,
you completed calculating the du dt for on time step.
So the loop through the interfaces is the same as our loop
through the interfaces.
So we can see that the loop is the same as our loop through the grid points in the one-dimensional case.
It's just in the one-dimensional case, as we loop over the i,
you can either see it as if we are looping through the cells,
or you can see it as if we are looping through the interfaces.
Right, remember in the 1D case, in our code over here,
right, so we,
all the way up to here, up to line 20,
is actually constructing the fluxes.
Right, in the, so I mean, we didn't do any loop over here,
but you can see this as we are looping through the interfaces
to construct the flux at each interface.
And here, when we perform the loop,
we are actually constructing the flux.
Right.
When we perform a loop, we are looping over all the interfaces
to construct the flux and add and subtract the numbers
to the adjacent cells.