So let's also, because you asked this question,
let's actually figure out what is the basis functions
for piecewise linear continuous space, right?
So let's figure out how can we choose these basis functions.
So let's imagine we have a space of simply four intervals going from 0 to 1.
We have x1, x2, x3 here.
So let's say this is 0, this is 1.
And one of the simplicities of finite expression
is that it's not just a function of x1 and x2.
The ultimate element comes from the fact that
we can choose basis functions that are local.
By local, I mean a function that is 0 in most part of the domain.
So for example, what kind of function can we choose
so that the first basis function,
let's just try to get the basis function,
can I choose a function that is 0 in most part of the domain?
So let's say we have a function that is only non-zero
within the first element, within the first interval.
How can we construct a function that is piecewise linear
and continuous and only non-zero in the first interval?
Just go from 1 back to 0 and stay 0 for the rest of the domain.
Exactly.
That's a very good idea of constructing a function
that is local, right?
So let's keep this as our first element.
Let's keep this as our first function in our basis.
Okay.
Can we construct a function that is only non-zero in the second element?
Most times.
Because it has to be continuous on both sides.
If a function is 0 at x1 and 0 at x2,
then it has to be 0 within the whole interval, right?
So we can't construct a function that is only non-zero in the second element.
But can we construct something that is different from the first one
but only non-zero in the first two elements?
How do we do that?
Huh?
What?
A head function, right.
So the head function, I think what you are referring to
is a function that starts over 0 here,
it gets to 1 at the grid point x1,
and go back to 0 at x2.
And then it also stays 0 for the rest of the domain, right?
Similarly, we can construct other heads, right?
Yes.
Okay.
So we have two head functions.
Function that stays 0 in the first element goes to 1 here,
goes back to 0 here.
Similarly, we can construct another head function that stays 0 here and do this.
And the boundaries are actually a special case
because it's a head function where the other half of the head is outside the domain, right?
So it's kind of a one-sided head function.
Now, in this case,
we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 basis functions.
So the question is,
can these five basis functions represent any continuous and piecewise linear function?
Where the pieces are these four elements over here?
Or if I have an arbitrary function that is piecewise linear, okay,
can I represent this gray function?
Using a linear combination of these five basis functions we constructed.
And if so, how do we do that?
If no, can you construct a count example?
So this, I have a gray function f of x.
The question I was asking is, how do you represent f of f as a linear combination of
phi 1 of x, phi 2 of x, phi 3 of x, phi 4 of x, phi 5 of x, phi 6 of x, phi 7 of x, phi
1 of x, phi 8 of x.
How do you do that?
So the gray function would be what times phi 1 of x plus what times phi 2 of x.
So let's say if you know the exact form of f of x, how do you figure out the linear combination
coefficients?
So the basis function times phi 1 of f is f of x.
So the basis function times phi 2 of x is f of x.
So if we do this, the nodes, that's the node ?
Yes.
The basis functions are one at each node, exactly.
So phi 1 is equal to one.
Well, let me name them differently.
Let me name them as phi 0, phi 1, phi 2, phi 3, and phi 4 so that the place they are equal
to one coincides with the numbering of the group points.
Right.
So if we do this, can you help figure out what are the linear combination coefficients?
Yeah.
f of 0, f of 1.
So this is the first linear combination coefficient is f of what?
0.
f of 0.
Okay.
The second one?
Oh, this is 0.
Yeah.
Okay.
So this is the first one is f of 0.
And the second linear combination coefficient?
f of 1.
f of x1, right?
The value of x at x1.
So if you multiply f0 with phi 0 of x, because phi 0 at x equal to 0 is equal to 1.
If you multiply this, the Green function is going to be scaled to a value that is equal to f0 at x equal to 0.
So this is the Green function.
After this scaling.
And if you look at phi of 1, after the scaling by f of x1, remember this is f of x1.
After you scale phi 1 to f of x1, the red function is going to be like that.
Right?
That already allows us to reconstruct this gray line in the first element, in the first interval.
So this green line, the scaled green line plus the scaled red line is going to be equal to the gray line in the first interval.
And similarly, if we scale phi of 2 by f of x2, the black line after the scaling, because this is f of x2.
After the scaling, the function becomes this.
Okay.
So the scaling.
The scaled red line and the scaled black line, they combine together is going to reconstruct this function f in the second interval.
So the blue line after scaling by a negative number, f of x3, which is here, is going to become this.
Right?
So this negative hat is the scaled.
Scaled blue line.
And combined with the scaled black line, it is going to reconstruct this gray line in the third interval.
And lastly, once we scale phi 4 by f of x4, or f of 1, we are going to get the scaled green line.
Which combined with the blue line is going to give us f of x in the last interval.
Any questions so far?
In how do we represent a piecewise linear function?
Piecewise linear and continuous function using these hat functions.
So this is not just true for this particular division we into four intervals, but this can be done for any subdivision of any interval in one dimensions.
Right?
Right.
If you have any subdivision.
of any interval, you can construct the head function so that they are equal to 1 at one
grid point and equal to 0 at all other grid points.
And once you have the value of the function at the grid points, you can simply connect
the dots to form a head function.
Now you have all the head functions, you scale the head function by the value of any particular
known function at the corresponding grid points, you're going to get a collection of scaled
head functions.
Once you sum up the scaled head functions, you get the function you're trying to reconstruct.
So this is an example of how do you use a basis set to represent any function within
a linear space.