So before we go to more complex iterative methods, let's introduce another very
simple iterative method called the Gauss-Seidel method. It is very similar to the
Jacobi iteration method in terms of we are solving a u equal to b and we are
writing a into the summation of lower diagonal and upper diagonal parts. And
therefore this equation can be rewritten as l plus d, so l u plus d u plus u u equal to b.
Now instead of moving both l and u to the right hand side, we only move u to the right hand side.
So l plus d times u would be equal to b minus u.
And now we put indices. This is k plus 1 and this is k.
The value of this splitting is that this iteration would be easy to perform.
Last time when we are talking about Jacobi iteration, it is easy to perform because the
left-hand side involves inverting d only. So why is inverting d only easy?
Because the left-hand side involves inverting d only.
It's diagonal, right? So the inversion of d can be computed explicitly. It's just another diagonal matrix with the
reciprocal of the diagonal entries of d. But this is more complex. This is l plus d and l plus d is not a diagonal matrix.
It is a matrix with what?
With lower diagonal matrix.
It is a lower diagonal matrix.
And how do we invert a lower diagonal matrix?
It's not that easy, right?
But it can also be done without having to perform complex manipulation to the matrix.
So let's look at what the lower diagonal matrix is.
So we only keep one matrix.
The diagonal and lower diagonal parts, etc.
Times u1 of k plus 1, u2 of k plus 1.
So imagine we are at the kth iteration and the u k is already known.
So it is equal to b1 minus u k1.
And the right-hand side is completely known.
B2 minus u k2, etc.
to be a minus UK n so where should we start in computing these u of k plus 1
oh yeah sorry we have a big view here yeah thank you yeah mistake so so here
we are let's see we already computed you you so you you is easy to compute
because it's a explicit multiplication right so you UK of 1 you UK of 2 so so
all of these entries are you times UK at the corresponding row of that okay
okay so now we have a negative equation and we are going to compute the value of
so so now we have the right hand side and we have a lower diagonal matrix where
should we start we start from the first row or the last row first row because the
first row is a 1 1 times u 1 of k plus 1 equal to a known number so in that is
easy we just need to take the reciprocal of a 1 1 multiplied with the first row
of the right hand side we get u 1 of k plus 1
so just give us k they wasted and now you see you can take a set of our
answers and out of the state thinking which thing we assumed is 2 and also
here you can see that we are not going to get 0 here we presenting those first
staffers now if we continue to можете input the terms of the first column and
we keep talking these statics to isn't it going toصل it out and get the other
Once we solve for the first two entries, we can just get the third entry by using the same procedure.
Right?
So we solve this one by one.
This is why Gauss-Seidel iteration is easy to implement.
It's because once we have the first, the first entry is easy to get.
And once we have the first entry, we get all the subsequent entries pretty easily.
So for example, let's see how do we apply this to Poisson's equation.
Yeah.
So in Poisson's equation, we are solving u of i minus 1 minus u of 2 of ui plus u of i plus 1 divided by delta x squared equal to bi.
And we would have...
We would have k plus 1 here, k plus 1 here, because this is lower diagonal, and k here.
Right?
As opposed to k both on i minus 1 and i plus 1, we now have k only at i plus 1, the upper diagonal part.
And the lower and the diagonal part are now k plus 1.
I would argue this is as easy to apply as...
Jacobi's iteration.
This is...
This is because when I sweep from the first i to the last i,
I have already computed ui minus 1 at the k plus 1 iteration.
Now I am supposed to compute ui at k plus 1 iteration.
That would be equal to...
minus delta x over 2 times bi.
So I have ui plus the average of ui minus 1 k plus 1.
Now this is the only difference from Jacobi's iteration.
u of i plus 1 k.
So this is actually...
This is the only difference.
And this is the value I just have computed, right, in my previous i.
So instead of using the old ui minus 1,
the value for ui minus 1,
I just use the value from the last entire iteration.
I use the value at the current iteration I just have computed.
Okay?
The major difference between Jacobi's iteration and Gauss-Seidel's iteration is...
The major difference is I can't now apply this in parallel
because I have to compute all the i's in serial.
I have to rely on my previous i to get the current i.
Well, Jacobi's iteration is very easy to parallelize.
Okay, so in the two-dimensional case, it's equally easy.
In the two-dimensional case, I would have u of ij at k plus 1
would be equal to delta x squared over 4 minus bij, right?
And here I would be having something over 4 of ui minus 1 j.
Okay, should this be k?
k plus 1 over k?
Is this something I already have or I don't have?
Right, I have multiple terms.
I also have ui plus 1 j.
ui j minus 1, ui j plus 1, right?
So this is...
If I remove the superscripts, this would be the Poisson's equation.
So now I need to put superscripts on all of these.
In Jacobi's iteration, I basically put k plus 1 on everything I already computed
and k on everything I have not computed.
So if I go from smaller i to bigger i and smaller j to bigger j,
what are the terms that I should put as k plus 1?
I want to find out the bigger one.
Yes.
All the minus 1s is something I already computed.
Well, this term is something I haven't computed.
This is what I have computed.
This is something I have not computed, right?
So this would be how we apply the Gauss-Seidel iteration to a 2D Poisson's equation.