If you do this analysis, it's called modified equation analysis.
You derive that, you derive, so instead of deriving a discrete scheme from the differential equation,
you use the same Taylor series analysis to derive a differential equation from the scheme.
And look at what is the leading term of this modified equation.
So this is the modified equation.
And what is the leading difference between the modified equation and the original equation?
And in this case, the leading term is a dissipation.
When the leading term is dissipation, you expect to see a lot of dissipation error in the solution.
That almost as if you added a dissipation term into the differential equation.
Now, this other term, this term is called dispersion.
It is a third order derivative.
In this case, it's almost overshadowed by the dissipation error,
because the dissipation error is O delta x, the dispersion error is O delta x squared.
Okay.
Is there some case?
This is where this is not overshadowed by the dissipation error.
Central difference.
That's right.
So to look at the effect of dispersion error, let's, instead of using the upwind difference,
let's use the central difference to solve the same equation.
Central difference is Ui plus 1 minus Ui minus 1 divided by 2 delta x.
So Ui plus 1 is equal to 0.
And again, we do Taylor series analysis.
Ui plus 1 is equal to Ui plus delta x U prime plus half delta x squared U double prime plus delta x cubed U triple prime plus O delta x to the fourth.
Ui minus 1 is equal to this minus delta x plus minus.
I mean, this is the same, the same, the same.
Right?
Now we take the difference.
Ui plus 1 minus Ui minus 1 divided by delta x is equal to this got canceled.
Oh, 2 delta x.
And this is not canceled, but the 2 delta x is canceled.
So this term, we are having a Ui prime.
This is canceled.
This term is not canceled.
It is canceled.
So we have a Ui prime.
And it is divided by 2 delta x, which makes it delta x squared over 6 Ui triple prime.
Plus O, in this case, O delta x cubed.
Don't forget, it is divided by delta x.
Yes?
Oh, yeah.
This fourth order is also canceled completely.
Yes.
So this turns out to be delta x to the fourth because U quad prime is canceled.
That's a good point.
Now, if you look at the modified equation, it's partial U partial t.
This is still here.
Plus U partial U partial x.
This is partial U partial x.
And now plus U times delta x squared over 6.
So that's actually where this acting in this term is connected.
And what
is that?
So what is this affection?
Let's modify that equation.
Halo.
It's this one. Let's copy this thing, paste it here, and call it dudt central. So we still have the same thing, but here it's u2 minus uand divided by 2 delta x, right?
And here, instead of 2 to n, we have 2 to n minus 1, because we can't loop all the way to n. We can only loop to n minus 1.
Sorry, and this should be modified to i plus 1, so still to n, but like this is 3. And this is i minus 1, which still starts at 1, but ends at n minus 2.
Again, divide by 2 delta x.
And lastly,
like,
making them aligned.
Lastly, we have
u of
1 minus u of
n minus 1, right?
At very end, u1 is i plus 1
divided by
2 delta x.
Alright,
any bug you find on this?
The name of the function.
Oh, the name of the function, thank you.
Central.
Alright.
Anything else?
That's it?
Okay.
So let's go back to the
x equal to
n equal to 100 case, because it's easier to see the smaller dispersion error in that case.
So let's take u0 to be the same thing, and od45, same thing.
We integrate by one period.
So let's close the previous one and plot.
So let's take u0 first.
Okay, so that's still the analytical solution after the wave being advected for any integer period.
Let's hold on.
Hold off.
And plot this first using red.
No?
Oh, I still did upwind.
So, sorry.
Okay.
I think it's still the analytical solution.
Should be central.
Okay, so let's close this thing, plot u0 first and plot this using red.
I didn't hold on.
Sorry.
Plot this first.
Hold on.
And plot this at red.
Okay.
You see, this is a lot more accurate, right?
So, there is almost no difference.
So, let's advect it for, let's say, 15,000.
little bit more time so instead of 2 pi let's do 20 pi all right so we add back
the whole thing over 10 periods and now let's take a look now after 10 periods
the dispersion error is it's showing its effect so the red one that is close to
blue is after one period the one that is away that looks a lot more less a lot less accurate
is after 10 periods so what is the dispersion error doing
it's introducing additional oscillations that's right
and mathematically if you do a fourier series analysis
it
is adapting different wave numbers or different frequency of waves at different speeds so the
first order derivative and that's all different frequencies at the same speed that is why it
preserves the shape of the function and a third order derivative at that different frequencies at
different speeds that is why it is creating oscillations this is even more obvious let's say
let's take a different initial
condition so u0 is equal to
uh let's take this to be greater than 0.8 so let's see if that works
so plot u0 so we get a wave of so so this is the operator that gives me zero or ones
right it's okay so basically i get a bunch of one over here and all zeros elsewhere and
start going to know if it's a good wave yeah something like this so let's take a look
right let's look at the first one okay so Katr's nowPERFOR machine to figure that out
there it is yeah it bulb okay
well actually it Penghuang has a lot of different functional function
entain a sleet
of single and double data for T .
So let's do U equal to float U .
Is that...
No.
Double.
Okay, that works.
Okay, so now it works.
And let's plot this after one period.
So I forgot to hold on, but if you remember what U is, let's hold on and plot X and
U .
So U is the blue, and the red is after one period.
And now it is plain obvious that even after one period, we get wild oscillations almost
everywhere.
So the very high frequencies in the blue curve gets affected at very different speeds all
over the domain.
So that's dispersion error.
So when you are looking at a numerical solution, your own solver or other people's solver,
now you should be able to distinguish or spot these kind of errors.
And these kind of errors are for...
They are all going to reduce as you refine delta X.
But the behavior of them, one is basically smoothing the solution away, and one is creating
artificial oscillations that shouldn't be there.
Should be plain obvious.
And by the way, dissipation error is a lot more difficult to spot than dispersion error,
because it makes the solution smooth.
It's just a matter of time.
Yeah.
I mean...
Who is doing this rookie...
All right.
That's good news.
Looks nice.
Next...
Does dumb package actually exist?
I don't know.
Yeah.
So only two languages, you have to find a completely namesake with this idea.
Just creature name and thepa uh, I don't have an idea of what this...
Do you know what I mean by that?
And yeah.
So
Yeah.
That's wind complimentary.
It's all right.
All right.
Okay.
Great.
There we go.
All right.
So thanks again.
Our wonderful Anh and the yeah.
Thank you all for attending this webinar.
I hope everyone enjoyed this video.
Thank you all for reading.