Alright, so find a difference approximation of the 2D Poisson's operator,
the 2D Laplace operator. The Laplace operator is basically the partial
square over partial x square plus partial square over partial y square. It
appears a lot in mathematics, particularly in differential equations.
So this is just a summation of two one-dimensional differential operators.
The first dimension is in x, the second dimension is y, right? And remember in the
1D case, the second derivative of u can
be approximated by u of i plus 1 plus u such as i minus 1 plus 2u x divided by
delta x squared, and we used Taylor's series analysis to either derive this or
analyze its order of accuracy, and just to remind order of accuracy means as
Delta x goes to zero how fast does the area of this approximation go to zero.
and do we remember what is the order of accuracy of this scheme?
It's second order, which means the truncation error,
the error of this approximation,
scales like delta x squared.
If it scales like delta x, it's called first order.
If it scales like delta x cubed, it's called third order.
All right, so this operator is second order.
The truncation error, left minus right,
scales with delta x squared,
a constant times delta x squared.
Now in 2D, we can do the same thing.
Okay, we can do the same thing.
The partial square u, partial x squared,
plus partial square u,
partial y squared.
Now we have more than the index i.
We have ui plus 1 and j
plus ui minus 1 and j.
So they are taking the finite difference operator
at the same j to approximate the x derivative.
Okay.
And we also add this up with
ui of j plus 1 plus ui of y plus 1.
So we have ui of j minus 1 minus 2 uij divided by now delta y squared,
where delta x is the distance between two adjacent x grid points.
And delta y is the distance between two adjacent y grid points.
All right.
So now we have an approximation to this operator.
So,
if,
I have the Poisson's equation,
which means this is equal to f.
Okay.
That means,
let me write approximation.
That means this finite difference operator can be equalized to f of ij.
So this equation,
which means,
which,
which is written out as a linear combination of,
of five different values of u at five grid points is equal to fij.
So let's say this is,
if this is ij under consideration,
okay,
the value of f at these grid points is equal to a linear combination of ui plus 1j,
which is this point.
This is ui plus 1j.
Right?
Ui minus 1j,
these grid points minus two uij.
So this grid points and uij plus one,
that's here.
Uij minus one,
And uij again is here.
So we have five,
we have five grid points and five different coefficients to multiply with the u at these grid points.
Add them together,
they should equal to F at the center grid points. And the same equation should
apply to every single interior grid point, right? So if we have nx minus 1
interior grid points in X, we have n y minus 1 interior grid points in Y. This
is not a single equation. This is nx minus 1 times n y minus 1 equations.
Okay? Again, how many unknowns do we have? If we know the boundary conditions u of i,
j equal to 0, if i is equal to 0, or i is equal to nx, or j is equal to 0, or j is
equal to ny.
Okay?
So if we have this boundary condition, the simplest type of boundary condition,
how many unknowns do we have?
Exactly. So this gives us nx minus 1 times n y minus 1 equations for the same
number of unknowns.
Okay? And all these equations are linear equations, right? So by this finite difference
approximation of the 2D Laplace operator, we converted the partial differential equation
into a set of linear equations that uniquely, that combines with the boundary condition,
I need to say, uniquely determines the numerical solution.