This is a very recent example from last year. How many of you have heard about
the news that human beings have for the first time detected gravitational waves?
So most of you have. And how many of you knows that numerical solution of partial
differential equations has contributed greatly to the discovery? Only a few
people. Let me tell you how this become the case. So if you look at the left-hand
side of this slide, you're gonna see the kind of signal detected on the two
observatories across the country. And the puzzle is of course how did the
physicists know that these kind of signals corresponds to the merger of two
black holes? Einstein has done a lot of research on this. He has done a lot of research on the
nonlinear equations. He has derived the equations almost a century ago. And it
turns out these equations are remarkably difficult to solve analytically, except
for very restricted, very simplified cases. And it turns out the merger of two
black holes has to be solved using numerical techniques. So people have to
put Einstein's field equation, which is a partial differential equation, a nonlinear
equation, and a partial differential equation. Discretize it using numerical methods, put
it on the supercomputer, and crank it for days or weeks to get the kind of signal
that could be emitted by the merger of two black holes. This is amazing to me
because when people are simulating this, they didn't even know this actually
existed. That was before the observation. That's
just in some cases, in some sense, a prediction by purely physical and mathematical and numerical
deduction. And then last year, people actually detected a wave that corresponds exactly
to the kind of signal that was predicted by the numerical solution of partial differential
equations. So this is, to me, is a very motivational example in science.
And I just want you to know it's really very useful, mainly for real life science.
Especially, for the kind of work that we can do today.
It's a pretty sophisticated machine, but not always.
So we'll come back to the actual problem of waterahlen technology, in the following
minutes.
And the end result is significant.
The contrast between these sufferings in an earthquake and an spaceship.
Is
It's also a brand new engine. If you zoom into the engine, the engine itself is a very complex machinery.
And
if you even zoom into the first stage of
the turbine, which is
directly after the combustion chamber that burns the fuel at very high temperatures, the turbine itself,
if you look at just the components by itself, it's a very complex machinery by itself.
And the question is how do engineers actually design this type of machineries,
given that they can't really see how it operates because it's inside the turbine, the temperature is so high that
the flow can basically melt any metal you can conceive of putting into there.
So it's very difficult to measure anything inside there. Of course, you can't see anything inside there.
How do people design these kind of things?
People design these kind of machineries by numerically solving partial differential equations.
For example, if you just zoom into the trailing edge of the turbine blade,
which is a small part of the whole engine, which is a small part of the whole airplane,
the simulation looks like that.
So this is a solution of
partial differential equation that governs the fluid flow of the hot gas going through the trailing edge of the turbine.
And the solution is to measure the temperature of the turbine.
And through that, people can predict how much heat is going into the turbine from the blade.
And people can predict what is the maximum temperature on the blade,
and whether the blade can sustain that kind of temperature under the given stress, which is also simulated numerically.
And they can predict, is this design good enough?
Is this design going to have a sufficiently long life?
That you can put it in the blade?
Or is the local temperature too high so that I have to redesign the blade
so that the temperature can be lower and can sustain this type of stress and heat for longer time?
And this kind of situation also happens a lot, I'm sure, in nuclear engineering.
Because the amount of power you can generate in nuclear reactor is really
determined by how much heat you can carry from the nuclear reaction
to the outside and do some mechanical work.
And
in the engineering field, this is news also from about a year ago.
President Obama issued the executive order establishing the so-called National Strategic Computing Initiative
to ensure that the U.S. continues leading
in the field over the coming decades.
And the executive order basically mandates that the U.S. is going to develop larger computers,
better computing technologies.
And the motivation for that is the kind of computational fluid dynamics simulations.
And they know it has been an important tool in aircraft design since the 1980s.
But it's also limited by the amount of computing power we have.
And in order to be able to design better engineering products, we need bigger computers,
better numerical methods for solving these kind of partial differential equations.
So numerically solving partial differential equations has been a huge thing in engineering and is going to be continued to be a huge thing and
even bigger in engineering in the future.
So these two motivations in science and engineering, they are very advanced things.
But numerical solution of partial differential equations has also been in our daily life
for probably as long as we can remember.
An example is weather forecast.
So that's weather forecast of
here in the next few days.
And many of us didn't really think about it, but the forecast is achieved through numerically solving a set of partial differential equations
that governs the evolution of the atmosphere.
And in that numerical solution, the differential equation doesn't know anything about, for example, hurricanes.
It only knows about the weather.
It only knows how does the velocity and pressure and humidity change corresponding to the environment around them.
But once you put these equations into the computer, you will see all kinds of phenomenons like hurricanes and polar vortices and things like that.
And this is pretty amazing to me.
The accuracy of numerical simulations has gone up
over the years.
And so does the accuracy of weather forecast.
And by the way, weather forecast is an extremely difficult thing to do, especially well into the future because of something called chaos.
And
exponential increase in the accuracy of numerical simulations is going to get you only
linear increase or incremental increase in how many days.
You can forecast in the future.
So the difference between being able to forecast three days and five days is really all those of magnitude larger computing power you can put into solving these equations.