So today is lecture 2 and before we begin let me tell you something a little
bit more logistics. First of all let's open the Stellar website. So this is the
website I'll be posting all the materials and you're gonna see project
one is already posted and you should start working on it. I'll go over project
one pretty soon. There is also collaboration policy, general information
about the class and a tentative schedule right now posted on Stellar and you can
look at the schedule and plan ahead a little bit. Lecture one the MATLAB code
is posted as a zip file. The video recording is a link to
YouTube.
And there are two old slides I'm reading. So that's the old slides before I
changed the lecture style from basically given presentation on
the screen to actually writing down formulas on my tablet. The reason I
switched was because it is a lot easier to follow when I write
things down slowly on the screen. It's just like writing down on
the blackboard. Well if I just present you the formulas pre-written it's a lot
easier for me to go too fast. So that's why I switched to handwriting. But of
course my handwriting is far worse than the typed down latex. So that's why I
also posted the old slides for you to look at and study by yourself. And also
the reading is the same thing. It's basically the same as the old
slides but formatted differently, more like a PDF document. And also this, the
last PDF slide is actually my worst handwriting lecture notes that I
actually recorded during the lecture. So these are the stuff I will be posting
every lecture. And today the only thing different is I also posted a project
which let me open this up.
So the project is called the
Project of the Year. And it's a project that I'm going to be doing for the rest of my life. So the project is called the
Project of the Year. And it's a project that I'm going to be doing for the rest of my life. So the project is handed out today and it is due
September 26th. So it's exactly two weeks from now. So you get two weeks to
work on this project. As I said the project is very different from a typical
undergraduate assignment. In that like maybe the first question you see like a
series of questions. Like one, two, three and two bonus questions. So only the first one has
a right answer. Only the first question is going to have a right answer. So the
this is basically modeling a bathtub with hot water in it. And the question is
how should the person be controlling the temperature in the bathtub while wasting
as little water as possible. And you'll be you'll be writing a code for solving
the PDE which is given here. It's a little bit more than
standard advection diffusion equation with the with the right hand side that
is H over D times T times Tc. And with also pretty standard boundary
conditions. We'll talk about boundary conditions later. So this one is a Robin
boundary condition and this the other end is a Newman boundary condition. So the
questions involves having you derive analytical solution to the PDE.
Under special conditions. And the analytical solution is going to be used
when you write a code for solving the PDE numerically. Which is going to be
working not only for the special case of u equal to constant but for general
cases. That's the advantage of numerical method is it works for cases where
analytical solution doesn't exist or maybe it's too difficult.
But the reason we still want analytical solution is that we can compare our
numerical solution to the analytical solution for two reasons. One is to make
sure the code we write is actually working correctly. It's not giving
completely wrong answers. Two is it allows us to assess the accuracy of our solution.
So today we are actually going to be talking about how accurate our solution
is.
When we are using finite difference, finite volume, finite element. We are not
solving the equation exactly. We are approximating the equation. How much
approximation error is made? Is it case by case? The answer depends case by
case. So here you're going to use analytical solution to figure out how
accurate your solution is. And particularly you need to decide by
yourself. There is no right answer.
How fine your grid has to be in order to make the decisions you have to make in
question three. Which is extend your solver to general case and use your
solver to figure out a strategy. Also there is no right strategy but you
figure out a strategy that like you can make it as good as possible to have the
temperature as constant as possible while wasting as much energy. So you can
do as little water as possible.
Okay so these three questions if you do all these three perfectly you get full score but
I have two bonus questions. You can get more than full score so that like at the end of
the class if you happen to not get full score on some other projects these may be able to
make up a little bit. So the bonus questions are two parameters in the PDE is on
certain. How can you design an experiment to figure out what these
parameters really are and also quantify how your best strategy depends on various
parameters in the PDE. Alright you can see all these are very open-ended
questions. There is no single right answer. It's almost asking you to write a paper.
Right.
So this is the type of projects we are going to be doing throughout the
semester and any questions about this particular one?
Yes?
How should we provide the answer? Can we provide the answer if we have to do calculations in handwriting or if everything has to be done on the computer?
That's a good question. So the question is are you supposed to
write a paper?
Yes.
Can you write down your solution in handwriting or it has to be typed on the computer?
So the answer to the question is either way is fine. But the submission is going to be in electronic form.
Which means if you choose to handwrite your solution you need to find a scanner and scan them and upload your PDF file.
Or you can just use your cell phone. There are pretty good apps to use a cell phone for scanners.
Alright so the end of the session.
Thank you.
At the end of this project you'll be submitting two things.
One is a PDF file that contains basically the entire report and don't include any of your, don't include like your code in the PDF file.
We won't be looking at them.
The PDF file is intended to serve pretty much like an academic paper.
And the other is a zip file containing all your code.
And make sure it has all the files that like if somebody wants to use it.
Okay.
So that like if somebody, if our TA looks at your report and see something.
We won't be running everybody's code.
But if we see your report and something makes us want to run your code.
Make sure we can run your code.
Alright.
Any other questions?
Yes?
Does Python code have to do with?
That's a very good question.
I'll answer this question.
Right after I finish discussing this particular project.
Which language we should use.
Any other questions about this particular project?
Yes?
Do we need to upload a separate code for each question or just one?
Or a big file?
You need to, that's a very good question.
So we ask you to upload a single zip file.
So they should contain all the code.
And I would suggest making a separate directory for each individual question.
That will make it a lot easier for us to look at your code.