So the central flux scheme works in the following way. So I'm going to use fi plus 1 to be equal to an average between fi and fi plus 1.
Where for each fi is equal to the flux function, which is usually an analytical function or something we know how to compute over the cell average.
Okay, so this is something I can use as an example to illustrate how a finite difference scheme works.
So I'm going to write a function.
d dt central.
And the input.
So let's again, to make it simple, we use OD45.
So the time, the input of the function is t and u.
So our u is no longer a time, no longer the function at the grid points.
It is these cell averages.
So my u is actually, to make it clear, let's actually.
Give it u bar.
So let's name it u bar.
So du bar dt is the output.
Okay.
So first of all, we can evaluate the fi's.
Right.
So let's say f is equal to.
Let's use the Berger's equation as an example.
u bar square over 2.
That's the Berger's flux.
If you want to change the equation.
To solve another.
equation.
This is the only line of code you have to change.
If you want to solve another scalar consideration equation.
The only one.
It's the only line you have to change.
Okay.
So this.
Let me call this f bar because they are.
Values evaluated over the cell averages.
Now the next step is to compute the f at the cell interfaces or at the grid points.
So.
So the f interface.
Is equal to.
What.
We did say.
In between.
Right.
So.
So we.
F bar.
Two to end plus f bar one to end minus one.
We'll just use.
Use that.
So we.
We see.
Obviously.
There is one caveat here is f interface has one less value.
As the number of f bars.
That's the one.
So.
So we.
We see.
Obviously.
There is one.
Caveat here is f interface.
Has one less value.
As the number of f bars.
And.
The number of f bars.
Right.
Now.
We need some kind of boundary condition.
So a simple way to specify the boundary condition is.
To specify the flux.
At the boundaries.
Okay.
So.
We need to talk a little bit about how that specifying flux relate to the character.
We.
Have been talking about.
In this case.
Let's make a easy example.
Let's say the boundary condition is u equal to zero.
Where there is no flux.
All right.
U squared over two.
Is zero.
When u is equal to zero.
So.
To.
Let's.
Avoid.
Discussing about.
How do we.
Adapt.
The flux setting of the boundary condition according to the local u.
Because.
I mean.
We know when.
U is positive.
The characteristics.
Of the.
Boundary.
Condition.
Are.
The same.
As.
U is negative.
The characteristics.
Is going towards the right.
When u is negative.
The characteristics.
Is going towards the left.
So.
You need to do something complicated on the boundary.
But.
Let's.
Just.
Avoid.
That.
By saying.
The flux is equal to zero.
F interface.
Zero.
Okay.
So.
Put the flux.
To be zero.
At.
Both ends.
Now.
The f interface.
Has.
One.
More value.
Than.
The.
Boundary.
So.
That's.
What.
We.
Need.
Because.
Then.
We.
Say.
U.
Bar.
Not.
U.
Bar.
D.
U.
Bar.
D.
T.
Would.
Be.
Equal.
To.
According.
This.
I.
Have.
This.
On.
The.
Right.
Hand.
Side.
When.
I.
Move.
This.
To.
The.
Left.
Hand.
Side.
Move.
This.
To.
The.
Right.
Hand.
Side.
I.
Have.
To.
This.
The.
Right.
Hand.
Side.
The.
Left.
Hand.
Side.
Right.
This.
Is.
To.
It.
The.
End.
Of.
The.
Right.
On.
The.
Right.
Hand.
Side.
To.
This.
So for the zero point, why couldn't you take f1?
So taking f1 is an appropriate way to specify the boundary condition
when the characteristics is going outwards, going out of the domain.
That's actually exactly what I would suggest you to do.
If you detect that u is going outside the domain.
But it wouldn't allow you to specify the boundary condition
if the characteristics is going into the domain.
Actually, if you do that, you are practically setting a zero Newman boundary condition,
which means the local derivative of u to x is equal to zero.
It basically says that, okay, the characteristics is going into the domain,
but I'm going to just use...
I'm going to use the flux at the first cell, which is actually inside the domain.
So this is basically saying my outside the domain is equal to the inside of the domain locally.
So it sets a zero Newman boundary condition.
So if that's not what you want, then you need to pick another way.
It does, but it's a less accurate scheme
because my boundary condition is u.
So if you add x equal to zero is equal to zero.
It's not the average in the first cell is equal to zero, right?
So it's so setting doing what you are suggesting is perfectly fine.
Just a less accurate discretization.
So what you did here, I'm wondering why doesn't that indicate boundary conditions of flux in and out of the volume being zero?
How you appended the zeros at the beginning and end of the f interface?
This is setting.
I have a few grid points in the domain zero L.
My u1 lives in here.
My u2 lives in here.
I need a flux over here.
I need a flux over here, but I only compute the flux over the interior.
So I need a flux at this point.
I also need a flux at this point.
So what I'm doing is I'm setting the flux here and the flux here to be zero.
So does that mean nothing is entering or exiting?
Yeah, no flux is entering or exiting the domain, which is corresponding to a u equal to zero.
So I'm basically setting u at this grid point is equal to zero and u at this grid point is equal to zero.
It doesn't sound like you are convinced.
So how are we going to model flux into or out of the body?
Isn't that the beginning of the model of that?
If the characteristics goes into the domain, I would be setting the flux to f of u.
If the flux is going out of the domain, if the characteristics is going out of the domain,
I should be evaluating f of u inside the domain.
Is that what you are asking?
I think so.
Okay.
All right.
So I was just trying to avoid having this discussion.
But it's good we have that.
So this is our central scheme for solving the Berger's equation.
If you need to change any other approximation, you just need to change this line.
All right.
All the others, this is exact boundary condition.
This is exact integral form of the equation.
The only approximation.
Happens over this line.
And the only place you need to change to solve a different equation is this line.
All right.
Any other questions about this code?
Finding volume is easy, huh?
Okay.
So to solve it, let's make initial condition.
So let's do x is equal to link space of zero.
Zero.
One.
So let's be sure that it is interface.
So zero, one.
And let's do 101 grid points.
That makes 100 volumes.
Right?
Okay.
So u interface.
So let's just make it a sinusoidal wave to start with.
So x interface multiplied by 2 pi.
All right.
And I'm using a crude approximation for the cell average of the sine function.
I'm just going to say it is going to be equal to u interface 1 to n minus 1 plus u interface
2 to n divided by 2.
Okay.
So that's...
And what we're going to do is into the percent, plusvey and even 2 pi plus c.
All right.
Once we've applied U to the X 거예요, 0 to n, plusve cure.
And what we're going to do is this.
Well, now our question is, how do we translate the propertyquery?
We write our variable.
We want our direct evaluation as plus e to the X.
What we're looking to do here is test it.
And again, we use min pass to elements.
We're going to
And y as a input.
E as a output.
And there.
So here we have r farming.
And this is a one to one survey of the ??? continua, r farming ziema's, for instance.
And this is used for the unterschied sum and inverse 키 and ...
So like this, this is the equation
And then now cn first round.
monotonically decreasing region is that
going to be steepening or shallowing?
It's going to be steepening, right? And this
is going to become more shallow and
this is going to become shallower.
Alright, so let's see if that is the
case. So let's say u0 is equal to u and
tu is equal to od45, ddT central, 0.
Let's solve it for 0.1 seconds and my u0
is my initial condition.
Alright, my u is going to be 41 by 100
matrix. Let me actually get my u x-bar, so
x at the cell interfaces.
Just to make the plotting a
little bit easier. It's equal to x interface
1 to n minus 1 plus x interface 2 to the
end, divided by 2 and I'll just plot x-bar
and u. Alright, so I'm plotting the
evolution of the solution. Initially it's
a sine curve, it's this one, and after
time goes, this becomes steeper
still.
So I'm going to plot the solution.
This is going to be a sine curve, it's
going to be a sine curve and the wave
goes steeper and the monotonically
increasing parts become shallower. This
is because when u is positive the wave
goes towards the right, when u is
negative the wave goes towards the left.