An example I want to give is the so-called wave equation.
So the wave equation doesn't look like a system of equations in the beginning, but somehow it is.
The wave equation is an equation involving a second-order derivative in time.
Okay, so if we have a first-order derivative, it is the heat equation.
It is a parabolic equation.
It means the function u is going to diffuse out after time.
But if we have a second-order derivative in time, the equation behaves completely differently.
To see that, let us use two auxiliary equations.
Let's do phi and psi.
So let's introduce these two variables.
And phi is defined as the derivative of u to t, and psi is defined as the derivative of u to x.
So, first of all, just by their definition,
we know that partial heat is going to be equal to the derivative of u to t.
So we know that partial heat is going to be equal to the derivative of u to x.
So we know that partial psi, partial t, is equal to the partial square of u, partial x, partial t, right?
Just by definition of psi.
Which is actually equal to partial phi, partial x, also by the definition of phi.
So that's one equation we obtained through the definition.
Okay.
Another equation.
Another equation we can obtain is from the equation.
So the equation partial square u, partial t square can be written as a time derivative of a time derivative,
which is time derivative of phi.
It is equal to the spatial derivative of u,
which is spatial derivative of spatial derivative, that is, partial psi.
Partial x.
All right.
So, we have these two equations, and we can write them down together.
Partial psi, partial t is partial phi, partial x.
Partial phi, partial t is equal to partial psi, partial x.
What an interesting system.
It corresponds to our previous example where this matrix,
where this matrix,
u11, u12, u21, u22 is equal to what?
0, 0, because the psi time derivative does not depend on psi spatial derivative.
And the phi time derivative doesn't depend on phi spatial derivative.
They only have a coupling term.
And it's minus 1, minus 1 here, right?
Any questions about the derivation from the wave equation?
From the wave equation to the system of two equations we are solving here?
No?
Okay.
And what are the eigenvalues of that matrix?
Of course, I don't expect you to do that mentally.
But if you just file MATLAB,
it's minus 1 and 1.
So, the eigenvalues of this matrix is minus 1 and 1.
And remember our stability analysis.
The lambda k1 would be then equal to our e to the jk delta x minus e to the minus jk delta x
divided by 2 delta x times 1.
Lambda k2 would be equal to the same thing times minus 1.
Right?
Okay.
And if you write the exponential of complex of purely imaginary numbers into sines and cosines,
you're going to find them to be purely imaginary numbers.
They go like that all the way to, let me see, this is 1 minus 1 divided by delta x.
They go all the way to 1 over delta x times, this is imaginary axis.
This is real axis.
And they go also all the way to minus 1 over delta x on the imaginary axis.
So, all the eigenvalues of both lambda k1 and lambda k2 lies in that region.
Okay.
So, we need something not forward order.
We need a Rangakala scheme or something else so that we have a stability region
that encompasses the imaginary axis.