One second. Yep, back to the presentation. So far we solved a very easy linear single physics problem.
So next thing we're going to introduce the second physics by right-clicking on component 1.
The entire thing is called a model, and if you save it, it's called a .mph, the multi-physics file.
Right now we have one component, but you could actually right-click on the root, add more components,
and the second component can be any dimension. It doesn't have to be the same as the first component.
The use of that, I can think of one, for example, if you have a laser heating problem.
You have a block of materials, a 3D coffee mug like this, and laser cutting it from the top cover,
and the laser penetrates a certain depth. So what I'm actually curious about laser heating is
how the heat distribution is going to be like through the depths in the 1D.
So I could solve that 1D heat, for example, a Gaussian curve or something, distribution across the z direction,
and then the 3D actual heat distribution.
So I could have actual heat conduction, convection, radiation in the 3D mug.
So that way I could have a 1D component coupled with a 3D component instead of solving everything in 3D.
All right, and then within each of the components, you could have any number of physics.
So, so far we have one. We could add a second one.
Sometimes you could grab a whole bunch of physics from the very first step when they interact with the model wizard.
I'm just showing how the workflow and I want you to understand each physics correctly before we move on to the next one.
So I'm doing it one by one.
So the second physics I'm going to choose is a heat transfer physics.
So it's on the heat transfer folder called heat transferring solid.
Again, I right click, add it to the component.
And then I could close the physics panel here.
So the second physics is added here.
As I mentioned, the sequence of physics doesn't matter, so you can actually drag them around.
You could pretty much drag everything around.
For example, the binary condition sequences, but you need to pay more attention to that one.
You know, make sure it's the correct settings.
So this is what I mentioned is the same workflow for any physics.
So you work with the actual currents. You know how it's like.
Now you look at heat transferring solids.
You have the same three D4 nodes, a domain condition, a boundary condition, and an initial value.
So the domain condition is the, you know, some conduction equation, the Poisson equation here.
And then a boundary condition D4 is thermal insulation everywhere.
So we know we're going to replace some of that.
So I'm going to right click on heat transfer.
When I case the heat transfer Ukrainies solid at first of all heat source, remember we have a heat source fromley
80.
Coming from air current and physics.
So I'm going to assign the volumetric heat source to the entire domain once everywhere in domain one.
Have this key source and what's the amount of the source you can either use to drop down comes to a smart enough to know DAD's you have.
Curve physics.
You have a heat transfer.
You probably want to do this.
The electromagnetic heating is a volumetric heat source, or you could type in the variable that you can look up.
OK.
either through, there's two ways of looking inside of
COMSOL variables, what are the internal variables that's being used. One is to
toggle on the equation view by clicking on the eye icon here. Then each of
the physics nodes you could actually expand. Then for example, if we
go back to electric currents, the current conservation here, all the internal
variables with descriptions are listed here. And I already know that it's
ec.qrh, that is the volumetric heat source
I want to type in. So I could type that here, ec.qrh.
So that will be
essentially the same. Or if I want a certain magnitude of that, I could write
the expression based on ec.qrh as well. So anything you want.
And what else I want to say. So the
variables can also be found through the post processing steps.
So for example, you could actually add a complete report, write a report
in the HTML format or a web format, and then you could actually
add a document format. You'll have all the information of the internal
equations from different physics and the expressions and the units
and everything. So that's another way of looking at those information.
Going back to the heat transfer physics, so
we define a heat source. The other things we want to do is change the
default boundary conditions. So I could right click, add a
heat flux condition. I'll grab all boundaries.
So the drop down has all boundaries. And say it's a convective heat flux
with a heat transfer coefficient of 5, the handbook value.
And the external temperature, just the room temperature, 20 degrees C.
And then I'm going to choose
a fixed temperature condition on surface number 1 and 10.
I'm going to make a selection out of these two, call them the feet.
So later on if I want to refer to both boundaries, I could just use the
drop down to choose feet instead of finding those boundaries again.
Sometimes we see customers, especially industrial level models with thousands of surfaces,
then it's almost necessary, very necessary to group the
surfaces and that'll help with the
workflow a lot. So the two is going to
glue to the heat sink, so it's going to be fixed at room temperature also.
And that fixed temperature condition will replace the heat flux condition here.
Another thing that we want to do is change the heat transfer coefficient.
Another way of coupling these two is through the multi-physics node.
So we have basically a central place to control those types of
coupling through the multi-physics node.
Depending on the two physics you have added so far, you could have
potentially electromagnetic heating, which is the dual heating. You could have
thermal electric effects, and you could have boundary
effects and also discharge heat source.
So some kind of a heat transfer coefficient.
And then you could add the plasma effect as well.
So the DC plasma.
So basically you can, instead of adding the heat flux under the physics node
of heat transfer, you could add that in the global sense here by just
adding the electromagnetics assigned to domain one. So those two would be essentially
equivalent. You could disable just one of them.
And yeah, the mesh should still be good. Now the stationary step will be solved
by adding the heat transfer coefficient.
So I'm going to right click on study, hit compute again.
So the progress actually shows you how many iterations and what's the
error estimate. And now it gives you the solution very quickly.
So I'm going to add a new plot group. You could change the previous
one as well. And I'm going to add a surface
plot of temperature, which is uppercase T.
And then you could also use the replace expression here.
A better color for thermal, I usually like the thermal light.
Oh, I choose the wireframe. Let me disable that.
So basically the coldest part is the feet.
And then the hottest spot is right here in the middle of the beam.
So that's it for the heat transfer physics. Any questions?
So we used some of the existing information from the
first physics for the second one. So far it's a one-way coupling between
those two physics. If you do want to introduce the reverse coupling,
let's do a little experiment here. The material properties,
as you see for titanium, is by default constant from that building
folder. So the actual conductivity, as we mentioned,
right now is a constant. If we make it a linear function
in temperature, 1 minus 0.001 times T,
and I'm going to use the square bracket just to neutralize
the units in the temperature so that everything in this later part of the equation
is a dimensionless number. So now basically I'm saying that
the electric conductivity decreases as temperature goes up. So what do you
think the maximum temperature would be? So right now we have
700 and around 80. Let me actually
add a maximum volume
of temperature so we know exactly what's the peak temperature here, which is
786.8. So after I change the electric conductivity,
I haven't computed it yet. So what's your guess? Who thinks the temperature
will go up? Who thinks the temperature
will go down? Okay, so the remaining people think the
temperature will remain unchanged. Let's test that.
Alright, so go back to that 3D plot. So now
the peak temperature is actually 568. It decreased by about 200k.
And why?
Remember in the heat transfer equation, which part now changed?
The heat source, right? The heat source is
EC dot QRH. Let's take a look at EC dot QRH.
Which is
right here. Basically it's EC dot
JX times EX plus the Y and Z components.
And if you look up the JX definition, it's sigma
times EX, right? So basically when the conductivity goes down,
the heat source goes down. The EC dot QRH is proportional to
the local conductivity times the field squares.
Of course the field doesn't change because we haven't changed the applied potential.
So the potential divided by distance doesn't change either. But the
conductivity goes down. So the whole source goes down and then the temperature goes down.
So this is actually, if you think a little bit about the physics, you could
with a little bit more time given, you can definitely arrive at the same conclusion
as the program gives you, which is a lower temperature. But what happens
if we change another thing? Say the thermal conductivity right here.
We can make it a physical expression. It's actually thermal conductivity
which goes as an exponential function in temperature.
Like EXP minus T divided by something. And then what's going to happen?
So the heat is going to dissipate slower and then it's going to accumulate a little bit
faster. And those, basically it'll be a computing mechanism
with the decreased conductivity. So we have more nonlinear
factors showing up in your model and they contribute to the model in different ways.
It's more difficult to predict what the actual results would be. So that's when the simulation
actually comes in handy to give you a version of the model.
So that's a very simple control experiment of what's going to happen.
Of course you have to make sure you are implementing the right thing and don't do typos.
So, yeah, that's for the heat transfer physics. Any questions?