If we write the solution u, which is a function of t, a vector function of t, as u1, u2, etc. to u n minus 1,
assuming we know the boundary conditions, which means we don't have to solve for u0 and u n,
then what we have is du as a vector dt would be equal to something times u.
What is that something?
Yeah?
It's a trinomial matrix where it's 1, negative 2, 1, to this, to that.
It's going to be a matrix, right?
And the matrix can be constructed by looking at the coefficients.
For example, the diagonal entries of the matrix is the coefficients corresponding to the same ui as the i that appears on the left-hand side.
That coefficient, kappa times minus 2, divided by delta x squared, is what is going to be appearing on the diagonal.
And that is the same in this case for every diagonal element.
There are also going to be off-diagonal elements corresponding to ui plus 1 and ui minus 1.
Because the ui's are ordered in an increasing manner, the one corresponding to ui plus 1 is going to be where?
Think of how you multiply a matrix and a vector.
To the right.
It's going to be on the upper diagonal because...
So you are going to be multiplying, let's say this is ui, ui plus 1.
You need to multiply this element and put it on this row of the equation.
So that has to be here.
So kappa divided by delta x squared.
And in this case, if you make an error, it actually doesn't matter because the lower diagonal is the same number.
But that's not true for all discretizations.
And if you just look at this, this corresponds to boundary conditions of u0 and un equal to both 0.
Because the very first equation...
The very first equation does not have a term corresponding to u0.
The very last term does not have a...
So this is nothing.
This is also nothing, right?
Nothing means the coefficient here multiplied by 0.
.
And in case you have non-trivial boundary conditions, how should you modify this matrix equation?
Hmm?
Interpolation?
Yeah, but what should you...
Hmm?
You make it a circular matrix.
You make it a circular matrix?
If you make it a circular matrix, if you put things here and here, you get...
You get periodic boundary conditions.
Right?
You get a constant.
So what if u0 is equal to un-1?
And un is equal to u1, then by adding two numbers here, the right solution.
.
What if u0 is equal to 1?
un is equal to minus 1?
What do you get?
How do you modify this equation?
.
Yes?
you could add a constant, exactly.
So if u0 is equal to a known number,
that known number is going to be a constant
that doesn't depend on this vector u.
So it is going to be this equation plus something.
And that something has to be a vector, right?
Has to be a vector of the same length as u.
And that vector only has to be non-zero for two equations,
which two are they?
First and last, we only need to modify the first row and the last row,
first equation and last equation.
So starting from the second to the second last, it will be zeros.
And for the first one, it will be kappa over delta x squared times u0.
For the last one, it will be kappa over delta x squared times ua.
Right, these are given numbers, and you know them.
So this is a constant term.
At the end, what you get is du dt equal to au plus b.
Well, a is that matrix, b is that vector.
That's a standard ODE you can solve using standard methods.
So this is what we achieve by discretizing the equations.
What we achieve is...
We start from a PDE, we approximate the function,
and we approximate the spatial derivative.
What we get is an ODE we can solve.
Yes?
Do you need to add rows and columns and zeros into the matrix though?
Or no?
Do I need to add a row of zeros into the matrix?
Yes.
In this case, no.
Because...
I want the matrix to be a square matrix.
du dt has the same length as u.
Right?
So the output of the a times u has to be the same length as u.
Which means the matrix has to be square.
So here, the matrix is already square.
You are correct in some other cases when you derive the discretization,
and the matrix is not square.
For example, if the solution...
If the bounded condition is more complex,
so that u0 and ua is also unknown,
then after you derive the matrix,
you may not get a square matrix.
In that case, you may add rows onto the matrix.
Maybe not necessarily zero,
but you need to add rows that behave differently.
So in this case, we don't have to.
Because we already derived the time derivative
of all the unknowns.
Alright.
So for example, if you implement this into an ODE solver,
what you need to do is you need to...
In MATLAB, you need a function that calculates a times u plus b.
That's all you need to write.
You need to precalculate what a is.
You need to precalculate what b is.
But in the ODE solver,
what you are going to be writing is a function that just does that.
Alright.
So it's that simple.
The trick or the math goes into construction of A and construction of B.