So phi of r should be exactly equal to 0 whenever r is less than 0.
Okay, let's then figure out if the positive part of this proposal works.
We only considered a case where r is equal to 1,
and we know that phi is equal to 1 is the appropriate value.
So let's consider two cases when phi is less than 1,
when r is less than 1, greater than 0, and when r is greater than 1.
So let's first consider this case when r is between 0 and 1.
So just to draw this case, r is less than 1 means let's look at the definition.
It means the difference between ui and ui minus 1,
the difference between ui plus 1 and ui is less than the difference between ui and ui minus 1.
So the slope is higher on the left than on the right.
So ui, ui minus 1, and ui plus 1.
So this is the case when I have r between 0 and 1.
Okay, so the question is when I want to reconstruct the solution at i plus half
using ui minus 1 and ui,
how should I guarantee that the solution would never overwrite?
Well, I should.
To the existing maximum or minimum.
The proposal we had before, the blue proposal, is whenever r is greater than 0,
which is the case, we are performing a linear reconstruction up to here.
Would that guarantee a non-increasing local maxima?
No, because the ui plus 1 could possibly be a local maxima.
Right?
So in this particular case, phi equal to 1 actually does not guarantee monotonicity.
In this case, phi has to be less than what?
r?
Well, it's not easy to figure out.
Actually, let me write the condition here.
So the reconstructed value u at i plus half,
I think I used the red here, ui plus half left,
is equal to ui plus ui minus ui minus 1 divided by delta x times delta x over 2 times phi.
Right?
Okay.
And this has to be less or equal to ui plus 1 for monotonicity reasons.
Now, if I look at this inequality and move that ui to the right-hand side,
what we get is ui minus ui minus 1.
These two delta x's cancel, we get over 2 times phi is less or equal to ui plus 1 minus ui.
Right?
And we divide this on both sides to get the inequality for phi.
We get phi is less or equal to 2 times ui plus 1 minus ui
divided by ui minus ui minus 1, which is exactly 2r.
So phi has to be less than 2r in this range.
If I draw it, if this is half, 2r at r equal to half is equal to 1.
And this is the upper limit for what phi could be within this range.
Alright?
Does it make sense?
Okay.
So this part doesn't work.
This part could still work, right, in your proposal.
Alright.
So this part of the domain I can't be.
So this is what this says.
So I already know less than 0, I have to be exactly 0,
and I have a slope of phi equal to 2r.
It has to stay underneath.
And at r equal to 1, I know I have to be phi equal to 1.
So the other case is when r greater than 1.
So for r greater than 1, we have conditions we want to satisfy is the so-called symmetry of the flux reconstruction scheme.
Okay.
So when we try to compute, so phi of r,
so when we multiply phi of r times ui minus ui minus 1,
we want it to be the same as phi of 1 over r multiplied by u plus 1 minus ui.
So that gives us a symmetric scheme.
That is, when we flip this x-axis,
so this is symmetry,
because if we consider the x-axis to go that way,
and if we look at a scheme that is,
if we look at a discretization that has i-th grid point here,
i plus 1 grid point here,
and i minus 1 grid point here,
so this going backwards,
we are still going to have exactly the same type of reconstruction.
Here r, remember r is defined as ui plus 1 minus ui over ui minus ui minus 1.
So if we flip the axis,
if we flip the i plus 1 and i minus 1, r becomes 1 over r.
And,
ui minus ui minus 1 becomes ui plus 1 minus ui.
So we should have flipped over,
we should have,
the symmetry means if we flip this over,
the solution we get should be equal.
I think there may be a minus sign somewhere.
But like,
what this tells us is that,
ui,
okay,
what this tells us is that if you divide both sides by ui minus ui minus 1,
what we get is,
phi of r,
would be equal to r times phi of 1 over r.
Right.
And,
if we have in the range of r goes from 0 to 1,
phi is less than 2r,
that translates into the case when,
the argument of phi is greater than 1.
Because if you take r in between 0 and 1,
1 over r is greater than 1.
And if phi has to be less than 2r,
when r is,
being between 0 and 1,
so if this is less than or equal to 2r,
it means,
when,
it means when 1 over r is greater than 1,
phi should be less than,
what?
should be less than or equal to 2, right?
If you,
so there is r here,
there is r here,
if you divide on both sides,
it means phi of 1 over r has to be less than or equal to 2.
So,
there is another line that caps the value of phi,
when r is greater than 1.
So this is the region,
where,
we are going to get monotonic schemes.
So,
Alright?
But,
here is the question.
If I keep phi equal to 0,
all the way,
is that good?
It satisfies both phi of r less than 2r and phi less than 2.
What requirement does phi always equal to 0 not satisfy?
It also satisfies the criterion that phi is equal to 0 when r is less than 0.
Yes,
I think that's a good question.
So,
Yeah,
it doesn't satisfy that phi has to equal to 1 when r is equal to 1.
And that is for second order accuracy.
Right?
So,
choosing a phi always equal to 0 is actually going to get us a monotonic scheme.
But,
it doesn't have second order accuracy.
It's first order accurate.
And it turns out,
if we analyze the criterion for second order accuracy,
we get two more regions that we cannot be in.
These two more regions are,
if you draw a straight line,
so this is phi equal to 2r,
this is phi equal to r.
If you also draw a line that is phi equal to 1,
the two additional forbidden regions is here.
So we cannot,
if phi goes into here,
we don't have second order accuracy.
We also don't allow phi to be in here.
So if phi is here,
we don't have second order accuracy.
we don't get second order accuracy.
So the only region we can get both a monotonic scheme
and a second order accuracy is within this region.
Is,
is for phi greater than 1,
phi has to be,
oh, is for r greater than 1,
phi has to be greater than 1
and less than the minimum of r,
and 2.
So for phi less than 1,
for r less than 1 greater than 0,
phi has to be greater than r
and less than the minimum of 2r and 1.
So these are the two criterions
we have to satisfy for a second order
and a monotonic scheme.
So now we can start
discussing several possible choices.
Do you have a question?
Question here?
Okay.
So the first choice is the most,
is the one that gets us to second order accuracy
while being as close
to the piecewise constant reconstruction as possible.
What is that?
Remember, phi equal to 0
means piecewise constant reconstruction.
Right?
Not using the slope at all.
So how do we get second order accuracy
being the green region
while be as close to phi equal to 0 as possible?
No question we have to trace through this 0 line.
In this region, I can't be state 0,
but I can stay at r, phi equal to r.
While in this region,
I can stay at phi equal to 1, always.
Right?
So the,
this is called the mean mod limiter.
So mean mod
of r
has three pieces.
It can be 0, it can be r, it can be 1.
It's 0 when r is less than 0.
And it's r when
r is less or equal to 1, greater or equal to 0.
And it's 1 if r is greater or equal to 1.
So that's the first type of limiter
that is going to give us
second order accuracy and monotonic.
There are also other limiters.
For example, the other extreme
is to stay as high as possible.
Right?
It's the other scheme using the green one
goes like this.
It stays 0.
Still, any working limiter has to stay 0
for r less than 0.
Then it traces the upper limit
of the allowable region.
So instead of three pieces,
it has 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 pieces.
So this limiter is called a super b.
It has five cases.
It is either 0,
in this range is 2r,
in this range is 1,
in this range is r, and 2.
So it can be 0 or 2r,
or 1 or r or 2,
depending on if r is greater than 0,
or r is in between 0 and half,
or when r is between half and 1,
and if r is between 1 and 2,
and r greater than 2.
All right.
So this is tracing the upper limit
of the contour of this allowable region.
And you can see that both type,
both mean limiter and super b limiter,
so this is super b,
they are piecewise continuous.
They have many discontinuous pieces.
And that is,
sometimes is not the most desirable behavior
for differential equation solvers.
When people want as little non-smoothness
as possible in their discrete solver,
they usually choose something in between
that align, that go smoothly
over all these regions
and stay in the allowable region always.
This type of,
the first type of this limiter
is constructed by Van Leer.
And, you know,
it's also,
so this limiter is called the Van Leer limiter.
It is only,
it only has two pieces.
Again, it is 0 when r is less or equal to 0.
But when r is greater than or equal to 0,
it has the same function,
2r divided by 1 plus r.