Let me write a hat just to emphasize we have a numerical solution.
hat, hat, hat.
We want to know what is the error which is u hat minus ua.
What we know is the truncation error.
What we know is, well we don't know exactly, but we know how it behaves.
We know how fast it goes to zero as delta x decreases.
Actually, no.
Tau is equal to this, not on the numerical solution, but on the analytical solution.
So I'm going to write a here, a here, a here.
The important thing is that the discrete operator and the continuous operator is applied to the same solution when you're looking at Taylor series analysis.
All of these analyses only are true when this and this is operated on the same function as this derivative.
If there are different functions, it doesn't apply.
And they have to be analytic solution because only the analytic solution has a derivative.
The discrete solutions, the ui hats, I mean they are only at discrete points.
They don't even have a derivative, a well defined, a uniquely defined derivative.
So when we do truncation error, we apply this on the analytical solution.
All right.
But when you look at the solution error.
And when you.
And when you derive the evolution of the solution error by taking the analytical solution and the analytical equation and numerical solution and subtract them from each other.
What you get is dui hat dt minus partial ua partial t.
So the left hand side would be equal to something very similar to the truncation error.
But not the truncation error.
It's not the truncation error because the discrete operator, the finite difference operator is operated on the discrete solution, not the analytical solution.
And the derivative, the analytical derivative is operated on the analytical operator.
So who remembers what we did to resolve that discrepancy?
You summed and subtracted the same terms.
So that's what we get there.
Both the brain, they were subtracting and they added because.
Exactly.
So I added and subtracted a term that is u analytic.
i plus 1 plus u analytic.
i minus 1 minus 2u analytic i.
Divided by delta x square.
So I subtracted this term and I added the same term.
Okay.
So this is the term I added and subtracted which changes nothing.
Right.
Then I copy what I have originally on this equation.
Also subtract derivative.
Now I group here.
I group here.
I get two terms.
One of them, which is this term, is exactly equal to the truncation error.
And this term goes like o delta x square.
The first term.
They are the same operator operated on different solutions.
And the difference between them is actually the discrete operator operated on what?
On u hat minus u a.
Which is the error.
So here we basically derived what's called the error equation.
So the left hand side is basically de dt.
D.
dt right this is the left hand side is equal to first of all this term is let
me say you ei okay ei so put an i here okay is equal to ei plus 1 plus ei
minus 1 minus 2 ei divided by Delta x squared so that's this first parenthesis
plus tau i this is called the error equation this is how the error of our
numerical solution evolves in time it has two terms one term is contribution
from tau i
the other term is a self evolution of this error okay and this is why we need
to make sure that this discrete operator itself is stable okay it is stable in
the sense that it has to be stable in the sense that if on the last time step
there is a certain amount of numerical error
if assuming we have no contribution from tau we have no contribution we have no
truncation error even in the absence of truncation error the error should decay
by itself at least it shouldn't amplify itself