So we are going to say ss is equal to this, and we are going to decide, so let's say f interface is equal to, so let's say is equal to f on the left, so 1, 2, and minus 1.
So this is saying I first choose on the left, and then I'm going to loop for i goes from 1 to length of f interface.
So let's actually make it easier. So let's say f interface is equal to just an empty array, and so let's do a loop to length of u.
And f interface, well, let's do it to 2 to the length of u, because we have one less, we are only computing the, we only need to use this upwind formula on the interior interfaces, right?
Okay, so f interface is equal to f interface, and I want to append one more.
And the one I want to append would be depend, depend if ss of i minus 1 is greater than 0, then I want to use which side?
If it's greater than 0, I want to use the left side, yes, I want to use f of i minus 1, right?
Because.
Because I'm looping i goes from 2 to the end.
If I'm looping from i goes from 1 to length of u minus 1, then this would be i.
This would also be i.
Else f interface is equal to f interface f of i.
Any questions about this f interface assignment?
Okay.
So let me make it, let me also append the 0 and 0 at the both ends.
So this is the boundary conditions.
We use the same boundary conditions as we used last time.
And then du dt would be equal to f interface 1 to n minus 1 minus f interface.
You can also add simple
step-by-step seguences since we're using the shape that we've already hamstrung our
tests with, and using the observation común values.
Next we have 2x, which follows f interface.
Having said that, we are blessed to know that f interface follows f demo, so we're more
launched, but we still have a little more bigger gap.
in dynamic configuration, for volume and mean width.
and 2013, x is equal to 2x buy a length of x.
And all the values are actual by Killer aspect only.
The only value in душit is.
If I enter x,
Great lecture.
IfI sport,Then the animation changes to give answer of horas innen,
wives depends on zone previous j value in six block,
so that the a time kind of we have a De worldly U.
So all right.
You can go to my have actually run an Threataland
yeah let's try it so I'm going to use a
arm so I'm going to use that say again
the same initial condition x equal to x
interface is equal to our link space of
0 1 and let's do 101 so that n is equal
to 100 so x would be equal to x
interface 1 to n minus 1 plus x
interface 2 to n divided by 2 so yeah so
x is going to be in the middle of the two
axes I'm going to use u equal to sine of
x times 2 pi
so if I plot x and u it'll be this sine
wave we used in our last lecture okay so
let's say we set u is equal to u 0
equal to u transpose that's for OD45
I think it accepts a column vector and
tu is equal to OD45 ddt upwind
and
we solve it last time we solve it for
for 0.1 seconds and u 0 okay so let's do
close plot x and u so this is still fine
this is also our last lecture we had the
same thing but I think we saw a problem
when we saw it for 0.3 seconds and this
time when we saw for 0.3 seconds we
still get a good solution right so so
let's do and colon so we get a solution
that has a shockwave sitting in the
middle and let's actually solve it for
one second we do the same we see okay we
get a we got a we got a shockwave and
the magnitude of this shockwave has
diminished from size about 1 to all the
way to 0.4.
if we plot all the solution at once so
we see the sine wave goes into the
shockwave and the shockwave starts to
decay
alright so that seems a nice solution
and you can it's interesting you can see
also see like how OD45 adapts the
time step over here initially it chooses
pretty conservative time step and it
starts to know it can cause them and
at this point it's a it starts to also
when the shockwave forms it looks like
the time step is decreased also a little
bit any questions about this upwind
scheme yes so the error comes from our
so you can think of several ways to
think of where the error come from so in
in a Taylor series analysis
you can think of the error coming from
the dispersion we have a second order
scheme we have we know like a second
order scheme from our previous
experience has very little dissipation
if any and has a lot of dispersion error
and the amount of dispersion error is
proportional to Delta x square and it's
also proportional to some derivative of
the function i think is third order
derivative if I'm not wrong.
so so it's proportional to third order
derivative times Delta x square if you
have a discontinuity how big is the
third order derivative it's going to be
huge right it's going to be when you
have something that is very oscillatory
like like a shockwave you have a very
very large third order derivative so
that causes a lot of dispersion error so
from that perspective last lecture we
also looked at the central difference
scheme
being something that conserves the cubed
solution so the conservation of these
higher-order statistics is going to of
the higher-order quantity is going to
prevent the solution from getting
dissipated right because because if you
have a solution like this at later time
it definitely has a has a small
integrated u cubed than the original
solution that's also something the
second-order central flux scheme cannot
capture correctly. The reason for
choosing that is one it so from
monumous stability analysis actually
from the modified equation analysis we
see that using an up-ending scheme is
going to
numerical dissipation right and it is
actually dissipation that we need over
here we need the scheme to be dissipated
by the shockwave the shockwave is
actually a inherently dissipative
phenomenon and if you look at a shock
wave of a real fluid flow of like
aerodynamics in a supersonic flow the
shockwave is very very thin so so here
like mathematically a shockwave is a
discontinuity in a real physics you
don't really have any discontinuities
but you have something extremely thin
it's so thin that the shockwave is on
the order of like 10 to 100 of the the
mean free path of the molecules so it's
like really really small and the
dissipation although the shockwave is
very thin the amount of physical
dissipation occurring during inside the
shockwave is is massive.
That's just because the length scale is
so small and molecules from one side
goes to the other side and they mix
together the amount of dissipation it's
so a lot of dissipation is appearing
there so even though we have an inviscid
equation we approximate the equation as
inviscid there is still a lot of
dissipation going on at discontinuities
and that is like the physical reason why
we need a dissipative scheme to resolve
discontinuities. That satisfies what you
are curious about. Any other questions?
And in fact a lot of modern numerical
methods they are trying to be high order
away from the shockwaves but at the
shockwaves you need a lot of numerical
dissipation because you can never be
your grid can never resolve the shockwave.
If your grid can resolve the
shockwave if your grid size is
actually like ten times the mean free
path of the molecules you don't need any
numerical dissipations you just need
physical dissipations you put the amount
of viscosity of air into the scheme and
you can have the appropriate amount of
dissipation but your grid can never
resolve that so that in that case you
need numerical dissipation to do the
same amount of work. Yes?
If your grid could resolve that can you just use one more difference?
If your grid can resolve that, yeah.
You can use finite differencing and
with not with not with this equation
but with the equation that includes the
physical viscosity so include a second
order derivative in x term and then you
can yeah you can use finite difference
you actually converge to a real