right no okay so F is equal to good enough of UI plus just copy and paste
UI plus half left UI plus half right I'm going to code up the good enough scheme
over here you L and you are okay so just to review our good enough scheme so the
flux is going to be taking either maximum or minimum depending on which you L or
you are is larger right
so so let me just so when we are taking maximum or minimum for burgers flux
burgers it can only be taking three possible values it can either FL is
equal to UL square over 2 F right is equal to UR square over 2 or F mean is
equal to Z
right so so because when we are taking the maximum and minimum of the flux over
a range of U values and the minimum or maximum depending on which side of U is
going to be larger and because the burgers flux is U square over 2 it's a
convex function and because it's a convex function when whenever we are
taking the maximum the maximum can
it can only be possible on one of the ends it's either F left or F right
right so so burgers the floor is like this F as a function of U so whenever
we have a range of U taking the maximum over the range can either a go on this
side or this side
Well, taking the minimum can be different.
So if I'm taking the minimum over a monotonically increasing or decreasing region, the minimum
occurs on one side.
But if the range of U overlaps with U equal to zero, then the minimum actually happens
to be zero.
That's why I'm writing fmin is equal to zero here.
So several cases.
So first, let me just say f is equal to zero's length of U .
Okay, length of U .
So I'm making a function of this length.
So f over the region of U is greater than U .
So when U is greater than U , should we take the minimum or maximum?
U greater than U , we should be taking the maximum, right?
So it is equal to, when we have a maximum, it doesn't matter, is it max or maximum in
MATLAB?
Max.
Max, okay.
Is f and f ?
Yes.
So f and f are.
Alright.
So this makes sense because when both are positive, when both are positive, so over
this region, over this region, so if I have U left, U ,
right?
I have a shockwave like that, and the flux should be taken on the left, which is U and
this is the maximum.
Okay, that's good.
Okay.
So f less or equal to U is going to be equal to the minimum of f and f .
And f less or equal to zero.
Okay.
So f less or equal to zero.
So f less or equal to zero and U and the zero less or equal to U should be equal to
f .
So these are the three cases.
Right?
So this is the case when U is less than U , which means we should be taking the
minimum and that U and U overlaps with the region of zero.
And by taking minimum, we are not taking one side.
We are taking the minimum inside that range, which is zero.
So this is the Berger's Goodenow scheme.
Okay.
So let's try it.
I'm sure I still have box somewhere, but let's do it anyway.
So let's make a, okay, x interface.
Let's still use what we had in the last lecture.
X would be equal to the cell averages.
And U is equal to sine of x times two pi.
So x and U is still the same as what we have in the last lecture.
So that's good.
Let's make U zero equal to U again.
And let's use the DDT.
We call it Berger's.
We solve it for this much.
Okay.
So starting debugging.
Error in this.
Oh, A and B must be the same.
So it's actually the maximum of these within that range.
So it's max of this and min of this.
And here should be the same.
It should be FL of this and FR of that.
All right.
Let's try again.
Okay.
Oh, so here, if I go back up to here, return the vector of length 1 0 1.
Oh, I see.
Okay.
So here we actually computed i plus half.
So we shouldn't have this anymore, right?
So because we only need i goes when, so for i plus half, we need, it goes from minus one to n.
Do this again.
we have a solution. So let's look at it.
Plot x u.
Right. So that way we, so you see
something different from what we got in the last lecture, right?
So we no longer, on the same grid, we no longer
see the minimum of this decaying as the wave propagates
towards the right. So that's the good thing about
a second order accurate scheme. That is, when we have the wave
going, we no longer, in smooth regions, we no longer have that much
dissipation error. The maximum of the solution no longer
seems to decrease over time.
We no longer see this weird gap over here.
And just to remind you what we have before,
the easiest case is to set phi
is equal to zero. So that's our
first order scheme.
And plot this again.
What we have is this curious gap over here
that it decreases the maximum of the solution and
increases the minimum of the solution. And by having
a proper
limiter, we no longer have that.
Alright, so previously we have a case that violates,
so if we set phi equal to zero, we
violate the condition that phi has to be,
we violate
the condition that, this page I think, ph has to be
greater than this black line.
So for example, if we try another,
if we try like your proposal what's your name again if I try Mike's proposal
which violates the second condition that is that is instead of setting fee to
this we set fee of everything is equal to one except for in the region of our
less than zero right basically we are violating I think we are violating the
met the monotonicity of total variation condition it's still gonna be second
order but if we look at the solution here it looks good but like if you see
MATLAB is a it's a smart thing whenever you have a solution exceed the one and
minus one it rescales the screen so that like it looks like you have let's let's
zoom in a little bit and see if we can see the difference between the two so
it's a smart thing whenever you have a solution exceed the one and minus one it
actually see this so you see that the solution has peaks now that exceeds the
the value one so it is not monotonically decreasing the total
variation all right but the solution is still second-order accurate so so the
proposal is not too bad and over over this region it actually damps down the
shockwave and doesn't it doesn't create wild or
the
everywhere because it's actually using information from the wrong side okay so
so this lecture we discussed how to solve scalar conservation loss in one
way or another so we're going to go through the whole thing and we're going to
go through the whole thing and we're going to go through the whole thing and
one dimension but now we have going to second order schemes okay so this
finishes our discussion on solving scalar conservation loss on one
dimensional domain and in the rest of final volume we are going to say we're
going to see how do we extend this type of techniques to more than one
dimensions and it turns out extending this to more than one dimensions is very
straightforward even for very complex unstructured mesh