So for example, there is this equation called the Berkeley-Leverett equation
that models how oil and water flows in the porous media, for example, an oil
reservoir. Okay, so and particularly describes the flow of oil and water
under a constant driven flow. So think of the total volumetric flow is constant.
So you have a porous media, you have a sponge or rock or something, and you have
your injecting water on the left side and you see what comes out on the right
side. And because oil and water have different properties, they don't really
mix together.
So the beauty of the flow is what it can merge into. So for example, if I have a
very well but the some of them are trapping small pores and they're off
surface tension etc if you look at the time evolution of a saturation for
example of oil DT it is not going to be so if if oil and water they are the same
material they are the same of the so if there is no porous media the situation
just at bats in a pipe linearly I would have partial s o partial X equal to zero
right so that's linear vector equation if I have a certain waveform of
saturation in the beginning that way would shift towards the right if there
was no porous media but the existence of porous media makes it a nonlinear
conservation law the F actually depends on the saturation at that local point
okay
region the flux of oil oil is more like in the free flow is in the bigger pour
so that they get pushed faster and as you approach full saturation equal to
warm everything is oil and water is now trapped into small pores that makes the
flux of oil to be more or less independent of how much water there is
so it's it the curve becomes flat again so this is this is a an example of a
scalar conservation law where you can use only one variable to denote the
state and all flux is a direct a scalar function of that one one variable more
often we have a system of conservation laws in which my U is a vector and
it has a function that is a value of u so if I have a function that is a state and I
is momentum and density, for example, or momentum, density, and energy.
And the flux of mass would depend on the momentum.
The flux of momentum would depend on the density.
The flux of energy would depend on also momentum and energy.
So you have a system of conservation loss,
but then always the flux, be it a vector or a scalar,
is completely determined by the state at that local point.
The state can be, again, a scalar or a vector.