So once we have these weak forms, we can
discretize our domain and restrict the
H1 space into a finite dimensional space,
a subset of all possible H1 functions.
So here let's go to MATLAB and click my window.
So let's generate a mesh. So I'm going to
launch PDToolbox. So what I can draw is
an arbitrary polygon, I guess. You can
make any shape you want.
Okay, so I have a domain like that. I can
mesh it. So I get a mesh and I can, in the
mesh menu, I can export the mesh into the
MATLAB workspace.
Okay.
So I'm going to export this mesh into the MATLAB workspace.
So what I get is three variables, E, P, and T.
P is a two-dimensional, it just contains
the X as the first row and Y as the
second row. And T contains, the first
three rows of T contains the indices in
P of the three vertices of each triangle
element. The final row is the index of
the domain, so you can make a
multiple domains. In this case I only
have one domain, so it's all of them are
one. E is pretty complex, but we won't use
this at all. So we are going to
only use the first two rows of E. So E is
not all the edges, it contains only the
outside boundary edges. Okay. So we are
going to only use E to identify which
points lie on the boundary. Okay, so
for example, let's look at the boundary edges.
Let's figure this out for now. So I at
the boundary is simply equal to the
unique points in the first row of E and
the second row of E. So these are IB,
it turns out there are 70 points,
there are exactly 70 points on the
boundary, which makes sense. There are 70 points.
So if you look at the dimension of E,
there are 70 edges. So because it's
two dimensional domain, the number of edges
on the boundary is the same as the
number of points on the boundary. Alright.
So what's next? Let's visualize the mesh.
So MATLAB there is a tryMesh function
and the first argument of tryMesh should
be the triangles, which I can take the
first three
rows of T. And MATLAB actually needs
is, sorry, it needs is transpose. So it needs a
n by 3 matrix as the triangles and
the three are just the indices of the
points. And the x dimension of P is P1
and the y dimension is P2. So that gives me
da da da da.
I think I have it.
I have an actual parenthesis. So that
gives me a mesh. Close. Right. So that's
that's a visualization of the mesh we
just made. Right. So when we are talking
about finding element, we're going to be
defining in this lecture a piecewise
linear function that is piecewise linear
in each of these small triangles.
And to, also we are going to enforce
these functions to be continuous. So can
you visualize what a piecewise linear
and continuous function should look like
in such a domain? A linear function on
the triangle is just a flat but slanted
function. If you think of the value of
the function in the other space. Let's,
for example, let's map out and say we are going
let's make one. So let's say u is going to be zeros, the number of points is 406,
and let's make a random u to be 1. Okay, I'm just making a function that is equal to 0 on all grid
points except for one grid points. And let's visualize what this function looks like.
I'm going to try mesh the function, but with another variable u here.
This is how the function looks like. It's a function that is piecewise linear because,
I mean, because it's on every, on all the flat surfaces, it's piecewise linear for sure because
it's zero. And on this, on the size of these particular points,
they are also piecewise linear, right? Because each element is a triangle, and if you define
the three values at the three vertices, you get a linear function, you get a unique linear function.
So this is one of the basis functions.
And I think you can also do a choice serve that may make it a little bit more clear,
right? So that gives you,
that gives you,
that gives you a continuous surface.
I should have, oh,
let me, let me do that again.
That's rotate, yeah, rotate 3D.
So, so you can see it's, it's going to be a function that is continuous everywhere and piecewise linear.
Okay.
And we can do this for as many times as there are interior grid points.
Right? Because if I have the boundary values to be zero,
I don't need the boundary grid points to contribute to the basis functions.
They are all zero.