So let's take a look at several examples of how we are dividing, how we can divide
the space on which we want to solve the differential equation into small finite
volumes. And as you can imagine the only criterion we have is that all these
volumes, first of all they don't overlap. Two, they fill the entire space, there is no gap
in between. So any kind of partition of unity is going to work for us.
So this type of grid is called a block structured grid. And what you can see is
that every piece of grid is logically a rectangle. So here for example
you can separate a rectangle, use this, separate a rectangle over here,
and then separate a rectangle over here.
So you can separate a rectangle over here, and then separate a rectangle over here.
And on the grid, on this rectangle, the grid can be arranged into i goes from 0 to ni, and j goes from 0 to nj.
And this is another rectangle you can draw.
Right? And so basically we have a partition of unity by first dividing the space.
In this case it's a turbo machinery
cascade. We have an array of status upstream and an array of compressor
rotors which moves in space and after which another array of status.
And we divide the entire computational space into rectangles and generate a
mesh on each rectangle.
So every one of these mesh is a finite volume.
And every mesh in this case has exactly four neighbors.
Right? It shares a non-trivial interface with four neighboring grid points.
Okay, so basically for every mesh we're going to compute, we're going to find the four neighbors
and use the cell averages on that cell and its four neighbors to compute the flux.
on the four faces and then the summation the summation of the flux on
the four interfaces multiplied by its interface face normal times the
interface size is going to give us the time derivative of that cell average.
Right?
Another type of mesh is
unstructured mesh.
Right? This mesh is a triangular unstructured mesh.
And in real applications unstructured mesh can have triangles, it can have mixed elements also.
So in this case every volume is one of these triangles in two dimensions.
And in three dimensions these can be tetrahedrals.
Having
four faces.
And these triangles have three faces.
And every triangle have how many neighbors?
It has exactly three neighbors.
Right?
So and each tetrahedral would have four neighbors.
So these are, for example, the black triangle has neighbors this one, this one, and this one only.
All the others are not going to be counted as neighbors in a finite volume sense.
Right?
If you do if you do other, for example, if you do finite element, maybe these are also going to be counted also as neighbors.
But in finite volume.
Only the cells that shares a non-trivial interface is going to be neighbors.
Again, we are going to use this cell and its three neighbors to compute the flux across these three sides.
Okay.
And the summation of the flux times the the the flux.
The the the phase normal and times the length of the phase.
Summed together divided by the volume of the the the area of the triangle.
We are going to get the time derivative of that cell.
Okay.
So these are the two cases where the number of neighbors are fixed.
There are also cases where the number of neighbors are not fixed.
That also can work.
So this is in this is particularly useful for cases where you need very different resolutions in different regions of the space.
For example, this is an application in which obviously we want to capture.
We want to have very high resolution almost near a contour.
And away from the contour, we don't need much resolution.
So this is the case.
We can have this kind of a hierarchical adaptive measure refinement like AMR.
So so there are very coarse grids and you can have a lot finer grids.
In where you want to have higher resolutions.
And for example, in this volume.
The cells, the neighbors which you count as your cells would be this one.
This one, this one, this one, this one, and these two.
Right.
So you have one, two, three, four, five, six, seven neighbors.