So last lecture we started the general formulation of finite volume schemes.
So we store the cell averages, ui is equal to 1 over delta x,
times the integral from xi minus half and xi plus half of u dx.
So remember, the first class cities in finite volume is now the cell averages
and the cells itself.
The grid points lies in between the cell averages.
So they are second class citizens and we use the i plus half, i minus half to denote them.
So this is our definition of ui bar.
And in the future, in finite volume, I will just use ui to denote them
because whenever I say ui, it's actually the cell average.
Okay, so the time derivative of a cell average,
so I will just say ui equal to this,
the time derivative of ui is going to be exactly 1 over delta x
times f of i minus half minus fi plus half.
This is exact. Again, this is exact.
This is exact if my f of i plus half is equal to f of u at xi plus half.
And so is xi minus half.
The reason finite volume is an approximation is not going to solve the equation exactly
is because we don't have the value of u at xi plus half.
We only have the cell averages.
So we need to...
We need to approximate f of i plus half from the cell averages.
Averages of u.
Okay, so in the last class, we did a central difference type of approximation,
not central difference, a central average.
Type of approximation.
We computed f on the cell average values
and we just averaged two neighboring cells to get the flux.
It turns out to be a working scheme before any discontinuity developed.
Right?
And after some discontinuity, after a shock wave is developed, what happened?
Oscillation starts to form.
Right?
The solution goes crazy.
And we didn't want that.
So today we are going to discuss a very crude way to fix that problem.
That's called an upwind scheme.
Okay, so the upwind scheme.
So it's a way to fix the oscillations.
Oscillations.
Around shocks.
Okay.
So the motivation of that is still looking at the X-T diagram.
The X-T diagram is a diagram when we saw on the screen that the characteristics were straight lines.
Remember that?
So we see straight lines being characteristics.
Right?
And straight lines being characteristics.
And in between these straight lines, when the straight lines meet, there is a shock wave.
And the shock wave is not necessarily going to be straight.
It can curve.
Right?
So this is what we see in the X-T diagram.
In the X-T diagram, and we know that the central difference has problems around the shock wave.
Right?
So we know that the central difference has problems around the shock wave.
So we look around the shock waves to see what is special on the X-T diagram around shock waves.
It turns out that what's special is that information in the conservation law only propagates in one direction.
It either propagates towards the left or propagates towards the right.
And around shock waves,
information may be propagating in different directions on different sides of the shock wave.
So the motivation it gives us is that when we compute the flux,
perhaps we shouldn't be averaging the value at both sides.
We should be emphasizing one side of the interface more than the other side.
Right?
And which side should we emphasize more?
Which side?
Which side should we use more information from?
When we are computing f of i plus half,
let's say instead of taking the straight average between f of ui and f of ui plus 1,
let's say if we want to weigh them, one heavier than the other,
which one should we weigh more?
Yes?
Whichever side the wave is coming from.
Right?
I want to weigh whichever side is coming from more.
So an extreme of that is I want to say it is either equal to f ui or f ui plus 1,
depending on the local speed of characteristics.
Right?
So, for example, and we know in a discontinuity,
let's move it to here, f ui or f ui plus 1.
The two cases are, we know that if we have a true discontinuity,
then a shock wave would be forming and moving towards a certain direction.
And the speed of the shock wave is going to be f of ui minus f of ui plus 1 divided by f ui.
So, if we have a true discontinuity,
then we can say that f of ui minus f ui plus 1 divided by ui minus ui plus 1.
If this one is less than 0, the wave would be moving towards the left,
in which case we want to use the right.
So, if it is greater than 0, the wave is moving towards the right,
and we want to use ui instead of ui plus 1.
Right?
And when it is less than 0, we want to use ui plus 1 rather than ui.
Yes?
I didn't hear a pal.
This is by considering there is a discontinuity at x i plus half.
Yes.
And in finite volume approximation,
this way of thinking is to approximate the solution as a piecewise constant function.
Right?
This is as if I'm saying, I only have the cell averages.
How do I reconstruct the solution from the cell averages?
This is a very crude way of performing.
That reconstruction is to say, on every cell, the solution is just a uniform constant.
Then, a small chocolate is going to be, I mean, a big chocolate is going to be formed at every interface.
And this is how I'm computing the speed of that shockwave.
Right?
Okay.
So, let's implement that scheme to see if that gets rid of our problem.
And in this case, before we implement that scheme, let's actually simplify this notation a little bit.
Because if we evaluate this formula, delta f by delta u in brute force, we actually have a problem.
Because ui can be almost exactly equal to ui plus 1 in some cases.
And we would be getting something divided by 0.
I mean, we would get 0 divided by 0.
Because f of ui is 0.
It's going to be equal to f of ui plus 1.
So, 0 divided by 0.
A computer would get, like, not a number.
And we'll be screwed after a while.
So, we want some way to evaluate this ratio without having to encounter a NAND problem.
Okay.
So, for example, Berger's equation.
A simple way to get rid of that is by plugging the formula for f.
Into that equation.
So, we are going to get f of ui minus f of ui plus 1 divided by ui minus ui plus 1 would be just equal to half of ui plus ui plus 1.
Right?
By plugging the half of u square formula.
All right.
So, the upwind.
Scheme.
In finite volume.
Is determining.
Is looking at the average value of the solution on both sides of the interface.
And choosing the side to bias according to the average solution in Berger's equation.
So, let's go to MATLAB.
And write a new function called ddt upwind.
And let's do that with a t and u.
And ddt.
So, still the first thing to compute is the f bar.
So, the cell averaged flux is equal to u squared divided by 2.
So, that's still the same.
All right.
And so, speed of the characteristics or speed of the shockwave.
Let's say.
Ss is equal to u of 2 to n plus u of 1 to n minus 1 divided by 2.
Right.
So, that's what is going to be deciding if we are going to use upwind or downwind.
Yes?
So, in this case, because f is u squared over 2, we were able to conveniently get rid of the differences.
Yes.
But there are cases where that's not going to be.
Okay.
So, you are concerned when you don't have an analytical formula you can use in general.
So, if you don't have an analytical formula to use in general, you have to separate the case where ui is almost equal to ui plus 1.
In that case, if ui is almost equal to ui plus 1, what is this?
What is the ratio?
Delta f over delta u.
The derivative of f to u.
Right.
So, generally.
You have like an epsilon criterion.
If the difference between ui and ui plus 1 is less than like 10 to the minus 6 or something, you use the derivative formula.
If it's larger than that, you use the delta formula.