Okay, so let's show that back in our MATLAB script.
So here let's make a new function called the multigrid.
Sorry.
Okay, thanks.
So we are trying to make it the same way as we coded up the Jacobi and the Gauss-Seidel iterations.
So the start is we are computing the residual, right?
So the residual, first of all, is going to be...
Let's actually first do the same thing to compute delta x again.
So that's the same thing as what we did.
And the residual is going to be...
The residual of the Laplace equation.
So the residual is going to be the b minus...
Okay, so let's first make it equal to b.
And for i goes from 2 to n interval.
For j goes from 2 to n interval.
Okay.
So for the interval, we are going to say the residual ij is equal to residual...
Let's make it clearer.
Let's do zeros.
Size of b.
So rij would be equal to the right-hand side, which is bij, minus the Poisson's equation,
which is u0.
So we have u0 of i minus 1j plus u0 of i plus 1j plus u0 of ij minus 1 plus u0 of ij plus 1.
We have to minus 4 times u0 ij divided by delta x squared.
Right?
So we have...
We have the right-hand side minus the left-hand side of the Poisson's equation.
So b minus the second-order derivative of u in both x and y directions.
Right?
Okay.
So that is our residual calculation.
And...
Once we have the residual calculation, we want to interpolate this to a cos grid.
Oh, no. Cos.
So our interpolation to the cos grid would be something like that.
So we should have R...
Let's call it RC is equal to...
Uh...
I think we'll do exactly what you mentioned.
We will make a cos grid that is exactly twice as cos as the fine grid.
So it'll be zeros and interval divided by 2 plus 1.
So I still need the boundary conditions.
And the RC of 2, 2 and minus 1.
2, 2 and minus 1.
Would be a copy of my R.
So...
So let's see.
How should I perform that copying?
I have a fine grid.
Like this.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
And I want a cos grid that is twice as cos.
So cos grid would be like that.
So the cos grid starting from 95,
and then the cos grid starting from 95,
so the cos grid starting from number 2 should be the fine grid starting from number 3.
Right?
So I should be 3, 2 and minus 2.
3, 2 and minus 2.
So the second number here is the...
I'm gonna skip one.
I'm taking every two values.
Yes?
Minus 2.
Minus 2, yeah. Thank you.
Okay.
So now I have the interpolation to the cos grid.
On the cos grid,
I want to solve...
perform iterations on the cos grid.
So it's usually good just to perform a few iterations.
So let's make a cos grid,
dx,
du.
So that's the correction on u is...
Let's do zeros.
The size of RC.
So we'll make initial guess equal to zeros.
And let's do 10 iterations.
And let's use the Gauss-Seidel iterations.
So du is equal to Gauss-Seidel of du and my RC.
Okay.
And afterwards,
I'm going to interpolate the du to fine grid.
So here I want to interpolate R,
the residual to the cos grid.
Fine grid.
So interpolating the correction to the fine grid.
So duf,
that's my fine grid,
is equal to zeros,
the size of B here.
And here I really need interpolation.
Because my cos grid is only a fraction of the grids I have on the fine grid.
So duf does have some places where I don't need interpolation.
So these are the same points where I can just copy the values from du.
2 to n, 2 to n minus 1, 2 to n minus 1.
Right.
So these are the places I can perform my copying.
And afterwards,
I can just do a linear interpolation in both x and y directions.
Okay.
So first let's do a linear interpolation in the x direction.
So that would be if I start from 2 to 2 to n minus 1.
I still have the same values here.
Would be equal to 0.5 times the average,
that would be the average between the neighboring values.
So would be the average between 1 to 2 to n minus 2,
which is,
includes both the boundary value 0 at r equal to 1,
and all the other values I have already copied from the du on the cos grid.
And plus
my duf at now 3 to 2 to n.
So this is my interpolation in the x direction.
So now I have all the values at every i direction,
at all the i directions,
but at every other j direction I want to interpolate in the j direction.
So duf,
now every j direction is filled.
2 to 2 to n minus 1 in the j direction is,
I want to follow the same formula,
duf,
colon, 1 to 2 to n minus 2,
plus duf,
to 3 to 2 to n.
Okay, so that completes my interpolation of du to the fine grid.
Yes, yes, all the i directions, thanks.
All right, so now I'm going to add a correction to the solution.
So my u1 is going to be u0 plus duf.
All right, and I want to do and perform iterations on the fine grid.
So I'm going to for i goes from 1 to 10.
I'm going to perform 10 iterations on the fine grid.
u1 would be equal to gauss, seidel, u1 and my du.
All right, so that completes my multi-grid,
I mean two-grid solution.
All right, so let's try it.
If we see,
we have our, let's again make u equal to u0.
And previously we performed 100 iterations of gauss, seidel,
and we saw what we had, right?
So in here, because we have 20 iterations on the coarse grid,
20 iterations on the fine grid.
So let's only do 5 iterations.
Let's say u is equal to multi-grid of u and b.
Okay, now I get my u.
Let's look at what u looks like here.
Okay, so do you see some difference between the solution I get
with 100 gauss, seidel iterations
and what I get through 5 iterations of multi-grid?
Let's actually make another image and compare.
Figure u is equal to u0.
u is equal to u0.
And the 4i goes from,
let's just copy the code I think I had before.
Title gauss, seidel, 100 iterations.
So this is gauss, seidel after 100 iterations.
This is my multi-grid after 5 iterations,
which includes 50 coarse-grid iterations and 50 fine-grid iterations.
Do you see some difference or not?
Yes.
So the gauss, seidel iterations looks very,
only has very fine lines,
and the multi-grid has a lot more smoothness, right?
It has a lot more lower frequency content in it.
That probably means that there are some lower frequency content
in the solution that starts to converge faster in the multi-grid
than in the gauss, seidel, right?