So I'm going to show the Comfort Workflow via an example called a titanium
micro resistor actuator. This is not a blue flow related problem but it could
be. So imagine a bridge shaped beam that has two feet and then a bend. So basically
you apply it's a conductive material titanium. So when you apply a potential
bias across the two feet you're going to have current flow through it. And then
because of the current flowing then you're going to have resistive heating.
So the dual heating is going to generate heat and the entire structure is going to heat up.
So there is going to be a temperature gradient in the structure. Because there
is temperature gradient then it causes thermal stress. So this entire structure is
actually going to deform because of all that. So the problem definition here we
have the first physics which is the electric current simulation DC current
through conductive medium. And the second physics is the thermal conduction with
a dual heating element.
So the thermal conduction is going to be the heat source. So it's a purely conductive problem.
So the boundary condition we'll be setting will be will glue the two feet on a huge heat sink.
So the temperature remains unchanged to 93.15. And then for the rest of the surfaces we'll assume
they are adjacent to dry air so they actually subjected to conductive cooling.
And then the third physics is a solid mechanics problem with the thermal stress.
So to make the problem more interesting you can introduce the reverse coupling.
You can easily say through the temperature dependent material properties the electric conductivity is the function of the local temperature.
Alright so I'm going to start COMSOL.
Here it is.
And I'm going to start a new model.
So the two options you have on this first interface is you can either start with a blank model or start with a model wizard.
So the model wizard is basically the first of few steps of the
in your model workspace.
So I select the Model Wizard, and now it
asks me to select what's the space dimension
I want to work with.
So of course, in a more theoretical class,
you would always start with a more simple situation,
like a 0D or 1D problem.
0D, you don't have to create a geometry.
1D, you just draw a line with a certain length.
And then the other options would be the 1D and 2D axis
symmetric.
So 1D axis symmetric is essentially
equivalent to a 2D circle surface.
And then the 2D axis symmetric is
equivalent to a 3D rotation symmetry way.
Both the physics plus the load and the boundary conditions
have to be, plus material properties,
have to be axis symmetric in order to qualify for that.
And then there is also the 2D and 3D options.
So right now, I'm going to choose a 3D.
It's a 3D actual beam.
And then I'm going to choose the first physics
I want to solve for, which is the electric currents, right
under the ACDC folder.
So here, the physics are grouped not by modules,
but by application areas.
So I'm going to choose Add.
There is a little specification on what is the interface
and what it does.
It's going to solve for a capital case V, the electric
potential.
And I can move to the study node.
In this case, I'll choose the simplest, the stationary,
as the solver type.
Click on Done.
So now the model, we are finished its task.
Now you're in the main console graphical user interface.
We call this the GUI.
So in the GUI, you see I'm using a Windows system.
So the screen now gets divided into a few parts.
If you use a Mac or a Linux, you'll
see a slightly variant of this interface.
Instead of this console ribbon, we
call the console ribbon and tabs on the very top,
you would have a console toolbar, so a slightly condensed
version of it.
And then basically, on the ribbon,
you have the different tabs that goes from definition
to geometry to material, physics, mesh, study,
and results.
So that's the workflow I'm talking about from left
to right.
And the same thing here.
In the model builder, you have an inverted tree structure
with a root on the top and branches and nodes after it.
There are a few options because we dictated that during the
model wizard step.
But essentially, you go from top to bottom of this tree.
You will go from definition, geometry, material, physics,
mesh, study, to results.
So that's the workflow, too, from top to bottom of the tree.
You can change the sequence in any part of the model.
It's just a general guideline that once you
have all the steps aligned, you'll
eventually have the results.
So all the options here are either
through the buttons on the ribbon
or through the right clicks on the model builder tree.
So all the options are through the right click.
So when you're in doubt, right click.
And in the middle, we have a settings window.
So when you click on a certain node in the model builder tree,
you have the corresponding settings for it.
And then in the right, we have a graphics window
with many buttons.
Now it's a 3D geometry, so it shows the 3D coordinate.
And in the very bottom, we have messages, progress,
and log.
So in this case, we're going to start
with building the geometry in console.
So I'm going to start with a work plane.
So work plane is right here.
You see there are some 3D primitives.
And if you import, there is some CAD-defeaturing tools.
And there is also the, I want to emphasize,
the virtual operations.
For those of you who have complicated CAD geometries,
those would come in very handy.
And then after I created a work plane,
I essentially added a work plane step
under my geometry sequence.
And under that work plane 1, now you
might see the settings of work plane 1.
So horizontal plane, which I actually
want to change it to a vertical plane, so xz plane.
So under work plane 1, I have a plane geometry.
When I click on it, I go into the 2D workspace.
I could use the draw line operation
to sketch the profile of the beam very quickly.
So I do a series of left clicks and then a right click.
It forms an enclosed surface.
You could change that surface into a closed curve or open
curve as well.
And you see that each of the points
that I click on, the coordinates,
are documented as a Bezel polygon
in the geometry sequence.
So everything you do is documented in that model
builder tree.
And you can change those coordinates if you need to.
So this is actually a microbeam.
So I'm going to go back to the geometry.
And I'm going to go back to the geometry node.
Before I forget, change the default length unit
from meter to micrometer.
So now I don't have to type the e to the minus 6.
So now I have a 2D geometry.
I can right click on work plane 1, add an extrude.
And I'm going to extrude it for about 0.2 micron.
That should be good.
So now I have a 3D geometry with a 0.2 micron as the thickness.
So now that's the geometry step.
I'm going to go back to the geometry node
and move to the next one, which is the materials node.
I can right click, choose the first one, add material.
And it's going to browse to the console material library.
I'm going to choose the building.
The building folder actually comes with the base package.
So you always have it.
I can right click on the titanium materials,
add it to component 1, and close the add material panel here.
So now titanium is added to my material list.
And automatically, it assigns the properties
that I have.
The first material I pick will be assigned to all the domains.
So right now, there is only one domain.
And now it's going to use two of the properties.
So those properties are what the physics calls for.
And that's because in the physics,
it's assigned to domain number 1.
And the material property says from material.
So that's how the geometry node, the material node,
and the physics node all tie together.
If the material pick actually doesn't have that information
necessary, you're going to get a stop sign right here.
And when it goes through the solver,
it's going to give you an error message saying,
mat.epsn is missing, or something similar to that.
So always check the material property.
And then the next node is the physics node.
So as I said, you always follow the same workflow,
no matter what kind of physics you work with.
So you'll see that essentially, the first physics I added
has three default nodes.
You can tell they are the default from the uppercase D
on the icon.
So the default governing equation,
you can tell from the shape of the icon, which
is a field cylinder.
That means it's on the domain level.
So if you see the equations very quickly here,
that is the Laplacian type of equation we want to solve for.
And that applies to everywhere in the domain.
If you right click on electric currents,
you see the other options here.
That's other than the current conservation,
you also have terminals, the domain, force calculation,
and then a list of boundary conditions.
So right now, the default boundary
conditions is electrically insulated everywhere.
So no current goes in or out.
And dot j equals to 0.
And the initial value, essentially
in a stationary problem, that's the initial gas that
is 0 potential everywhere.
So we're happy with comparing these equations
with the equations we wrote down on the slide.
We're happy with the governing equations,
but we do need to replace some of the boundary conditions.
So I can do that by right clicking
the electric current physics, add a ground condition.
And now I can choose that boundary I want to work with.
So the graphics window in COMSOL works with a three button
mouse.
You can left click, rotate the view, right click,
handle the view, click on the center scroll wheel
as if it's a button, move up and down, it'll zoom in or out.
So with the combination of that, you
can very easily navigate to any part of the geometry.
And you can always go back to the default view
with those default buttons here.
So in this case, the ground is going
to be applied to one of the feet.
So I'm going to rotate.
And basically expose the foot.
And then hover my mouse over, do a single click.
So now boundary number one is being selected
to satisfy the ground condition.
If there is actually a very complicated geometry
that some surfaces are hidden inside the domain,
you could use the transparency option or the wire rendering
to have the different visualization.
And you can hover your mouse over and then
use the center scroll wheel to rotate
through the different surfaces, the different layers
of the geometry to get to the inside layers.
So again, that makes the selection easy.
You can also, in the definitions,
define some selection lists.
Like everything within this certain ball shape
belongs to one group, and they'll
satisfy the same condition through the model,
through the entire model, something like that.
The other condition I need to change
is the electric potential condition on the other foot.
And that's going to be 0.2.
And now you can see that the other foot is going to be 0.2.
Now, if I go back to electrical insulation,
surface number 1 and 10 are both overridden.
So they no longer satisfy that n dot j equals to 0.
Instead, they satisfy the one with the red triangles that
basically tells you what's the correspondence
communications between the different nodes.
All right, so that's it for the physics.
Any questions for the physics?
Could you say more about the red triangle
and how it's about to reach there?
Yeah, so when you click on electrical insulation,
the ground and electric potential
has the upward red triangle, meaning
that this condition gets later on overridden by the other two
conditions.
When you click on the ground, it says
that the electrical insulation has actually
definition on some boundary conditions
on the same boundaries, and it's overridden by the ground.
So it means those two nodes are actually
defined on the same space, and which one dominates which one.
So in terms of a lot of places, the sequence does not matter.
For example, if you have 10 different physics,
how they are actually sequenced in that component one,
it doesn't matter.
The only thing matters between the physics
is how you have the communication between them,
what's the coupling that's happening between the physics.
But the sequence of the boundary conditions do matter,
especially if you duplicate boundaries.
Then the later defined conditions
will override the earlier defined ones.
Some of the boundary conditions can coexist.
For example, natural convection and radiation
can coexist on the same surface in heat transfer problems,
and some conditions are not coexisting.
So what's the difference?
So the later defined ones will be the one effective.