And as we know, nobody can integrate time exactly.
So from your project, if you use OD45, I know some people see weird oscillations that can be reduced if you set the tolerance of OD45 to smaller.
Right? So that's because OD45 also don't know how to integrate things exactly.
But if now we don't know how to integrate things exactly, we may not have a stable solution, even with that good numerical scheme.
Yes, question?
To take a Fourier transform, does the system have to be stable in the first place?
The answer is no.
Because we are only taking Fourier transform to the function, to the solution at a particular time.
So if you draw y-axis as time, x-axis as time.
And y-axis as space.
We are only doing Fourier series to every horizontal slice of the solution.
And stability means as you go up in the time domain, does things blow up or does things not blow up?
So the Fourier series and the stability is analyzed on two different axes.
They commute. They don't interfere with each other.
Right.
So yes, if I'm taking Fourier series on the x-axis, I can't do anything.
But if I'm taking Fourier series on t, then I do have to make sure it is stable.
That's a good question.
Any other questions?
All right.
Space-time discretization.
So that's what we said.
Now if we further discretize the differential equation in time, then what we have is the system is no longer stable.
Always.
So how many people knows stability analysis of ODE solvers?
Like, forward Euler is stable if, anybody can answer the question?
Forward Euler is basically solving a differential equation.
Let's say x at k plus one over t.
Right.
So k plus one minus x k divided by delta t.
No delta x.
Let's say equal to lambda x k.
Right.
So that's for solving a scalar ODE.
It is stable if what?
Delta t is less than something.
Right.
Let's look at this equation.
All right.
So the way to analyze stability of ODE solvers is to look at the following.
So let's say here of ODE solver, explicit ODE solvers doing this.
It's moving all the known.
So let's imagine we are solving this at time step k.
What are the known numbers?
What are the unknown numbers?
x k is known.
x at k plus one is unknown.
Right.
We solve for x k plus one.
And then k plus one becomes my k.
And we go forward to solve for k plus two.
So I'm going to use red to specify the unknown and blue to specify the known.
So the way to analyze the stability is move all the unknowns to the left-hand side.
And move all the known to the right-hand side.
So x k over delta t is moved to here.
Bless you.
And.
And lambda x k is over here.
Which is combined into one over delta t plus lambda times x k.
And imagine.
And also multiply the delta t on both sides.
So we get x k plus one is equal to one plus delta t lambda times x k.
And you can do this exercise for all kinds of ODE solvers.
Including the schemes used in ODE 45.
I mean ODE 45 uses two schemes.
A fourth order scheme and a fifth order scheme.
That's why it is called 4-5.
And it adapts its time step by comparing the error, the difference between the fourth order
scheme and the fifth order scheme.
If they agree pretty well, it thinks the solution is accurate enough and keeps going.
Otherwise it tries to reduce delta t to make it better.
So.
So you can do the same thing for there.
Just to move all the unknowns to the left-hand side.
Move all the knowns to the right-hand side.
So.
So you can do the same thing for there.
Just to move all the unknowns to the left-hand side.
And remember here lambda can be complex.
So for what values of lambda delta t would this equation be stable?
If I draw a complex plan for delta t lambda.
So this is the real part.
This is imaginary part.
Delta t lambda.
Which part of the complex domain is this iteration.
Stable.
Meaning not going to infinity.
Right part.
Huh?
Right part of the domain.
So if my lambda delta t is for example 1.
Is the iteration going to be stable?
If lambda delta t is equal to 1.
1 plus 1 is going to be 2.
That means xk plus 1 is equal to 2.
xk plus 1 is equal to 2.
So.
Is it stable?
The xk?
Is that stable?
No.
Right?
If you multiply by 2.
I get thousand times.
After eight.
After 10 iterations.
I get a million.
After 20 iterations.
I get a trivial after 30 iterations.
Ok.
It goes to infinity pretty fast.
Yes?
Within the circle of unity?
One.
Like this.
.
Now imagine if I draw a point here, delta t lambda equal to half.
1 plus delta t lambda is equal to 2 third.
No, 3, like 1.5.
I get xk plus 1 equal to 1.5 times xk.
Is that stable?
No.
Not again.
Yes?
A circle of radius 1 and dot 1.8 of 1?
About negative 1.
So your answer is negative 1.
I draw a circle like that.
That's the right answer.
Because if delta t lambda is within this circle,
then 1 plus delta t lambda is going to be in this dashed circle.
Right?
And the dashed circle has a modulus less than 1.
And the modulus less than 1,
is what we need for this iteration to be stable.
To not grow.
The magnitude of xk plus 1 is equal to the modulus of this complex number
times the magnitude of xk.
So you need something that is less than unity
for the iteration to be stable.
All right.
So that's for this scalar equation.