But let's say I want to solve this algebraic equation, just finding roots, right?
I want to solve u cubed is equal to 8 for u.
Now the template is f of everything is 0.
So then you have to write it in this template, right?
Then what you will do is you specifically write u cubed minus 8, because that is going to be 0.
And then you put your initial value.
So let's see how to solve this.
File, new, model wizard.
This is going to be a 0D problem.
There is no special variation to it.
I come to this, global ODAs and DAEs.
I add this.
I'm going to solve a stationary problem.
I'm done.
Now, here I write I'm going to solve for u.
And the equation is I'm not going to say u cubed is equal to 8.
I have to write whatever it is needs to be set to 0.
So now u cubed minus 8.
And what's the initial value?
Well, for a stationary problem, that's meaningless.
For time dependent problem, I mean, for time dependent problem, it's meaningful.
But for a stationary problem, it's only a numerical item.
Let me compute this.
This is a reasonably simple problem, right?
We even know the solution.
But it's saying, we have to find a solution.
What do you think is going on?
Huh?
Anybody?
Let's think in terms of just real, whatever.
Yeah.
If we talk, if we assume it's going to be a real solution.
Let me show you the equation.
Okay.
I was solving it anyway.
Here.
Okay.
Any suggestions?
Yes?
Okay.
to change the integral value.
Yeah.
You're the new expression in the class.
So anyway, let's assume we are solving this using the Newton
method, right?
If we are solving this with the Newton method,
we're trying to form f of u is equal to 0 for u.
We don't know how to approach this,
but we can always state it, right?
This is actually a question I always ask myself.
When I run into a new numerical problem that I don't know how
to deal with, you ask yourself, what would Taylor do?
Once I Google, what would Taylor do?
And there are and one piece for what would Taylor do?
But it's for Taylor Swift.
That is a point that I know there would be for .
But anyway, so the way you do it, you
are trying to find.
You are trying to find a distance, a displacement that
will take you closer to your solution.
And if you put the Taylor expansion of this,
then you are going to have f prime of u delta u.
And we ignore the I-order terms.
So now if you set this to be 0 in a one-dimensional case,
I mean in a scalar problem, what you're getting
is the distance you need to move on is going to be f of u
over mu.
So you're going to have f prime of u negative.
And if f prime is 0, or if this is a scalar,
your vector system of equations you are solving,
f minus f, which is the residual, is going
to be your Jacobian matrix like this.
And if this is singular, you're going to run into a problem.
And here we are solving u cubed minus 8.
What is the root?
The derivative.
3u squared.
Check it out.
It's 0.
So that's what we are getting here.
So let's change the initial value and recompute.
And our solution here, if I evaluate, it's 2.
So that was the problem with the initial starting point.
So all these ideas that you keep talking
in your numerical analysis classes, they have consequences.
And a lot of times when we have people difficulty using the software,
it's because you miss things like this.
And then we'll be like, hey, why isn't this working?
This is really a simple problem.
And you guys cannot solve this and pay me back.
Anyway, moving on.
Since Comsol doesn't distinguish in this interval,
you don't have different interfaces for algebraic and global equations.
So before I actually go to differential equations,
I want to talk a little bit about domain algebraic equations.
What we solve now is a global algebraic equation.
But let's say we want to solve a problem.
Instead of u cubed being equal to 8,
you want to solve u cubed is equal to some function of location.
So what is going to happen?
Every point is going to have its own solution.
At every point, the problem is algebraic.
But it is going to have different parameters.
So in any problem like this,
you're going to have an algebraic field equation.
For example, when you are solving sometimes multiphysics problems,
there will be some kind of dynamic constraints
between different variables, some algebraic constraints.
And sometimes you know that directly, one in terms of the other.
So you have, let's say maybe you know p is some function of temperature
and other quantity.
If you know this, you can just directly type this.
But most of the time, you have some implicit equation, right?
p, d, whatever is of 0.
And at every point, this algebraic relation has to be satisfied.
But then every point has its own solution.
So that's what you use domain algebraic equations for instead of global.
Just like that, we also have global and domain ODEs.
Let's say we are solving this population projection problem,
the local prey-predator equation.
Which one is the prey and which one is the predator in this equation?
Between u and v, if one was prey and one was predator.
Predator.
Look at the interaction terms.
Assuming all coefficients are positive,
a1, b1, a2, b2 are all positive.
Or non-negative at least.
u is the prey.
u is the prey, why would you say that?
Because when u and v meet, it's...
Yeah, basically when u and v meet, it's u's damage and v's gain.
So u is the prey, the other one is the predator.
So the way to specify this is we don't differentiate between algebraic and global equations.
You use the same global equation interface.
The only thing is...
I already have a solved model for this.
The only thing that you have to consider here is
when you enter this equation,
now instead of just being an algebraic equation, you are going to have derivatives.
Remember when we talked about derivative operators?
So if I...
Here also you enter everything is equal to 0.
So if I want du over dt is equal to something,
I would move the right-hand side to the left.
And I would write du over dt minus a1 u1 minus u over k minus b1 v is equal to 0.
Initial values of this I have parameterized here.
Initial prey and predator concentrations, carrying capacity,
these interaction terms.
But...
So now if you have this,
then you have to add the time-dependent solvers, specify the time you want,
and you just solve that.
So for example here what I get is for the initial values I started with,
the prey population goes down,
the predator population goes up.
At some point it runs out of food,
so then it will start...
declining.
But the major point here is that the global differential and algebraic equations,
they are just time derivatives, no special derivative.
You use the same interface.
Clear so far?
Okay.
Now...
We can have domain ODEs as well.
Here it's global ODEs.
Let's think about this.
Instead of talking about population projection,
maybe this is prey-predator relationship in one area,
let's say you are talking about a whole area.
Then different areas can have their own carrying capacity.
Different areas can have their own...
populations.
Maybe prey-predator interactions are going to have different outcomes based on location.
Maybe there is climate effect.
There's a special effect.
But...
Still what we are having is ordinary differential equations at every point.
So here what we are assuming is there is no interaction between population at one point
or at another point.
So every point is independent of the neighbors.
So there is no keeping up with the Genesis or with the Cartesian
or whoever it is that people keep up with now.
Every point has its own evolution.
Irrespective of what happens on the neighbors.
But every point is different from another point.
So it's not a global equation.
Now the question here is how will this equation, this population model, become a partial differential equation?
Now we have...
I've made domain ODEs from global ODEs.
Can it become a PDE?
Any idea how it can become a PDE?
Any physical effects that can be treated to be mythic about it?
When we had a single population, this population equation was something like this.
For example, the predetermined population is going to be...
This derivative is going to be something containing U and W.
Can I have this term?
In this equation.
Is there any physical effect that can ever make it have this?
Transport?
Transport.
So in terms of population, what would that be?
Migration.
Yep.
This is not a proposal to solve today.
Especially...
What?
We prepared the presentation before.
Anyway, if you have migration, then we can assume...
One thing to assume is people migrate from high concentrated areas to low concentrated areas.
Maybe if that is the effect, you will have diffusion.
And you have an advection term in this equation.
So now if you have migration where people want to run away from high concentration areas,
you can have the advection term, the diffusion term.
But can you have any advection, any reason for adding advection?
Yeah, what would it be?
Yeah, so in terms of population projection, population analysis problem,
what would be an advection effect?
What would motivate...
Basically advection is...
Diffusion is you move based on the concentration, right?
Whereas advection is just a velocity irrespective of the concentration.
You have it with us.
People moving in a certain direction, and that's not going to be concentration dependent.
Why would that happen?
Why would anything like that happen?
.
Yeah, something like that.
Like more food or like some resource.
Remember the California boat rush, for example, right?
People find out, oh, there is good things at that place.
So irrespective of whatever population you have in this place, you might want to move.
So in that case, you might add advection terms.
The diffusion coefficient is positive.
What if we have negative diffusion coefficient?
.
So what is the assumption in having a positive diffusion coefficient?
We're saying move motion away from high concentration area.
What would then making that negative mean?
.
Huh?
Yeah, right?
What would that make out of the country?
.
It makes that, it helps everything, stuff that you can find, make it more obvious,
why it is happening, where nothing's happening.
.
and if migration is just to the higher direction,