So the second equation we are going to look at is another limiting case. So that's actually limiting case number two.
An elliptic equation. So that is the case where u is equal to zero and t goes to infinity.
We have just said that when u is equal to zero, we get the heat equation.
If we have f equal to zero. And as t goes to infinity on that heat equation, we recover a constant.
So that is in the case where we don't have a right-hand side f.
If we do have a right-hand side f, the equation becomes kappa times partial square u partial x squared plus f is equal to zero.
And we can in general study the case where kappa is equal to one.
Because if kappa is not equal to one, as long as it is non-zero, we can divide the whole equation by kappa.
And we replace f with f divided by kappa. And we get the same thing.
So let's remove this kappa from this equation and study that.
This equation is called the Poisson's equation.
And the solution to that equation can also be analyzed using Fourier series.
So in this case, we only have x. We don't have t.
And strictly speaking, this is an OD. We should have d instead of partials.
But most of the time when we talk about Poisson's equation,
we are describing the Poisson's equation as a partial square.
And we are discussing multiple dimensions in space.
So let me write this as a partial, even in the one-dimensional space case.
We are going to expand u of x using Fourier series again.
k equal to minus infinity to infinity.
u hat of k, u to the i kx.
And the second derivative is going to become b.
So we are going to have minus k is equal to minus infinity to infinity.
k square times u hat of k times e to the i kx.
Okay. I'm also going to expand f, which can be a function of time,
using Fourier series.
We have f hat of k instead of u hat of k for the coefficients of f.
Now, matching the two sides of the equation, both using Fourier expansion,
we have, if we plus that equal to zero,
what we have is k square of u hat of k has to equal to f hat of k.
Okay. So what does that mean?
What does this equation mean for k equal to zero,
for k equal to a small number, small can include negative or positive,
for small absolute value k, and for a large absolute value k?
For k equal to zero, we can see that f hat of k has to be zero.
Otherwise, we don't have a solution.
That's because the domain is periodic.
And as we take t to infinity for the heat equation case,
the f is like a heat source.
It's like a source of thermal energy that pumps into the domain.
So if you have a non-zero average or a non-zero integral
in the amount of heat you pump into the system,
then the temperature is going to keep increasing to infinity
or keep decreasing.
So if you have a non-zero average or a non-zero integral
in the amount of heat you pump into the system,
then the temperature is going to keep increasing to minus infinity.
You don't have a steady state solution,
which is what this equation is describing,
a steady state solution.
You will only have a steady state solution
if f hat of zero is equal to zero.
So that's the first thing this equation tells me.
f hat, for the other case, it can be arbitrary value.
And then I can have a solution u hat of k
is equal to f hat of k divided by k square.
Right.
So it takes the Fourier components of f
and divide it by k square.
Divided by small number for small k
by a big number for big k.
This is almost a filtering in space,
a low pass filtering in space.
Because it takes the very high weight numbers,
takes the very oscillatory components of f
and decrease that by a large factor
while taking the smoother components of f
and decrease that only by
a smaller factor.
So this is a,
some variation of this, this equation
has been used in numerical methods
to serve as a filter, a low pass filter.
And this is called a differential filter
because it uses a differential operator
to achieve the effect of removing
the high frequency components while preserving
the low frequency components.
All right.
So that's the effect of the second limiting case
of time goes to infinity while the u is equal to zero.
Question?
What's the condition that you wrote next to the bracket
when equals zero?
Oh, I'm saying these two terms added together
has to be equal to zero.
Okay.
Yeah.
So that's substituting these into the differential equation,
into the Poisson's equation.
Thanks.
Okay.
Any other questions?
Thanks for clarifying.
Yeah?
Why is there only a steady state solution
if f naught is equal to zero?
when f naught is equal to zero?
This is because if f naught is not equal to zero,
okay, so for example, if f is equal to one as a constant,
that means f naught is equal to one and all the other f hats
are equal to zero.
If you actually add the time derivative term,
so let's actually analyze the other case.
Okay.
So if you write down a partial derivative of t
is equal to kappa partial square u,
partial x square plus f,
and let's say u naught,
u of x, t equal to zero is equal to,
is equal to any, let's say is equal to zero
and f of x is equal to a constant one.
Okay.
What is the solution going to be?
Can you just look at the initial condition?
The right hand side and the equation
and guess what the solution should be?
Linear growth.
I would have u of x and t equal to t, right?
That solution is always a constant of in space,
so the second of the derivative in space goes to zero
and the time derivative is always equal to one
which matches the right hand side.
So I would have linear growth.
Okay.
And by the principle of linear superposition,
if you have any initial condition and any f,
as long as the f naught term is not equal to zero,
you can express the solution as a linear combination
of a solution that has f equal to zero
and another solution that is equal to this.
So that solution with f naught is equal to zero
is going to stay bounded
and this solution grows
to infinity.
So when you perform linear superposition
of these two solutions,
you're going to get a solution that goes to infinity.
So there doesn't exist a steady state solution.
Yes?
Could you please go to the previous slide?
This might be a very long question,
but the baseline counterline,
isn't that one fully dictating that f naught should be zero?
Because with p equal to zero,
we have zero.
So zero equals f zero.
Yes.
Isn't that just that?
That's a mathematical way of answering the question
why f hat of zero has to be zero.
And the physical way to answer the question
is what I was describing.
Yeah.
Any other questions?
So in this case,
f is only an explicit function of x
rather than some function of u?
Oh, yes.
In this case,
f is a function of x only.
It's not a function of u.
Yeah, that's right.
And if f is a function of u,
then especially if f is a nonlinear function of u,
then we get into the field of nonlinear differential equations
that cannot be analyzed using Fourier series.
Yeah.
All right.
Any other questions?
And that's a great case for solving the equation numerically.
Thank you.