We are often asking a question, when does the Jacobi iteration converge?
When does it not converge?
And it is very hard to figure out a necessary condition for the convergence.
It's very hard to figure out a sufficient and necessary condition for the convergence.
But there are sufficient conditions for the convergence of Jacobi iteration, which means
there are some conditions you can check, and if it satisfies this condition, then you know
Jacobi iteration is going to converge.
So for example, one of the methods to check the convergence of a Jacobi iteration is called
a diagonal dominance.
What does diagonal dominance mean?
If you have a matrix.
The diagonal entries.
Of A, of this matrix A. A , A , etc. to A .
The absolute values of the diagonal entries, if they are larger than the sum of the absolute
values of all of its off-diagonals.
Okay so let's say A, the off-diagonals, I will just use another color to denote it.
A , A , etc.
So if the absolute value of A for any k is greater than the summation of I not equal
to k of A absolute value.
This is called diagonal dominance.
Actually this is called strict diagonal dominance.
If you have greater or equal.
A non-strict diagonal dominance.
Remember for our Poisson's equation, do we have strict diagonal dominance?
No, but we have the weaker non-strict diagonal dominance, right, because the diagonals are
minus two and the off-diagonals, we have two off-diagonals, both one and one.
In the 2D Poisson's equation the diagonal is minus four.
The off-diagonals, we have four ones.
In 3D, the diagonal is minus one.
Okay.
the diagonal would be minus 6 and we have 6 off-diagonals. And if you remember
our finite element case when we solve the Poisson's equation, we also have a
non-strict version of diagonal dominance. Alright, so if a matrix is diagonally
dominant, we know that Jacobi iteration converges. So how do we know that? We need
use a theorem called theêug Positive circle theorem. So what
does that mean? It means the eigenvalues of a matrix, so the lambda k of a matrix
are the lambda k has to lie in at least the one of the so
called a digestible
matrix. So every ment realtà pose uma esn da equação blindada...
circle. So every lambda k must be within a circle that is defined as all the lambdas,
such that lambda minus one of the diagonals is less or equal to the summation of the i not equal to k, a, i, or a, k, i.
So in the complex plane, this is a circle.
It's a circle centered at a, k, k with a diameter of the summation of the absolute value of the diagonal entries.
Okay, that means all the eigenvalues have to lie in the union of all the Gershgorin circles.
And each Gershgorin circle corresponds to one row of the matrix.
So why is that the case?
It's the case because if we have a eigenvalue, let me say a times vk equal to lambda k times vk.
Okay, so if that is the case, let's pick.
So, okay, so let's actually use j here.
Instead of k.
So a times vj is equal to lambda j times vj.
So let's pick k such that vkj, so the kth entry of the vector vj, has greatest magnitude.
Okay.
Which means vkj.
vkj is greater than vij for any i not equal to k.
All right, greater or equal.
So why is this helpful?
It's helpful because we can write this equality.
We can write the specific line of that equality as the summation of that particular line of the matrix,
which is a.
So vkj times vij would be equal to the corresponding line of the right-hand side, which is lambda j times what?
What is the corresponding row of lambda j times vj?
If I choose the kth row.
Vkj.
Yeah, vkj, right.
Great.
So now let's try to move all the vkj's to one side and all the non-vkj's to the other side.
What we get is akk times vkj minus lambda j times vkj would be equal to the minus of the summation of all the i not equal to j of aki times vij.
Okay.
Ki times Vij.
Oh, by the way, I have moved the absolute value from outside the summation to inside the summation.
Therefore, we have a less or equal to sign.
So we have a less or equal because just moving the absolute value to here.
Vkj.
And also we know this is strictly less or equal to 1.
Because we have chosen Vkj to be the largest among all the Vij's.
So this again is going to be a summation.
Oh, here we also have absolute value.
Summation i not equal to k, absolute value of aki.
Right?
So here we prove the Gershgorian theorem.
Basically, all the eigenvalues have to lie in one of these circles.
And fortunately, for a diagonally dominant matrix, the Jacobi iteration matrix,
has Gershgorian theorem.
It has Gershgorian's circles that are very friendly to us.
In the sense that the minus D inverse times L plus U would be equal to a matrix that is minus 0 on the diagonal.
Because we already removed the diagonal, we are looking at L plus U.
And all the diagonal entries are, for example,
a12 divided by a11, a13 divided by a11, etc.
So the Gershgorian circles are centered at 0 because all the akks are 0.
Right?
So if you look at the complex plane, all the circles are centered at 0.
How about the diameters?
The diameters are the summation of the absolute value of all these diagonal entries.
And we know that if we are diagonally dominant,
the a11 is the absolute value of all these diagonal entries.
And we know that if we are diagonally dominant, the a11 is the absolute value of all these diagonal entries.
So this A1 would be greater than the summation of all the absolute values of the diagonal entries.
So the diameter, which is the summation of all these absolute values, would be less than what?
1.
Right.
So all the Gershgorian circles would be centered at around 0 with various diameters,
but all of them are less than 1.
What does that mean in terms of the eigenvalues of the Jacobi iteration matrix?
This is not the answer.
There are 4 different argumentations.
But there are 4 different arguments about the force of these numbers.
So this is a very complex problem.
Very lost argument.
Thank you very much.
they have to lie on a circle that has to be strictly within the stability region, right?
So basically all the eigenvalues have to have its magnitude less than 1.
Therefore, for diagonally dominant matrices, we are guaranteed to converge.
And we can also have a similar argument of saying that for non-strictly diagonally dominant matrices like the Poisson's equation,
we would have some Gershgorian circles that are exactly having a radius of 1.
Okay.
So then what we know is all the eigenvalues of the Jacobi iteration matrix,
they cannot have magnitude greater than 1.
But they can potentially have magnitude equal to 1.
That means you may have some moles that are never decaying, but like you shouldn't diverge.
Your Jacobi iteration
could be
basically the error equation, in the error equation, the error could be constant.