if you are if you're using any discretization method you know that more
and you have the more accurate the solution is but this tells you the
bigger the n is the slower if you have to use it with method the slower the
solution is going to converge so there is a trade-off that okay if you have
finite amount of computation time you may you can you have to balance if you
increase n you should not only expect your solution your calculations to be to
be more for each iteration you would also expect the number of iterations to
go up or you can you have to trade off between your discretization error and
the error in the
solution of the linear equation so is it possible to have the best in both
worlds is it possible to both have the fast convergence in the linear solver in
the iterative solver you would get for small n and also the accuracy you would
get for bigger it turns out is quite possible the idea is the following
okay so let's see if this is possible to get the solution of the linear equation
What if you can have a method that uses multiple Ns?
So one is a finer grid with a bigger N discretizing a PD that is more accurate
and also a small N, you know the solution in your intuitive method would converge faster.
Okay, and the smaller N would only be able to deal with the solution that can be represented on the coser grid.
But that helps a lot because if you think of, so let me take an example of a Poisson's equation.
Again.
So for Poisson's equation, in 1b we know that this mode converges the slowest.
The rate of convergence of this mode is proportional to n squared, right?
So the iterations you need.
But this mode is actually the easiest mode to represent on the very very coarse grid.
This mode you can potentially
only use three grid points to represent this mode.
With three points, one, two intervals, the number of intervals equal to two.
And with n equal to two, cosine of pi over n is something what?
Is cosine of pi over two is what?
Zero.
Right.
So for the eigenvalue equal to zero, what does it mean?
One.
We converged in one iteration.
Exactly.
So the mode that is most difficult to deal with in a very fine grid is something actually
that is easiest to tackle in a coarse grid.
Right.
Because the mode is very smooth.
And can be potentially very difficult to deal with.
Right.
represented on the very coarse grid and converges in one iteration.
And of course we also have modes that are cosine 2 pi over n, 3 pi over n, etc.
These won't be able to be represented on the n equal to 2 grid.
But if you can design a series of grids, n equal to 2, n equal to 4, n equal to 8, etc.,
all the way to our case where n equal to 1024,
then for every single mode, there should be one of these grids
that you can represent that mode with sufficient accuracy,
and that mode would decrease pretty fast over that grid.
So that's the idea of multigrid.
And so how do we implement multigrid?
So the multigrid is, we can represent the procedure as the following.
So the x-axis is the algorithm,
which means as we perform, as the computer performs subsequent operations,
we are moving along the x-axis.
The y-axis is the grid.
And the y-axis is the grid.
Okay.
And if you go up, it's a finer grid.
And going down is a coarser grid.
So multigrid would always start with the finest grid.
So the finest grid is where we discretize the equation
because on that grid, we have a lot of grids.
So we have a lot of grids.
So on that grid, we can compute what the right-hand side is.
On that grid, we have the matrix.
We have the right-hand side.
So on that grid, we compute the b minus ax that we call the residual.
And we can think of all what we are doing in iterative method
is to compute is going to have a successively better approximation to x
in order to drive the result.
So we can compute the residual r to zero.
So this is our first approximation.
And then what we are doing in the coarser grids
is to solve for the correction.
So what is the correction?
So for delta x such that a times delta x is equal to a times delta x.
So if we can solve for the correction,
what we can do is we can solve for a times delta x
would be equal to this r.
Let me see if that's the case.
Yes, would be equal to r.
So if we can solve a times delta x equal to r,
then my x zero because I know that my a times x zero
would equal to b minus r, right?
So this is a rearrangement.
So here's the B minus r.
So this is actually a B minus r.
So this is a B minus r.
of the definition of R so let's see then a times X 0 plus Delta X 0 the
correction would be equal to B does that make sense so instead of solving
directly for X we can solve this correction equation a times Delta X
equal to R where R is the residual of my best guess yet and if we can exactly
solve the correction equation we get the exact solution and but even if we can
approximately solve this correction equation we get a better approximation
to the solution by adding the original solution
with my Delta X and why are we doing this in multi-grid we are doing this in
multi-grid because as we go to causal grids we no longer have an as good
approximation to the differential equation as in the final grid and what
we want is that if on the final grid we already have a very good solution which
we hope is true as we move towards the right-hand side of the algorithm
you
if we already have a good solution we don't want to spoil it in the in the
course grid right therefore we want to solve this correction equation because
if we already have a very good solution that R should be very small and the
resulting Delta X would always hopefully give an improvement to the solution
instead of the other way if we keep solving the original equation on the
coarse grid then you'll be able to solve this equation without making a big change to the solution.
the cross grid would always have a mismatch with the final grid and that's something we don't want
we always want the cost of grades to improve upon the best solution we have on the final grid
we want the whole solution to converge the solution of the final grid
so when we go to the cross grid we want to interpolate we first want to interpolate
the residual r0 to cost grid
once we interpolated r0 now my r0 is on the cost grid then i solve my delta x 0
is equal to is approximately equal to a inverse
times r0 and how do we do this approximation we can perform a few jacobi iterations or a few
a few gauss-seidel iterations remember on the cost of grids the moles that we can represent
on the closer grid would always converge faster than how they would converge in the fine grid
okay so once we solved this we can now
go back and interpolate the delta x 0 to fine grid
so this is a two grid algorithm we have one fine grid one cross grid we are going to generalize to
a multi-grid pretty soon and then we perform x 1 would be equal to x 0 plus that delta x 0
of zero coming from the cost grid
okay and now we are going to do this again but before we do this this again we want to perform
a few other iterations on the fine grid and what is the purpose of of performing a few
jacobi or gauss-seidel iterations on the on the fine grid the purpose is to get the residual
to be at a good enough state to be smooth enough so that the residual can be interpolated
to the cost grid all right okay so so here we move towards uh uh iterations on fine grid
and then go back again so so we go back and
compute the residual and interpolate the residual to the cross grid and perform iterations on the
on the cross grid and interpolate the correction back to the fine grid
okay so so the two so the uh so the ingredients that are important is one computing
residual so that's over here and the interpolating
residual to the cost of grids
and the three is uh
is uh iteration iterative solver on both course
and course and
fine grid
and four is interpolating
not the residual but the solution
to find a grid
so once we have all these four components we can put together a multi-grid solver all right
any questions so far on this uh overall uh oh any other uh if there's any other uh questions that I have as well?
I think that's it for this video, I hope you have a good one and I hope to see you in the next one.
So thanks for watching and I will see you in the next video.
Thank you all and have a nice day.
idea yes oh yes actually if you can design the grid so that you don't need
interpolation that will be great so then the interpolation is a trivial
interpolation that's right just picking the values right