When we are performing a minimization, we are performing it over all possible functions that satisfies a certain criterion.
And these all possible functions is what we call the space.
And here I'm going to give two examples of that space over here.
So the first example is x is the space.
And the space is a set of functions.
It's a collection of functions that satisfy a certain criterion.
For example, is f of x between 0 and 1 such that for all i.
Okay.
So for all the i.
We are still representing the space using a finite number of intervals.
And these intervals are now what we call elements.
And for reasons I'm going to discuss a little bit later, let's now, instead of labeling the elements as integers,
let's label the element boundaries as integers.
1, 2, 3, 4, etc.
So for all the i's.
Let's see.
fx is linear in x in xi minus 1 and xi.
Okay.
So this is one class of functions.
So can somebody tell me does this correspond to this case or the previous case?
This one, right?
Because.
Because I'm no longer requiring my x to be continuous.
So.
So for example, when i is equal to 1, when x is in x0 and x1, the function is linear like this.
In between 1 and 2, the function can be like that.
Okay.
So I can have a function that is like that to approximate whatever function I want to approximate.
The second case, which is the case we're going to discuss in this lecture.
Is putting an additional constraint on the function.
And f is continuous.
Continuous.
And for all the i, fx is linear.
In x.
x.
i minus 1 and xi.
So this is a space that I require the function to be not only piecewise linear but continuous.
So these are these kind of piecewise lines that I can draw with one stroke.
Okay.
Now.
What I claim is that this space of x satisfies a particular.
Particularly nice properties called linearity.
So what does linearity mean?
Linearity means that if I have x1 and x2 both in the space x.
Okay.
So linearity.
So this is not linearity of the function but linearity of the function space.
Right.
That's different from the linearity of the function f.
Linearity of the function f just says like f is a straight line.
If you put it like this.
You plot it.
But linearity of the function space is something different.
It's saying that for any pair of f1 and f2 in that linear space.
a1 times f1 plus a2 times f2 is also in the space for any real numbers a1 and a2.
Alright.
So.
Any linear combination of any two elements in the space also belongs to the same space.
That is linearity.
So in this case why is the case?
Why is this particular space linear?
So let's check it.
First of all if I have a function like that.
If I scale the function by a real number.
The scaled function.
Let's say if I scale it to a little bigger.
The scaled function would look like that.
Of course it's still continuous.
And of course for every interval the scaled function is also linear.
Right.
So if I have f1 in x.
a1 times f1 is also in x.
Again if I have f2 in x.
a2 times f2 is also in x.
This is pretty much linear.
This is because scaling is invariant.
Scaling is.
I mean the x is invariant to scaling.
And also if I have both a1 f1 and a2 f2 in the space.
Adding them together the sum of two continuous functions is continuous.
And the sum of two linear functions is linear.
So.
a1 f1 plus a2 f2 is also.
Continuous and piecewise linear.
Therefore we can prove that x is a linear space.
By simply arguing about the properties of the functions.
It has to satisfy.
Alright.
Any questions so far?
Okay.
Now.
We need to introduce the concept.
Once we have a linear space.
A linear space is particularly nice.
That it has this thing called a basis.
Okay.
A basis in a linear space.
x1 x2 all the way to xn for example.
Is a basis.
So this is a basis.
Of x.
If and only if.
The following properties are satisfied.
So first of all.
For any x.
In that linear space.
X can be represented as a linear combination.
Of these basis.
Alright.
So this is the first property.
But that's not the case.
Because.
The first property.
Is the linear space.
And the second property.
And the third property.
Is the linear space.
And the fourth property.
So this is the first property.
But that's not enough.
Another property is that.
For any.
Another property.
Let me just say like this.
Another property is that.
This representation.
Is unique.
So.
For any x.
The.
The set of.
A i's.
Is.
A x.
And a x.
Is.
A x.
And a x.
Is.
A x.
And a x.
Is.
A x.
And a x.
Is.
A x.
And a x.
Such that.
A x.
Is.
Such that.
X.
Is.
E.
Equal to.
A i.
X.
I.
So.
This is i.
Is.
Unique.
So you can't find.
Two.
Different.
Set of.
clues you from having a basis in which xn can be represented as a linear
combination of x1 x2 to xn-1. Because if you can do that, xn is of course a
member of x, right? And then xn has two different representations. One
representation is that xn is equal to a summation where all the a i's are zero
except for a n which is 1. So xn is equal to xn. And also it has a different
representation using only the values x1 to xn-1. So the
representation of a summation of a i is not unique, right? So basically if we
have property 2 that means any members of the basis cannot be represented as a
linear combination of the other members.
Okay.
Also it means if we have a basis we cannot add anything onto the basis. So if
we add any other members of x onto the basis it becomes no longer a basis.
Because if we add another member that that additional member would be able to
be represented either just as a linear combination of itself or as a linear
combination of the previous set of basis.
Okay.
Any questions so far?
So the basis is very useful because it reduces an optimization problem. It reduces a least
squares problem just like what we saw before. From a least squares problem in the abstract
function space to a least squares problem that a computer can solve.
Okay.
So that's the basic.
Thank you.
So but we'll have to think about how to solve a least squares problem in a bunch of
numbers. So for example if I want to say I want to minimize the distance. We're going
to define what the distance should be before or a little bit later. Between the distance
between any function f and x for all x in the linear space, x. Right so if we want to solve that minimization problem.
Right so if we want to solve that minimization problem.
Right.
minimization problem. It's pretty tricky because I'm minimizing over a function space that I don't
know how to choose. But I can transform that minimization problem because any x in x can be
represented as a linear combination. I can minimize over all the possible a's that is in Rn,
right? So if the basis has n entries, the distance between f and that linear combination
of xi. So I know I'm minimizing over a space of n numbers, and that is something I can solve
with the computer. So that's why basis is useful, okay?
Now let's discuss... Yeah?
That's a good question. What if the basis is not finite? Actually, for some function spaces,
the basis is infinite. For example, you can simply choose x to be all functions that are
continuous. So if you have a function space that is infinite, and you want to write it as a linear
continuous, it don't require x to be piecewise linear or anything. In that case, you actually
cannot find a finite set of basis. You can still have a basis, but the basis is going to be an
infinite set. It's not a finite set. And in that case, this particular problem cannot be transformed
into a finite dimensional optimization problem. That is why in finite element, there is this word
finite, okay? We need to construct...
Because the space of functions, as you can see, it's of my choice. I can choose what function space
I want to operate in. Therefore, I need to choose a function space that I can actually construct
a finite set of basis. And that enables me to transform any minimization problem. So this is
just for approximating a function, a known function. I'm going to tell you a little bit later, like,
how to do the same for approximating an unknown function, which is a solution for PDE using the same
framework. We are also going to be able to translate that into a finite dimensional optimization problem.