I think in your project 1, a lot of you are formulating your problem into optimization problems.
And for those of you who were not lucky and you formulated your objective function,
if you formulated your problem into a very high-dimensional optimization problem,
you notice that the optimization problem can be very difficult to solve.
Low-dimensional optimization problem with a few parameters,
for example, if my n is equal to 2, I should be able to solve these problems with no difficulty.
But you can imagine for very complex functions, I may need a large n to have a good approximation.
So it's not trivial how to solve general optimization problems of high dimensions.
But if I define the distance in a particularly good way,
the optimization problem...
can turn out to be very easy to solve.
So, for example, if I define the distance between two functions f and x to be the following.
To be the square root of the integral over domain, let's say a and b, f minus x squared.
Maybe I shouldn't use x here.
So f and g, let's say, dx.
Square root.
All right, that's the least squares distance, right, between the functions f and g.
Okay, so if I want to minimize over all the possible g's that is in the space big X,
that kind of minimization is called...
a projection.
Because it is looking for the minimum...
Because it is looking for the minimum distance in the L2 sense between f and g.
So let's figure out why is it called projection.
It is called projection because of the following.
So let me say I have one point in space.
Let's say this point.
Like the tip of my pen.
And the space I want to...
The space of g in which I want to...
So let's say this is f.
Okay.
And I want to find a g within...
On the table that has a minimum distance to g.
How should I find it?
What is the special relation of that minimum distance g with f?
.
Yeah, I can just drop my pen and the point on which it lands is that g, right?
Or in other sense, I'm drawing an orthogonal...
I'm drawing a line that is orthogonal.
I start with f and I go into the space in an orthogonal way.
Once I hit the space, I find g.
Right?
It's that simple.
.
So the orthogonality can be expressed like that.
Orthogonality to a space...
So let's say if I go from f to g, that is g minus f.
g minus f is the vector from f to g, right?
The vector from f to g is orthogonal to the space x.
It's defined as for any g prime in x,
g minus f times g prime is integrated to zero.
So that's the meaning of orthogonality.
And the reason is the following.
So if I find a particular g that minimizes that distance,
it also minimizes the squared distance.
That should be pretty obvious.
Right?
And so let me just call this g star
because g is the result of this optimization problem.
So then for any g, I can express...
Let's define...
So g star is the minimizer.
Let's define g prime being the distance between g and g star.
Then this can be represented as integral of f minus g,
which is equal to g prime plus g star.
.
Yeah.
g prime minus g...
So yeah, g is equal to g prime plus g star.
d x.
And that, because of the property of the square,
that's very special.
That's why we design our objective function to be f minus g square.
I can expand this into f minus g star square
minus 2g prime times f minus g star
plus g prime square.
d x.
Right?
So I'm just expanding these perfect squares.
Okay.
And you can see that this term,
because of g prime square integrated,
is always greater than zero.
So as long as I can make the second term
to be equal to zero...
So if integration of a times g of g prime
times f minus g star d x is equal to zero,
then the left-hand side is always greater than this.
f minus g square d x is equal to integration of a and b,
f minus g star square d x plus g prime square d x.
And this is always greater than this,
and it is only equal when g prime is equal to zero everywhere.
Right?
Almost everywhere.
So that means
if I can have this equal to zero for any g prime
in that linear space,
then I know that f...
I know that g star is the minimizer
of this distance function,
distance square, distance function.
Let me write that down.
So...
Which is also saying that
g star minimizes
the squared distance function
among all the g's in the linear space.
Right?
So what I have done,
I have transformed the optimization problem.
To an equality problem.
So...
So the optimization problem...
Optimization problem has been transformed
into an equality problem
for r g prime,
in x.
Okay?
Does it make sense?
And now remember that
if I can express
the x...
If I can express r possible g prime in x
as a linear combination of the basis
of the space x,
then...
I get
a linear equation for numbers,
and...
I also have finitely many numbers.
So the reason for that is...
If I can express...
g star is equal to a summation of
i goes from 1 to n
of...
Let's say, ai times x i,
where...
x i...
is a basis...
for...
So let me avoid using x.
Let me use phi.
Because x I want to use as space.
It's a basis for phi.
It's a basis for x.
Okay?
Then...
this equal to 0 becomes...
Okay.
So also for any g...
So...
If I...
If I enforce this equality for any g prime in x,
and all these phi i's are also in x,
right?
All the basis functions are members of the space.
So...
So this...
I can simply enforce...
that...
phi i...
times f minus...
summation of ai times phi i...
dx...
equal to 0.
And the reason I use phi i here...
So let me just use phi j here,
because I used i for this...
for this summation.
So the reason I substitute phi j...
into g prime...
is because...
if I can have this equation satisfied...
for all the phi j's...
then...
this equation is linear with respect to phi j.
I can...
multiply any b j onto this equation...
and sum over j...
to get...
the same equation for any g prime.
Right?
So then...
if I...
if I have this...
then...
for any g prime...
that can be represented as...
any j goes from 1 to n...
b j times phi j...
the integration of a to b...
of...
b j...
can be pulled out of the integral...
times phi j...
f minus summation of...
a i phi i...
dx...
is equal to 0.
Because...
all the integrals are equal to 0.
So...
a linear combination...
of these integrals...
is for sure equal to 0.
Right?
Questions?
Yeah.
Both g prime and...
g star...
are the same.
They are.
So...
we've already...
taken...
a few more steps...
to get...
the same...
linear space x...
down to the same...
linear space x.
Very good point...
for the projection to work.
So...
now...
remember I have...
transformed...
the optimization problem...
to an equality problem...
for any g prime.
Now I have...
transformed the equality problem...
to...
this...
equality.
Right?
To...
to an equality problem...
for any...
equality problem for a finitely many vj's.
So here, up to now, I have arrived n equations, one equation for each j.
For n unknowns, because the ai goes from 1 to n are unknowns, right?
n equations, n unknowns, that enables me to solve it.