and what happens next is a is the interpolation of the solution of the
solution which is the correction I should have on the final grid solution
back to the final grid so that's what we are doing here we complete the solution
and we add the correction to the previous solution you 0 so let's see
what the addition is previously my u 0
my u 0 is an array like that and the D u F is an array like that so adding them
together my u 1 is going to be basically this plus this so so
this array has the smoother features and this array has the less smooth
features of the solution so adding them together I have the u 1 and after a few
post smoothing iterations my u 1 is going to be even more improved right so
it basically what this post smoothing iteration do is it it removes the error
that comes from interpolating the D u from the causal grid to the final grid
the interpolation of the solution so that's what we are doing here so this
interpolation is going to make an error all right okay so if we continue my next
time I'm going to come back to line 22 okay here is
what happened oh because it's doing the iterations I shouldn't put it here okay
continue I
I'm going to come back to line 22 on the on the course on the final grade so let
me go back a few times to see how the image is going to change so now we are
at an interval equal to 16 let's go back to and let's go to a more final
grid okay 128 okay so let's stop over here and look at what's the effect of the
little line hours over here so what's the effect of the interpolated iteration
I left in the horizontal line and I left it to the horizontal line for the first
example okay you can see here with that this is actually our partial uncial
요 and I didn't show it but the salvation has capped its error to Kang
okay so now we're done with our interpolation and our isolations so
the next thing I'm going to do is I'm going to change something um let me
show you how that looks like okay so this is my initial beautification this is
you can see here's the ghost Oddland where we are in our Π user and this you
solutions, which is DU.
This is my DU.
Let me compare these.
So my final grid solution is very sharp, but only,
it's bigger, but only contains the very sharp features,
the high frequency contents.
My cost grid solution is actually a lot better,
but it's smaller.
Therefore, what I do is I perform this interpolation.
So let's go here, and we have the DUF.
Now let's look at, I am sure, of what is DUF.
This is DUF.
If you compare this, this is my original U0.
This is my DUF.
So U0, DUF.
You can see that.
DUF is blurred, right, because it's interpolated
from the cost grid.
Well, if you add this up to DU, let's do that.
Let's step so that we have U1.
We figure, I am sure, of U1, which is the summation of U0
and DUF.
Get a solution that is, of course, much better than U0.
But it's also better than the interpolated cost grid solution.
So this is interpolated cost grid solution.
This is the summation of these two.
Cost solution, summation, right?
You can see the solution has improved.
It has the sharp features on top of it.
OK, let's keep going through the code.
And now we are at an even final grid.
OK.
So 1024, so that's at our finest grid, right?
So we can see the same thing here.
I'm going to close it.
I'm going to show the U0.
The U0 has the very sharp contents of this airplane.
And DUF has almost the entire solution, but it's probably
missing the most high frequency contents.
And now if I step over, I have U1.
So that's our funnel.
That's our summation of the cost grid solution
and the smoothing I have performed in my finest grid.
OK.
And continue.
I'm done with one multi-grid cycle, right?
So I have stepped going down from the finest grid
to the closest grid and then back to the finest grid.
So one iteration, I have solutions of all frequency
added together.
And that's still not fully converged,
because I have performed only one cycle.
And if you keep performing these multi-grid cycles, you're going to converge.
OK.
So I'm going to go back to the solution.