Yes?
What is the structure of the grid going to be?
Like the actual...
How do you get the normal
and the SIG from
your grid information? How do I get that from the grid information?
Yeah, okay.
That's a very good question. So let me
actually demonstrate using
one thing. How do I do that?
So for example, in MATLAB there is a good PD toolbox.
Okay. So the
PD toolbox is useful for generating a mesh. For example,
if I just draw a circle over here and
I click mesh, I get a mesh.
MATLAB PD toolbox supports the kind of unstructured
triangular mesh.
Then after you generate a mesh, you can export the mesh
into this environment.
So we can see we have E
and P and T. So P is
going to be all the grid points. So for example,
if you plot P1 and P2
you get all
the points where we generated.
The T, the triangle, the T's
are a 4 by the number of triangles.
So we have 992 triangles. The fourth
column is R1. It's the number of, it's the domain
index. So in this case we only have one domain, so it's R1. We don't
need to care about that. And the other three rows, 1, 2, 3
are integers corresponding to the index
in the P array. Okay.
So these, for example, gives you
gives you
the length, so the length of the
triangle size and the direction of the triangle size
are going to give you the surface normals.
Right. So for example,
so let me
let me just walk you through this one. So for example, I
coded up a function, it's a pretty short function that extracts
the edges from the P's and T's. So from the points and triangles.
So if you run it, for example,
extract edges, P and T, what I
returned you is an array
of 4 by
1520. And 1520 turns out to be the
number of edges in the whole mesh.
And
the four rows are
the first two rows
are indices corresponding
to the array P.
That means which two
points are these edges
connected.
The three and
fourth row are
indices in the
array T. That means
which two triangles
are these edges
separated.
Okay. So if you
if you use, if you follow
the unstructured
mesh finite volume, then
it's the third and fourth
row that
identifies which control,
that identifies the corresponding
i and j of that interface.
But you can use
the row one and row two to calculate
what is the normal
and the s i j.
So for example,
for example, if you
compute the distance,
so let's say d s,
the distance between these two
points would be equal to
P of
column, which includes
both x and y.
So the first dimension is x and y.
Of e1
column minus
p e2
column. That'll give
us the, the
the distance,
the vector that points from
one point to the other point
along the edge.
So the length would be just
equal to
the square root of d s
one
square
square plus
d s two
square.
So that'll give me
that'll give me the
length
of each interface.
These numbers are similar.
Okay, so the surface normals
would be equal
to d s
of two
and d s
minus of d s
one.
Divided
by
uh, divided by
s. I don't know if the division works.
Okay, so I have to wrap
that, uh, s
over two and one. So that's
right, so that'll
that'll give me
the matrix dimension must
agree.
s is this by this.
If I replicate it,
is it wrapped like that?
Oh, yeah.
It should be a semicolon, yeah.
So that'll give me
the normals of all the interfaces.
Right.
Does that make sense?
So it's all from
it's all from like a
geometric manipulations
of the mesh.
Any other questions?
The number of points
is like 529.
So the number of points
So the number of edges should be
529, see through them.
Or something less than that, but
Uh,
No,
because
every point
can share many edges.
Right, so
so if you look at
the unstructured mesh
over here,
so every point has
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8
I mean, did I count?
Did I count correctly?
I mean, every point can have many edges
and every edge only have 2 points.
So the number of
edges is equal to the number of points
times the average number of edges
shared by a point
divided by 2, which is the number of
points shared by an edge.
So if the number of
if the number of edges
shared by a point is greater than
4 on average, then the number
of edges is going to be more than
twice the number of points.
Well, there is
a relationship between the number of edges
and the number of triangles.
So if you look at T,
we have this many triangles
and we have this many edges. Every triangle
is shared by
3, uh, every triangle
is shared by 3 edges.
Right, and
every edge is shared
by either 1 or 2 triangles
depending on if that edge lies on the boundary
or in the interior.
So there is a
inequality
constraining the number of edges
and the number of triangles you can
apply here. But I don't
see any constraints in the
number of points and number of edges.
Okay, any other
questions regarding to this
uh, mesh
geometry
finite volume business?
Okay, we are
all fine.
You can do this in your project.
Okay.
Alright.
So let's, uh,
now
we are basically talking
about how to apply
finite volume, uh, on, uh,
on, uh,
on multiple
dimensions on, uh,
complex geometry. Right?
So you need to generate a mesh and
there are plenty of mesh
generators out there.
You can use, if you just want to
generate a two-dimensional mesh,
MATLAB is a pretty good
mesh generator.
If you want to go to three dimensions,
MATLAB doesn't really do that
for you. And, uh,
we have, uh, open source mesh generators
like Gmesh and commercial
mesh generators, uh, like Pointwise
that can generate good meshes
for us.
Okay. Um, so
once we generate a mesh, we can compute
these surface normals
and surface sizes, and we
use the same type of
reconstruction schemes. We use
the same type of finite volume schemes
to compute a flux
as a function
of the
volume averages on the two sides.
And then, by
accumulating this flux
over all the edges,
we compute the time derivative,
which we can apply to an
ODE solver to solve the differential
equation.