So multiple dimensions is really a slight extension of the finite volume
scheme on a non-uniform grid. So in multiple dimensions, let's write our
conservation law as partial u partial t plus the divergence of a flux vector
which is a function of the solution u equal to 0. Okay and let's actually make
a little bit more general form.
Okay is equal to a function g, let's say, which can also be a function
few. So g is called the source term, that is the non-conventional
conservative part of the equation. So in momentum conservation, for example,
g can be a body force, gravity for example. In conservation of energy, g can
be a source of energy coming from something else. Let's say if you are
showing fluid dynamics equations, g can come from chemical reaction, right?
So g is a source term.
So u is a scale?
Huh?
u is a scale.
g is a scalar. Yeah, g is also a scalar. f is a vector corresponding to two or three
dimensions depending on how many spatial dimensions we have.
The gradient of f, the gradient of f.
So the gradient, no, this is the divergence. This is not the gradient. So f as a vector of u,
I can write it as fx of u, fy of u, fz of u. These are different components.
This is a differential equation. So f is a function of x, y, z components of the vector.
And the divergence of this vector u is defined as the partial derivative of fx to x plus
partial derivative of fy to y plus partial derivative of fz to z.
If you apply the chain rule, because f is a function of u and u is a function of x, y and z.
If you apply the chain rule, you're going to get partial fx.
This is no longer partial because fx is a function of u.
In this case, dfx du times partial u partial x plus dfy du times partial u partial y plus dfz du partial u partial z.
Right?
And this can be written as df vector du dot with the gradient of u,
where the gradient of u without the dot is defined as partial u partial x, partial u partial y and partial u partial z.
Right?
So depending on if you write the second term as the divergence of a flux or equal to a vector field, df du,
dot with the gradient of the solution.
This is two different differential forms of the same equation.
This is the conservative form.
This is what form?
The primitive form.
And that's the derivative form.
So, we can write the first step, the derivative form, or the derivative form of the equation.
Okay.
So the first step in deriving a final volume is to take the conservative form of the equation
and integrate to get the integral form.
Right.
So we take, this is the conservative form.
And this is the primitive.
Okay?
we take the conservative form of equation we integrate
integrate over space over a finite volume what we get is integration over a small volume let's say
over V partial u partial t plus divergence of f of u is going to be equal to integration over the
same V G of u DV let's say DV and the first term because V is a constant volume right in our setup
V is a constant volume if V is a constant volume then we integrate over space over a finite volume
actually changing as a function of time then there are more terms that is coming out but right
now let's say we have a fixed fixed volume we have a fixed mesh and each cell each final volume is a
stationary it's stationary in time what we get is DDT of the volume integrated you integrate over
the volume plus the volume over the volume and then we integrate over the volume and then we get
D and we apply the divergence theorem integral of the divergence of a vector is equal to integral
over the boundary right so the the the nabla operator is exchanged is replaced by the normal
the outward phase normal at the boundary dot with the same f of u DV becomes D s
and this is equal to integration of G dv.
Okay, and in final volume,
we track something that is closely related
to the cell integrals, which is the cell averages.
So we divide both sides by the volume of the cell,
by the volume of v.
Let's just call it v.
Right, so this is the volume of the cell.
And again, if v is stationary,
if the mesh is stationary as a function of time,
we can take the v into the time derivative.
So in the final volume,
so let's say if I have a cell and I discretize,
if I have a space where I want the solution,
if I divide the space into v,
v1, v2, v3, v4, v5, v6, v7, et cetera,
then the d dt of ui,
where ui is defined as 1 over vi,
the cell size,
times the 1 over vi times the cell integral,
this plus 1 over vi,
right?
Integrated over the boundary of vi.
So for v1, the boundary is like this.
For v2, the boundary is like this.
For v3, the boundary is like this.
Okay? The surface normal dot with the flux vector ds is equal to gi,
which is the cell average of d.
Okay?
So this is the normal.
g computed on the ith volume.
So up to now this is still exact.
And now we start the approximation.
So this is still exact.
The approximation is the following.
We're going to approximate two things.
We're going to approximate, first of all,
this integral over the boundary of a cell, we're going to approximate the
boundary as a piecewise constant. We are going to approximate this f as a
piecewise constant function. So for example, let's take v2 as an
example. v2 has one part of boundary interfacing with v1. It has one part of
the boundary interfacing with v3, one part interfacing with v4, and one part
interfacing with v5. And we can split up this integral over the entire boundary
of vi into a summation of integrals. And the summation is over all the cells, all
the boundaries.
That over all the cells that are neighbor of that particular i. So I'm
going to write it as j inside the neighbor mbr of i. j is defined as a
neighbor of i if i and j shares a non-trivial interface. Right, so if the
flow can go from cell i to cell j through a boundary.
And this is the phase normal between i and j. So this is the average phase
normal between i and j. The dot with the flux between i and j and ds is going to
be s i and j.
Okay, this normal is the normal.
This normal is the average, the normal of the interface s is the total amount of interface
length.
In particular this approximation is approximating this f as piecewise constant.
Right so, and if we do that we can, we can say that the integration over partial, let
me,
over partial, over the boundary of i and j of n ds is going to be defined as n i j which
is a unit vector times s i j which is a scalar.
Okay so, so if we, if we say f of u is a constant over the interface we can pull that f out of
the integral and the integral is a purely geometric.
Okay.
So, weultan that f is just going to be plane on this surface, right.
So, we can wonder that what's going on over here when we put沒有 i z to where's this
particular, okay.
Remember we can't do that, you can't
sticking your finger over the edge of this.
So, we have a point S
in the boundary, so creative delay, right?
Yes, and I want to figure out how to want to Personalize
this data so what we're going to do is several times within this darren, that's why the big
point.
Okay, let's do it very quickly.
is exactly orthogonal to the line connecting these two points. Okay.
Oh that's a very good point. I'm thinking in two dimensions. If you have
multiple dimensions, yes it's a plane, it's not just a line. So you will be
integrating the face normal over a potentially non-trivial surface and the
magnitude of that integral is going to be Sij, the direction of that integral is
going to be your Nij. One of the trivial cases is when, let me go to
the mesh then. So this plus this is equal to, if we also approximate Gi as
piecewise constant, then we are going to be applying G onto Ui. The function G
applied into Ui is going to be my right hand side. So here if I can approximate
the piecewise constant surface flux, if I can approximate Fij as a numerical flux,
this is theistol motion. What happens is our final result, second figure we
found, a tangential form. What happens is if you can dominated by Fij
by's vast enough tovous or am skull's mass of Ja, then My feelings that
we 행복 that is computed from Ui NJ then my finite volume scheme works.
Right question so far?
between any pairs of neighboring cells. And we are approximating the flux in
between these neighboring pair of cells using the cell averages on these two
cells. Yes? What do you mean by a non-trivial boundary? A non-trivial boundary is a boundary that has
length more than zero. It's not a point. Yes. So for example, if you have a
grid like that, these and these are neighbors, but these and these are not
called neighbors.