We also need conditions for A. Okay, so first of all, A also has to be
continuous in a very similar way. So A, so continuity of A, u and v. So continuity
of a linear functional, let's go back to here, says that there has to be a constant,
finite constant, for which the value of the linear functional has to be less or equal to
the norm. So again, this is not in xv because L of v is to a field. So L of v has to be less than
the constant times the norm of that function. So continuity of this is very similar. So A of u and
v.
The norm of this, or absolute value, let's stick to the real number. So absolute value of this
is less or equal to c. So there exists a c such that this has to be less or equal to c
times the norm of u times the norm of v for all u and v. Okay, now because it's bilinear,
we need to
multiply. So the right-hand side, the bound is also bilinear. It's also bilinear in the sense that
it's not exactly bilinear. So the right-hand side is also a product of its ingredients. So if you
scale u by a number, by 2, the bound is also scaled by 2. If you scale v by 2, the bound is
also scaled by 2, right? Okay, so the continuity is easy. In order for finite element to be well
posed, we also need to multiply the number of elements. So if you scale u by 2, the number of
elements must be well-pumped and equal to the number of elements. So if you scale u by 2, the number of
elements must be well-pumped and equal to the number of elements. And we also need this
coercivity. That's a word I haven't seen anywhere else, but like this is what's called about a
bilinear functional. So coercivity is that there also exists a number b that is finite. So this
is only has to be finite, right? The b has to be greater, strictly greater than zero. And
that's the right-hand side. So we need this coercivity. So we need this coercivity. So we need this
and also finite, such that the other way is true.
So A of u and u, so that means if I plug in the same function on these two linear functionals,
on these two arguments of the bilinear form, this has to be greater or equal to this b
times the norm of u squared.
So if A...
One way to think of a bilinear form is that A is like an infinite dimensional matrix.
So A operated on u and v is like u transpose times that infinite dimensional matrix times
v.
I mean, a matrix.
So I'm going to do this.
So a matrix is a bilinear function or a bilinear form in a finite dimensional space, finite
dimensional linear space.
You have a matrix A and you have v transpose times A times v, you get a number, right?
So this continuity is really for finite dimensional matrix, continuity is automatically satisfied.
For any finite dimensional space, you don't have the problem about continuity.
So but co-versivity in a finite dimensional sense is basically saying that the matrix
is positive definite.
Right?
You cannot have u transpose A times u being negative or being zero.
So the matrix has to be full rank and it's all the...
So u times A times u transpose A u has to be always positive.
All right.
So these are the two properties that needs to be satisfied for finite...
For the weak form to be well-posed.
And let's look at why under these conditions the weak form is well-posed.
So well-posedness of weak form.
All right.
So let's look at this.
So this is the weak form.
This is the well-posedness.
Okay.
So well-posedness of the weak form is that if I have a u satisfying A of u, v equal to
L of v for all the v's, then I can bound this u.
I can bound this u because...
Because v times the norm of u squared, okay, is less or equal to A of u and u.
Right?
And this can be rewritten as this.
It can be rewritten as the norm of u is less or equal to 1 over this b times A u u divided
by the norm of u.
I'm just splitting the u norm squared into norm of u, norm of u here.
Okay.
So this is the normal view.
This is the normal view.
But this splitting is interesting because if I substitute this A u u with L of v, and
this is because...
This is because of u satisfying the weak form, right?
If u satisfies the weak form for any v, and that any v also include u itself, so what
I'm having is L of u divided by the norm of u.
And now what is this?
This is like the...
This is what appears in the definition of the norm of the linear functional.
This appears in the definition of this linear functional being bounded, or being continuous.
So this is less or equal to 1 over b times the norm of this L.
Right?
Okay.
So...
Now this is...
The result is saying that if we have a u that satisfies the weak form, then the norm of
the solution is less or equal to the norm of the right-hand side, the linear functional,
divided by the coercivity coefficient of the bilinear form.
Now it also guarantees...
This result also guarantees the solution is unique.
Okay.
So...
The solution is unique.
Why is the solution unique?
The solution is unique because if I have u1 and u2 satisfying the same weak form, auv
equal to L of v for any v, so that is satisfied by u1 and u2.
So...
Of course, it's continuous.
And the norm of that 0 function is 0.
The norm of that 0 functional is 0.
So the norm of u1 minus u2 has to be less or equal to 1 over b times the norm of 0, which is 0.
That means the norm of u1 minus u2 has to be 0, which means u1 minus u2 has to be 0, which means u1 is equal to u2.
That means the solution is going to be unique.
All right.
It also tells me if I make a small error in the linear functional L, if I perturb the right-hand side by a small factor,
the perturbation in the solution can be bounded by the norm of that perturbation on the L.
So that's what I mean by, so the solution is unique and the solution is stable to perturbations.
Oh, the zero map is a linear functional, it's not a bilinear form.
Coercivity is a property.
So in order for you to define coercivity, you need a to be a function of two functions.
It has to be a bilinear form.
So the continuity can be defined on both bilinear form and linear functional.
So the zero functional on the right-hand side is a linear functional.
You can define continuity, but you can't define coercivity.
Coercivity is satisfied by this A, the bilinear form.
Yes?
What is definition of L?
Definition of L is the linear functional in the weak form of the differential equation.
Oh, yeah.
It's the same as L of V, L of V.
It's just saying that we have defined the norm of this L.
L is a map.
L is a map from a function space to real numbers.
Right?
So here we define the norm of that map to be the maximum ratio between L of V and the norm of V.
For any possible V you can choose.
That is non-zero, of course.
Right.
Yes?
Yes.
Your question is, can I have a very large B?
So that I can do very small.
Very small.
Yes.
If I have a large V, if I have a large B, then even a very large perturbation on the right-hand side would give me a small perturbation on the solution.
If I have a small B, then the stability is less.
I have less stability, right?
A small perturbation may make me a large.
Change in the solution.
Yeah, that's right.
So B really determines how stable the solution is.
Oh, the step from here to here?
Okay.
This is because of U satisfying the weak form for any V.
So if I replace V with U, this is also satisfied.
Right?
So U is one of the possibilities of any V.
That means A.
A of U, U is equal to L of U.
So A of U, U is equal to L of U.
The others are kept the same.