The reason we use finite volume is really because of nonlinearity.
So if you think of all the examples we did in finite difference, most of them, at least on the differential operator, it is linear.
So when we go to nonlinear conservation laws, we are going to see that finite difference doesn't work anymore.
And we'll see, first of all, why.
So I'll give you, first of all, a general form of nonlinear conservation laws, and then we give you specific examples.
So in one dimension, a nonlinear conservation law looks like this.
A time derivative of u plus the spatial derivative of not u itself, but a nonlinear function of u, equal to 0.
A more general form is that it is equal to an algebraic function of u, but let's think of this as 0 for now, at least in this lecture.
The nonlinearity lies within F.
And can somebody think of an example of a conservation law that we have touched about in previous lectures?
So for heat equation, we have a second derivative of x, which means that F cannot be an algebraic function, but a differential operator.
That's also fine, but this is not the simplest type of conservation laws we are going to be talking about here.
Conservation of mass, right, so this actually can be used to model conservation of mass, where F of u, if u is density, we'll talk about later that this is conservation of mass.
But a very simple example we have touched about previously is F of u is equal to u.
What kind of equation is that?
That's just a linear vector equation, right?
And in this lecture, we'll just use a slightly different example.
It's equal to u squared, for example.
Actually, to make our life a little bit easier in the derivation, we make half of u squared.
That's called the Burgess equation.
So the Burgess equation is really a prototypical nonlinear conservation law that is very, very simple.
It has the simplest form of nonlinearity, just a square.
If you remove the square, it'll be just a linear vector equation, what we've discussed before.
Something that works perfectly, we find a difference.
And now with the square, we see things start to break down, we find a difference.
So before we discuss why things break down, we find a difference, let's first look at three different forms of the differential equation.
And we'll see some form gives us better intuition, some form actually doesn't give us good intuition about the solution of the differential equation,
and sometimes lead to strange contradictions.
The first form is something we know how to deal with and find a difference.
If you take chain rule on this term, what do you get?
df du times du dx, right?
So if you apply chain rule to this, we get the so-called primitive form.
It's partial u partial t plus df du.
Times partial u partial x is equal to zero.
That's the primitive form.
In terms of the Berger's equation, what is it?
What is df du?
It's just u, right?
So the Berger's equation is taking our linear vector equation before and replace our previously big u, which is a constant, with the small u, which is not a constant, it's actually the solution.
So one way to interpret the Berger's equation is,
it's just a linear vector equation with a varying advection speed.
And this advection speed is basically proportional to the solution value.
If the solution locally is positive, the wave goes towards the right.
If the solution locally is negative, the wave goes towards the left.
So we will see in the MATLAB case, for example, if we type Berger's equation.
And I would like somebody to come to our initial condition, trying to verify our initial interpretation of the Berger's equation.
Can somebody come and do an example of initial condition that tries to see if we can verify or disprove
what we thought the Berger's equation would give you?
Go from inside, yeah.
Alright, thank you.
So now we are seeing how the Berger's equation is evolving.
So the rate of evolution is pretty slow, so let's see if we can see the waves moving.
Okay.
So you can see like the positive side is actually slowly moving towards the right.
And on the left hand side I'm drawing a space-time plot, x-axis is x, y-axis is t.
And I'm drawing the solution as a color contour.
So you can see the positive side is actually moving towards the right.
So previously this discontinuity was to the left, and now it's moving towards the right of this x equal to 1.
And this, for example, should move towards the left of x equal to 1.5.
So let's wait until this discontinuity crosses x equal to 1.5 to make sure it is actually moving towards the left.
Right, now it's almost crossing.
So what we were guessing was correct.
But we have almost a linear advection equation whose wave is advecting according to the local solution value.
But there are also something that is not the same as before.
That is, if the advection speed is dependent on the solution value, then the wave no longer maintains its original shape anymore.
So we see the wave actually distorting and becoming different from what you draw as the initial condition.
In addition to that, we also see some of the original discontinuities expanding into a fan,
and some of the original discontinuities actually joining towards one stronger discontinuity.
So this discontinuity is called shock waves.
And this is a nonlinear conservation law that doesn't actually appear in the linear differential equations.
Alright, so let's stop this simulation for now.
And go back here.
So this is the primitive form that gives us a little bit of insight on how the waves are moving.
So think of this as a wave speed.
For any differential equations, for any conservation equations with a different f,
we can always derive how does the wave speed depend on the local value of the solution u.
For example, for this example, the very first example, the wave speed is always equal to 1.
And for the second example, the wave speed depends on the solution in a linear fashion.
So now, the second form, the conservative form, is actually what I have written down here before.
So the conservative form is partial u, partial t, plus partial fu, partial x equal to 0.
And for the Burgess equation, it's partial u, partial t, plus partial partial x,
of u squared over 2 equal to 0.
Now the reason we call it a conservative form is because it is used to derive the integral form,
which really tells you why this is called a conservation law equation.
So, integral form.
The integral form is taking the conservative form and integrating it over an interval.
So, integrate from a to b, a is less than b, partial u, partial t, plus partial f, partial s.
This over dx should equal to 0.
Right?
Now, in the integral form, our a and b are fixed, independent of t, independent of u.
So they are just fixed numbers.
Two arbitrary fixed numbers with a.
So, with the fixed 9 by 8 integration, that integral commutes with time derivative.
As long as a is not dependent on t, b is not dependent on t, then you can exchange the integral and the derivative,
and make the time derivative outside.
So the time derivative of the integral becomes the first term.
Okay?
And the second term is the integral over a derivative in x.
Can we simplify that?
Fundamental law of calculus.
That is, f evaluated on b minus f evaluated on a.
Right?
So, think of what does this mean.
Let's write it in a maybe clearer way to illustrate how this means.
So, I'll move this term to the right hand side.
I'll write it f minus f .
The time derivative of the integral of the solution over a range
is equal to the flux, f is called the flux, at the left of the range minus the flux at the right of the range.
So somebody mentioned conservation of mass.
Right?
If, for example, the solution u is some kind of density,
density of mass, density of electrical charge,
density of energy, density of momentum,
density of momentum, or something.
Right?
If u means density, then the integral means what?
The integral of the density over a spatial domain means what?
Means the total mass, or total energy, or total momentum, or total electrical charge, or something.
Right?
The total amount of stuff inside this range.
And d dt is the rate of change.
The rate of change of the total mass inside a volume.
It's equal to the rate of flux going into the volume minus the rate of flux going out of the volume.
So this is why it means a conservation law.
Because the integral form really tells you the conservation of some material over a volume.
Alright?
So, for example, for the Berger's equation,
we get d dt integration over an arbitrary domain.
And for the integral form to be an integral form,
it has to be over an arbitrary pair of time independent points.
Would be equal to
u b squared over 2 minus u a squared over 2
squared over 2 is equal to 0.
So that'll be the integral form of the Berger's equation.
Okay, questions so far?
Oh, why did I turn the partial derivative in time to just a plain derivative?
This is because when you write u, u is a function of x and t.
So once you integrate over x, the dependence on x goes away.
So the integral of u over a and b is only a function of x and t.
That's why it's just a notation.