So let's first analyze the behavior of the conservation law equation on the
smooth region. So if you think of back over here, over this previous
solution, we want to analyze the behavior of this equation on somewhere other than
this discontinuity, like over this region for example, how does it behave. And if
you take a look at the contour in space and time, let's magnify it a little bit,
can somebody describe to me how the solution behaves? Is there something
special you see on the spacetime plot? Yeah there is a discontinuity, let's talk
about this later. Right now we are talking about smooth part of the
solution, that's right. Did you see something special on the smooth part of
the solution?
What did you see?
A lot of what? Dispersion? I'm just, don't interpret it yet. It's leaning
inwards. Yeah what else, what do you see on this plot other than colors?
A bunch of lines, right? A bunch of not just the regular lines, a bunch of
straight lines. Does it occur to you as non-obvious
that the contour of a function should be straight lines? If you draw an arbitrary
function of space and time, you would expect I get curved contours. It's not
common to see functions in two dimensions with straight lines being
contours, right? So why do we get straight lines? I mean that's actually not the
case when you hit discontinuity. For example, over here,
we don't get a straight line. We get a line that actually turns, right? Two things
hitting to each other and it turns. But on the smooth portion, you see all straight
lines, so why do we see straight lines and what are these lines? That's a great point.
So you already did the analysis I want you to do. So that analysis is from the differential
form of the equation, right? So if you go back to the differential form of the
equation partial u partial t plus df du times partial u partial x equal to zero okay and we
said this is the wave speed and if f is only a function of u then df du is only a function of u
that means the speed at which the wave propagates they are just a function of u
so as the wave propagates at for example towards the right the because if i'm if i'm riding along
the wave then locally the solution value u doesn't change and therefore the speed doesn't change
intuitively that's the answer right mathematically let's do a little bit a little bit of analysis
so so if we look at the differential equation
okay
what what we can do is we can write the solution u at a particular x plus
plus or minus x plus yes x plus uh df so let's let's just do this x plus a ct so let's look at
a function along the the value of the solution along a straight line
on the xt plot
only x more than on the right distance to be the slope of dx dt
okay
so the derivative so now because i wrote u as a function of not x plus ct so x plus ct
x plus ct is x, and also t.
So this is x, this is t.
Does it make sense what I'm doing?
I'm looking at a function of the solution along a line.
So basically, if I make x a dependent variable of t,
then I reduced u into a single-variate, univariate function instead of bivariate function.
x plus, I think.
So basically, let me use x0 to be a distinguishing from this x.
So this is x0, this is t equal to 0.
So as t increases, x is going to increase by c times t.
So this function, if we fix x0, is just a function of t.
So let's look at what is du of x0 plus ct.
t dt.
Again, we are using chain rule.
So this is equal to partial u, partial t times dx0 plus ct dt plus partial u.
Oh, sorry, this is partial x, right?
I am differentiating towards the first variable.
Partial u, partial t times 1.
So this is dt dt.
And what is this?
What is the first term?
It's just c, right?
So this whole thing is equal to c times partial u, partial x plus partial u, partial t.
Now, let's go back to the original differential equation.
According to the original differential equation,
this whole term is equal to 0 when c is equal to what?
If c is equal to df du,
this whole thing is going to be equal to 0.
So there is a chain reaction here.
So if I choose c to be equal to df du at x equal to x0 and t equal to 0,
then I know that the time derivative of u along that line is going to be 0.
Which means along that line, my u is going to be constant.
My u is going to be constant tells me that c is going to be constant.
So that means I can go along straight into that line
and expect my solution to hold constant, not changing at all.
All right, does it make sense?
And that is why we see a lot of straight lines on this contour.
A contour is a line on which the value,
the value of a solution holds constant.
And these contours are characterized by these lines,
x equal to x0 plus c.
So, okay, so this line is,
you can either write x equal to x0 plus ct,
or you can write it as x minus ct equal to constant.
Either way is fine.
I think maybe you are thinking about this, right?
So,
if x minus ct is a constant,
that also represents that straight line.
All right, okay.
So now, another question is,
how does the slope of the line depend on the local solution?
The slope of the line is the inverse of df du, right?
So if I have a df du locally equal to 0, for example,
what kind of line should I get?
I get a vertical line, exactly.
If df du is equal to 0, c is equal to 0.
I get a vertical line.
What if df du is negative?
I get a line that is tilted towards your left, right?
If df du is positive,
I get a line that tilts towards your right.
And again, let's look at the Berger's equation
to see how does my df du depend on u.
So Berger's equation,
if f of u is equal to u squared over 2,
df du is equal to u,
then,
u less than 0, c is equal to 0.
I get negatively sloping contours.
u equal to 0, I get vertical contours.
u greater than 0, I get rightward tilting contours.
Let's look at this to see if that's the case.
Right, so,
so,
when u is positive, the color is u,
I get right sloping contours.
When u is negative, I get left sloping contours.
And when u is almost 0,
towards here and here,
I get vertical contours.
And the more negative I get,
the more leftward sloping I get.
The more positive I get,
the more right sloping I get.
So that's
the contours we call characteristic lines.
So these are
the characteristic lines of my solution.
x equal to any x naught
times df du locally,
df du plus t,
uh, not, not this one,
this way, the other way, I think.
x plus df du times t
are called
characteristics.
Alright.
So, so, when we solve
nonlinear conservation laws using any numerical methods,
we should expect to see these
characteristics.