f has a negative slope.
Oh, yeah, it's a minimum.
Sorry.
It's a minimum.
Right, so because df du is negative,
so it has a negative slope at the left
and a positive slope on the right.
So these are corresponding to u u f.
Right.
Any questions about this?
So if the characteristic of u changes sign,
which means, in this case,
f has a local minimum in the range of ul and ur,
then I need to choose that minimum as my flux.
Neither f of left nor f of right.
Well, if f is monotonically increasing or decreasing,
then, yeah, that would never happen.
Right, so for example, for linear action equation
where f is just proportional to u,
you don't need to use this.
You can just do upwinding or, yeah.
So, OK, so let's say this formula is also
applicable to all the cases where u r
is just a linear action equation.
Right.
So, OK, so let's say this formula is also applicable to all the cases where u r is,
is, is, is, is non-negotiable.
Right.
is greater than ul.
So for example, in this case, the entire short wave
propagates towards the left, which means f of ur
minus f of ul divided by bur minus ul is less than 0.
So this means f has a negative slope in this range.
And taking c.
It's c.
And the ur minus ul is.
So taking the minimum would be taking.
So the denominator is greater than 0,
which means the numerator is less than 0.
And that means ul is greater than ur, right?
Ul is greater than ur.
So.
Taking the minimum over that range, what would I get?
I would get ur, right?
So whenever ur is greater than ul,
I want to take the minimum of the flux over this range.
And the other case is also is the opposite.
So when ur is less than ul, I should be taking the maximum over this range.
So for example, that would never happen in.
So this kind of reverse scenario would never happen in Berger's equation.
But you can think of if the flux is minus of u squared over 2
instead of positive u squared over 2, then the scenario would happen.
So the kind of shock wave would diffuse into expansion
after infinitesimal amount of time.
So the solution would be.
The solution would go towards the left on the left side.
The solution would go towards the right on the right side.
Then.
So this is the case where ur is less than ul.
And in this case, the derivative of f to u at ur,
which is higher, is positive.
So at u.
So at ul.
At u.
At ur is positive, sorry.
So let me draw.
Let me draw.
Let me actually draw this case in the next page.
So we have a discontinuity that evolves into an expansion.
We have ul greater than ur.
And ur is over here.
So my df.
Now,
dt.
u over the range of u r which is less than u l is going to be like that so u r is positive
the the uh the solution u r goes towards the right which means the characteristics is positive over
here and this negative over here so the characteristics is going to going to cross
zero over here which means on the function value of f we have a positive slope
and then the negative slope and this point
is the local arg max of f
and at that point the characteristics has zero speed which exactly corresponds
to the value where you should be evaluating the flux after infinitesimal amount of time
so this case arg max of f u is greater than u r greater than less than u l is what should be
choosing here so in in summary the flux at i plus half
let's just say godunov scheme is equal to two cases one is equal to the maximum
of f over
over a region
u r less than u less than u l if
u l is greater than u r
so left in this case is i r in this case is i plus one i should say that
left is i right is i plus one
and other case is the minimum of f over u i less than u less than u i plus one
if u r is less than u r plus 1 and of course if u r is equal to us plus 1 F is just f of that u
so this method is looking at a discontinuous solution at the interface evolve that solution
analytically for absolute amount of time and look at what is the flux i should be using after that
absolute amount of time all right this was all theFT regularly assume you're interested in my famous
Alright, and there is an analytical formula for that flux over here.
So this is a very elegant result, and unfortunately this only works for a scalar conservation
law.
So for a system of conservation laws, the same argument actually applies.
So you can look at this continuous interface, solve that equation for epsilon amount of
time and look at what flux you should be using there.
But then we no longer have this very elegant formula.
It becomes an equation-dependent problem.
And there were entire PhDs that worked out for a particular system of equations what
is the correct flux to use over here.
Well,
there is also different ways to approximate, not exactly solve this problem of evolving
for epsilon amount of time and computing the flux.
There are also many methods developed to approximate that.
But for scalar conservation laws, this is a very nice formula we can use.