One second.
Actually record this one.
So for example, if you have a fluid flow problem, what you
care about is the velocity field and the pressure field.
And sometimes a typical mistake people make is they
say, what is the velocity input?
What's the flow rate output?
Things like that.
But they forget to give a pressure constraint.
So then basically it's not a unique solution system.
You could have the pressure adding any constant to the
entire system and it'll still be the solution.
So in that case, COMSOL either cannot give you a converged
solution or it'll give you an arbitrary solution.
And the better way, a more predictive way of getting a
right result is to add a pressure point constraint on
one of the points, like a gauge fixing.
And then same for the electric problem as well, actually.
If you do have the current, like input current of 1 amp
and output current, but you don't give a reference point,
then you have the same situation.
So you do want to
have the constraint just one point.
So you can easily do so by right click and then add a
point condition and then add a ground somewhere in the system
or any kind of potential.
And sometimes you actually, for example, don't know what
is the reference point, but then you know kind of like a
floating potential.
So we do have other conditions.
I'm not too familiar with the ACDC part of it, but we do
have different terminal types, floating potential, and other
things you can use.
But you're very right.
So a lot of times in physical world, we think in the very
physics intuition kind of way.
But in the numerical world, then it's interpreted
differently, and you have to think from a mathematical
point of view and how the machine actually understands
those information.
Another important point, since you mentioned, is for
numerical solutions, so far can we trust the results?
Can we trust that 768, 568?
Maybe.
But I wouldn't trust it to the digits.
So I'm going to try to do that.
Because so far, we're using a relatively coarse mesh.
So in numerical studies, what you always want to do is you
can start with a coarse mesh so that you solve faster.
And then after you do that, refine the mesh a couple times,
actually, more than a couple times, and make sure that the
solution doesn't change according to the mesh density.
Then you know you actually eliminated the numerical
artifacts, and you're actually looking at a converged
solution.
Of course, the engineers have different tolerances of errors.
So you'll see the asymptotic limits as you refine the mesh.
And then you can determine, oh, just use less memory and be happy
with that 5% error.
So that is your call in terms of how fine, eventually, you want
to match the geometry.
There would be another approach, which is actually under the
solver setting, a more automatic way, which is to add adaptive
mesh refinement.
So basically, what it does is, depending on what error estimate
you gave, what tolerance you gave, it'll automatically insert
mesh points where necessary, say, where the gradient is high, where
the gradient is high.
You know, where the gradient is high.
So where you see a lot of things happening.
Then that is going to be more memory intensive.
But it's going to be more efficient in terms of
determining where to insert a mesh.
Because otherwise, you can do a local refinement in the manual
way, which will take you more time in terms of choosing which
region to refine and how fine to actually, how many
iterations to refine.
So yeah, something that comes in handy.
All right, so that's the second physics.
We'll go through the third physics really quick.
By, again, right click on component one, add physics.
And we are going to choose structural mechanics, solid
mechanics in phase, add it to the component.
So by now, you already know the drill, right?
You close the physics panel.
You have the solid mechanics here.
You have three default nodes, a default boundary condition.
Sorry, default boundary condition, free to move
everywhere, default governing equation of linear elastic
material.
If you want to change that, add non-linearity or pre-structural.
And if you want to change that, add non-linearity or pre-structural.
And you can also do it by using the thermal stress, or thermal
stress.
You do the right click on the material.
So in this case, we're going to just add a thermal expansion.
And say the temperature calculation for thermal
expansion comes from the heat transfer physics.
And then that's it.
So that's how we tied the second physics to the third one.
And then the free to deform everywhere, again, that's not
enough constraint.
Another example, actually, for constraint
is the number of degrees of freedom there are if it's a
rigid body.
More or less rigid.
Six, that's right.
Yeah.
So how do you have a unique solution?
You need six constraints.
So a typical way is people fix one point.
That eliminates three degrees of freedom.
Then the second point, you say you can only move in one
direction, so in case the structure actually expands.
But it will still stay on the same axis.
So that eliminates another two.
And then another rotational one.
And then the third point, you say you can only move in one
direction.
So that eliminates the six degrees of freedom.
So that's how you eliminate the six degrees of freedom.
Or if you know that the shape on one end doesn't change,
you can actually glue the entire surface to another surface,
say a fixed surface.
So that will, of course, be sufficient for eliminating
the uncertainty here.
All right.
So in this case, we're going to just use the fixed constraint
on the two feet.
Actually, I could use the drop-down feet.
If you want to show that you can just, say,
use a please plate in particular, and then
each point may have two points, actually.
We've just given you theHệ IQ.
And so that's that much of dürfen excited about the
question after all.
And we think it's prettyigned.
Obviously, it's very easy to read the question form
here.
And it's so simple.
Instead of learning it's usuallyators that these
ones are adding, that's what we're seeing here in the
uni.
So what I mean to say is thisíd be theしま
needs all three off airplanelett.
So that means we have two dimensions.
It includes x, y, z components and a
way to contaminate every plane in each photosensitive
inals.
So that's how you compute it on your own.
I think it's for doing.
Bye-bye.
Well, so far it's actually a two-way coupling between physics number one and two, but a
one-way coupling between physics two and three.
So what I could have done is in the study step, I can use step one to solve for physics
one and two, and then step two to solve for physics three, use the information from step
one.
But in this case, the memory requirement is very minimal.
So how am I going to do the visualization for the third physics?
I could right-click on the surface plot of the temperature, add a deformation plot, use
the deformation to show the XYZ component deformation.
So you see what's the straight line, the initial shape, and the shady part.
After deformation, it's actually exaggerated by 53 times.
I can change that to one.
So you have a very small gap between the initial shape and the after deformation shape.
Of course, you can exaggerate it.
Any questions for the third physics?
Adding the third physics?
So more stress and analyze the structural deformation?
One second.
So coming back to the slice.
So so far, I hope I showed you the workflow where to find the different buttons.
I mostly used the model builder because the ribbon was actually introduced later, so I'm
more used to the older version of it.
But hopefully so far I showed you how to solve a coupled phenomena, how to introduce the
coupling.
And by now you understand there's no limitation how many physics you can choose and what kind
of coupling you can implement.
Even for a single physics, it's a very useful or simple tool to have because you have the
same workflow for all the physics that you also show in the UFO score.
And then I mentioned that anywhere you can type in constants, you can type in all the
other different things, numbing expressions, function calls.
You can add user-defined equations.
I haven't showed that yet.
Oh, and parameterization.
I want to quickly show that.
It'll be in the next slide.
Okay.
It'll only take a minute or so.
So a lot of times people want to compare different designs.
Actually let me disable this multi-physics node.
It was introduced with the second set of equations I introduced.
So my expansion, I'll disable that as well.
Okay.
So this was the working version of my last computation, the model.
So what happens if I want to try a few different designs and see which one gives me the peak
temperature, the highest peak temperature on one of the shoulder points?
So what I'll do is in geometry, I want to use a parameter to control that distance,
extrusion distance, so the thickness of it.
So just call it thickness.
Of course it's going to turn red because it's not defined anywhere.
In global definitions, I can add parameter list.
And here I'll say thickness 0.2.
And then I can go to the study.
Okay.
So in the study node, add a parametric sweep.
So now here pops the entire list.
Right now I only have one parameter.
And I'll say instead of 0.2, run me three cases, 0.2, 0.3, and 0.4.
Or you can use the range button right here, typing the beginning and end, what's the step.
And now you've computed, it's essentially going to run the same problem three times
with a different geometry.
And every step is going to build a new geometry, build a new mesh, assemble a new system matrix,
and then give me a solution.
And it's going to put all the three solutions in one solution data set, as three separate
frames.
So if I want to run an animation that loops through that three frames, I could actually
do that.
Of course in time-dependent problems, you save the solution every certain seconds, and
then you can run the animation of that as well.
All right.
So now you've finished computing.
So now you see, for example, if I look at the temperature plot.
So you can see that the temperature plot is now running.
So now you can see that the temperature plot is running.
Okay.
So I could choose a different parameter and here the plot is going to update the visualization.
And I said I want to look at the temperature information at the shoulder point.
So let me first find out what's the coordinate of that shoulder point.
I'm going to add a measure under geometry.
I'm going to measure a point, 0.250.2.
And then what I'll do is in the solution data set, so the solution we have saved so far,
I'm going to right click, add a cut point 3D, type in 0.250.2, and choose that parametric
solution.
So I'm going to plot the information on that particular point.
I'll add a derived value of point evaluation, use this data set, evaluate the temperature
information.
So now it shows me what's the thickness and what's the temperature on that particular
point.
Okay.
So here I have a graph, shows me where the highest temperature is.
It shows up at the point four case.
Of course, it's only a small variance among the three cases.
So what should we do?
Run a batch refinement study, right?
Remember?
So after then you'll be confidently saying which one actually gives me the highest temperature
down.