So the reason we are defining the sub-left space is because it's the kind of sub-left space that we can define the weak form of the differential equations.
So for example, in our previous Poisson's equation, we derived the equivalent form of the Poisson's equation,
that is, integration of the product between the derivative of a test function and a solution,
plus the integration of the test function times the right-hand side, is equal to zero.
So that was an example.
And in order to say this is equivalent to the differential equation in some sense,
we need to restrict both u and v into a space.
And in our previous example, we directly went to a finite dimensional space.
But of course, going to a finite dimensional space makes an approximation.
It makes an approximation to the differential equation,
and through this...
this weak form.
But if we don't restrict the u and v to a finite dimensional space,
but restrict it to a sub-left space, which is infinite dimensional,
we can say that the solution recovers the solution of the differential equation exactly.
Okay.
So...
So the weak form of the equation is to...
the weak form of the Poisson's equation is the following.
So find a solution u in H1 of A and B.
H1 is the sub-left space we defined earlier.
Such that...
for all v,
we call it test function,
we call it test function within the same space.
Okay.
This box is true.
Right?
Which is like the integral plus the integral equal to zero.
So this box is the same as this box.
So this is the weak form of the Poisson's equation.
And it's a weak form because...
if...
if f is regular enough,
so if f is a smooth function, let's say, or continuous function,
then we have a twice-differentiable u, right?
Because if f is a function,
actually any function,
then the second-order derivative of u has to be equal to that function,
which means, of course, that u is twice-differentiable.
If that is the case,
then the solution of the weak form
is equivalent to the solution of the strong form of the differential equation.
But it is weaker in the sense that...
if f is not a function,
so it holds,
even if f is not a function,
even if f is a distribution,
it is a function instead of a function.
And...
for example, what is an example of a distribution that is not a function?
Hm?
Sorry?
A Dirac, right, or a delta function, a Dirac delta function.
So for example,
let's say f of x is equal to a Dirac delta function x minus 0.5,
and our domain is in 0 and 1.
Okay?
We can see that it doesn't make sense to say
the second-order derivative of u plus a delta function is equal to 0,
but it does make a lot of sense to say
this integral is always equal to 0.
Because if f is a Dirac function,
then what is the integral of f times v?
It's just the value of v, right?
It's just the value of v at 0.5.
It's perfectly well-defined, right?
Okay, so in this case,
what we are going to get,
so let's figure out what we are going to get here.
So what we get is that
the integration of a and b of any v times,
not any v, partial v partial x,
partial u partial x dx,
has to be equal to v at 0.5.
Okay, so what does this tell us?
It tells us that the u,
so it tells us that u is not twice differentiable.
We are going to solve it later.
We haven't defined the boundary conditions yet.
But it tells me that u has to be a piecewise linear function
and this derivative has to be discontinuous at 0.5.
To see this,
let's define a boundary condition for this equation.
For example, let's define
with u equal to u equal to 0.
So let's define a most trivial boundary condition.
And what we need to do is,
this boundary condition is,
we are going to talk about later,
is an essential boundary condition that restricts
this,
that shrinks the space.
So we call it h1 0
because this is equal to all the f within h1,
a and b,
such that f0 is equal to f1 is equal to 0.
So all the functions that satisfy a certain boundary condition.
Right, so it's even a smaller space.
So then for all the v in the same space,
which is also have to be satisfying the boundary condition,
we have the,
we have the weak form to be true.
Okay, so now if we know both u and v satisfy the boundary condition.
Okay, and so here what we can see is that
one way for this to be always true is for u to be a linear function
in both.
So, so for this to be true,
u has to be linear in 0 and 0.5 and 0.5 and 1.
Because a linear function means the derivative is going to be a constant.
Right.
A constant times the derivative of v integrated between 0 and 0.5
is going to give me the value of v at 0.5.
And so let's do this.
So the integral of a and b of these is going to be equal to,
so let's say a is equal to 0, b is equal to 1.
Okay.
So b is equal to 1 is going to be equal to from 0 to 0.5
of du dx left times dv dx times dx plus du dx right.
So, so u is going to be split into two halves.
So u is going to be like that.
Okay.
And it has to satisfy the boundary conditions.
And you get partial v partial x dx 0.5 to 1.
So what we ended up getting is that,
so du dx,
so du dx at the left is basically 2.5.
So basically 2 times u, u at 0.5, right?
Because this is 0.5, this is 1, and this is u at 0.5.
If you divide by 0.5, you get the slope at the left times v at 0.5.
And the other quantity is the slope of u is negative.
So minus u times 0.5.
And the integral of v dv dx over the second half of the domain,
because v is also satisfied the boundary condition 0.
So it's going to be minus v at 0.5.
And with that summed together, we have 4 times u at 0.5 times v at 0.5.
Right?
So what we are doing is that we have constructed a u that is in H1.
u is in H1 because u is a hat function.
It's continuous.
The square is integrable.
The derivative of u is also integrable.
It's no longer continuous at 0.5.
It's piecewise constant.
But the square of that is still integrable.
So we constructed a u that is not twice differentiable,
but in H1.
That satisfies the weak form for a right-hand side being a delta function.
Right?
So to get the u, this is equal to v at 0.5.
That basically means u at 0.5, this has to be 1 fourth.
Right?
So with u equal to 1 fourth,
this is going to be equal to v at 0.5,
which is the right-hand side we want.
So we constructed a v that goes from 0 to 1 fourth
when x goes from 0 to 0.5 and then goes down to 0.
That satisfies the boundary condition.
It satisfies the weak form for f.
That is a distribution.
That is not a function.
So the weak form is weaker in that sense.
It's somewhat...
The sense of that is similar to how we change the strong form,
the differential form, to the integral form in finite volume.
Right?
In finite difference...
In finite element, we also transform the equation to a weak form
using integration by parts like that.
And the weak form is weaker in the sense that
the exact equation, differential form,
does not have to make any sense.
Make any sense, even.
For right-hand sides that are not even a function.