So this is a previous project done in Virginia Tech, so in another university.
So basically, you have a code that is going to evaluate your solution.
So you can look at the project description over here.
So this is a demo project.
Please write a function with a function name, computer lab 5.
So whatever you write, the function name should be the same as what the project name is,
which in this case is computer lab 5.
And you can see that this code calls the computer lab 5, which is the function you wrote.
And then it assesses the result.
If it's not equal to, this is a dummy case, if it is not 256, it tells you your solution is wrong, otherwise it's right.
So for example, you can come into the room, you can say code up takes one x,
and you say, okay.
My result, you need to say result is equal to computer lab 5.
So the syntax is the same as what you would do in MATLAB.
Say 256.
Somebody is also, okay.
Then you can run it.
It says your answer is right.
So I see a lot of people are in the room, so can you just change the result to something else and run it?
Okay.
T-plant.
Yeah, 25.
And yeah, it says your result is wrong.
So click this one to look at the result.