Okay, so if I do this, what do you think is the order of accuracy of my solution
to my system of conservation laws? First order, why is that? Because I add a
numerical dissipation that is on the order of Delta X, right? So basically I
have modified my equation with a term that is proportional to Delta X. Of
course the term is going to go to 0, as my Delta X goes to 0, but at a rate of
only Delta X to the power of 1. And that's what makes the truncation error
of my scheme to be first order. This guarantees stability, so I have a
stability and that makes my solution error to be also
1.
going down at the same rate as my truncation error,
which makes my solution first order.
So we have studied in a scalar conservation law case
how to make the scheme more than first order.
We have invented this limiter business
that tells me that in smooth regions of the space,
we are going to be using a high order scheme
more than first order scheme.
But where I'm close to any discontinuity,
I'm going to switch to a first order scheme like that.
So how do we make that switch in system of conservation laws?
There are multiple methods,
and I'm just going to introduce a method
that is the easiest to implement.
And that's the JST scheme.
So the JST scheme basically switches
between what we just discussed,
a second order derivative,
and a fourth order derivative.
Remember when we did the dissipation
versus dispersion error analysis?
There was a very good question of asking
what is the behavior of a fourth order derivative?
And we did a brief analysis.
The effect of a fourth order derivative
is very similar to a second order derivative.
It's dissipative.
It removes energy from the solution.
Right?
And it turns out
a fourth order derivative
is exactly what we are doing
in our limiters when we set our phi r.
So we have phi r equal to one.
Why is that the case?
Because if we set our limit to phi r equal to one,
we are computing the left and right value
on the interface by extrapolating the solution
from the two adjacent cells to this left value.
And I'm also extrapolating two adjacent cells
on the right hand side to this particular value.
So we can see that the left and right values are the same.
I'm involving one, two, three, four grid points
in this calculation.
And when I'm computing the difference
when I have a u left and u right,
both from extrapolation,
and then if I use the same amount of
the same numerical dissipation
I discussed in the last page,
not using the cell average values,
but using these extrapolated left and right values,
what do I get?
What do I get is
I'm going to get my delta x
times the absolute value of df du
times u right minus u left
over delta x.
I'm just substituting
u i plus one with u right
and u i minus one with u left.
In the case we have
phi r equal to zero,
we turn on the limiter.
When we have a local streamer,
remember when r is less than zero,
we have different signs of slopes
on two sides of the interface.
In which case we want to have
a piecewise constant reconstruction
in order to enforce
total variation diminishing properties.
We don't want the reconstructed solution
to overshoot the original solution.
In that case, we set phi r equal to zero.
Which means we want to do a piecewise
constant reconstruction.
In that case, u r is exactly equal to
u i plus one
and u l is exactly equal to u i.
When phi r is equal to one,
we know the solution is very smooth locally
and we want to do a second order reconstruction
by extrapolating.
No matter what value phi is,
let's replace phi i plus one
by phi r and phi i with phi l.
So this is the formula we get.
And this is equal to
let's just cancel out
this delta axis
u r minus u l
and
if we allow ourselves
to calculate the extrapolation
which is u i
u r is going to be equal to
u i plus one
minus half of delta x
times the slope
which is
u i plus two minus u i plus one
which is u i plus two minus u i plus one
over delta x
so this is my u r
my u l is going to be u i plus
delta x over two
times the slope constructed from the left
which is u i minus u i minus one
over delta x
and now
if we combine
the terms
the term that is multiplied by
u i plus two
is going to be minus half
the term that is
applied on u i plus one
is going to be
minus half
so we have
a one here
we have a half here
so it's a
three halves
what is multiplied on
oh we have a minus sign here
we have a minus
what is multiplied on u i
is going to be minus one here
and another minus half here
so we have minus three over two u i
what is applied on u i minus one here
right
so we have a linear combination of one two three four terms
and
if we perform a Taylor series analysis
to figure out what kind of
derivative
what kind of differential operator does this
approximate
what do you think
ok to make it a little bit
clearer let's
let's make it like that
let's perform a
ah
let's perform
a
grouping minus half of
u i plus two
minus two
u i plus one
plus u i
plus half
of u i
plus one
minus two
u i plus u i minus one
so here what I'm doing is
I'm grouping these values in a different way
right
so u i plus two is going to still have minus half
u i is going to have
one plus half
etc all the terms are still preserved
but I'm just combining them differently
now if you look at this
linear combination
what do you think
that a linear combination is
that approximates
the d three u by d x cubes
and
this is actually
yeah that's right
so what we are looking at
is
if you divide the first term by delta x square
it is an approximation
to the second order derivative
it's a finite difference operator
for the second order derivative
the second term is also
a derivative
of the second order derivative
so
the second order derivative
multiplied by delta x square
it's a finite difference between two
second order derivatives
which gives us the third derivative
and you are absolutely right
and
it's the third order derivative
multiplied by delta x to what power
cubed
that's right
so it is minus half
times delta x to the cubed
and
d f d u
times the third order
derivative of u
so
so if
this is going to give us
if the additional term on the flux
gives us the third order derivative
what is going to be the effect
on the differential operator
on the difference in the flux
it's going to be a fourth order derivative
it's going to be a fourth order
derivative proportional to d x square
and
it's going to be a fourth order derivative
proportional to d x to the cubed
right
so the effect
of having a
piecewise linear reconstruction
like that
is adding a fourth order derivative
is adding a fourth order
dissipation
to the right hand side of the equation
and the amount of dissipation
is proportional to delta x
to the cubed
okay
yes
oh
okay
so this is
this is the way we are
let me see
so this is the additional term
in the dissipation
right
so this is the additional term
in the flux
our flux is going to be equal to the half
of this
half of in this case
plus
this additional dissipation
term
right
so this is how we are constructing
our flux
now in the system of
equations
instead of upwinding
instead of using upwinding to choose either
f r or f u l
we are adding
we are averaging them and adding
the numerical dissipation to achieve the effect of upwinding
and what i've been doing is the
additional dissipative flux
we are adding
and in a finite difference operator
in a finite volume
scheme d u i d t
is going to be equal to
f of i
plus half
minus sign
minus f plus f of i
minus half
right and
so this is going to be equal to
we have a central
flux
we are going to reconstruct
so it's going to be equal to
i plus half
central
plus
f of i minus half
central
plus an additional term that is
one over delta x
times
f
r
i plus half
sorry i plus half
dissipation
plus f i minus half
so
if the dissipation terms are proportional
to
the third order derivative of x
taking the finite difference of that
is going to give us the fourth order derivative
so we have
the modified equation
for
this particular scheme
for the scheme where we
always choose
a limited value of f of r
equal to one
is adding a fourth order derivative
to the right hand side of the equation
proportional to delta x to the cube