So there is a potential pitfall here. A potential pitfall here is to approximate this solution v using exactly the same numerical method as what I solved for u h.
That sometimes doesn't work. Because the pitfall here is that if I solve for a, so let me see, I have a L o of u h minus u, I have already represented as a of u h, u hat, which is the adjoint solution minus L of u hat.
So if I approximate this by a of u h.
L of u h and u hat of h minus L of u hat of h, where u hat of h is solved using exactly the same method as I solved for this u h.
For example, if I have Poisson's equation, remember our a is symmetric, right?
So a of u and v is equal to a of v and u.
If a is symmetric, what is its adjoint operator?
It's itself, right?
Symmetric is also called self-adjoint.
Okay, and then I can basically replace the right-hand side and solve using exactly the same numerical method.
But what is the problem if I do that for approximating this u hat?
Yes, this would be zero.
Exactly.
So if u hat of h belongs to this...
This finite dimensional space, xh of v.
Then, by definition of the finite element solution, so remember the finite element solution, u h,
it's that particular u h in the finite dimensional space that makes the residual equal to zero for any v in this space.
My approximate residual is going to be zero.
Okay.
So I cannot use the same numerical method or the adjoint version of the same numerical method.
So for that particular u hat.
The normal practice is to have a richer basis, is to have one...
For example, if I solve u using piecewise linear basis function, I can solve for u hat using piecewise.
Okay.
So I can solve u using piecewise linear basis function.
And that will give me a higher order solution for this u hat and give me a proper area estimate, a posteriori area estimate.
So the posteriori area estimate is not going to be free.
You need to spend additional effort to get that.
All right.
So normally, u hat is approximated...
Approximated...
with higher order solution.
Or you can just refine the grid by one more factor
and solve for u hat h.
All right.
Okay, so this finishes our discussion on error estimation.
And the remainder of this lecture
will go into more than one dimension,
go to two-dimensional finite elements
to see how do we apply what we have learned
into higher dimensions,
which can deal with more complex geometry.