Approximating second-order derivative with finite difference. So the
approximation error we define is basically this minus this. Okay
approximation error is ui plus 1 plus ui minus 1 minus 2 ui divided by delta x
square minus this. And one of the very powerful way to analyze the accuracy of
an approximation scheme is Taylor series.
Taylor series expands the solution at a particular point as a function of the
values and derivatives of the same function at a different point. So for
example ui plus 1 which is defined as the solution u at i times delta x, right?
Because each grid spacing is delta x, the i-th gradient
point is at x equal to i times delta x. Oh not i but i plus 1 delta x. So i delta x
plus another delta x. It can be expanded using Taylor series assuming the
function is smooth analytic. It is equal to k goes from 0 to infinity of
u at i delta x of the k-th derivative times delta x to the k-th power and
times 1 over k factorial. Right so this is the Taylor series of expanding the
solution at a particular point. So we can see that the first term k equals 0 is
the 0-th derivative which is u itself. And the second term is the first-order
derivative. The third term is the second-order derivative which is what we
are trying to approximate. And the third-order derivative etc. is something
also we don't want. So basically in this Taylor series analysis we want to also
write down the Taylor series of ui minus 1 and use the coefficients to cancel the
0-th term, k equal to 0 term, cancel k equal to 1 term and preserve k equal to 2 term.
And make the k equal to 3, 4, etc terms as small as we can. That's the first term.
Thank you.
Something we want to do right now. ui minus 1 would be equal to ui delta x minus delta x.
It is equal to the same summation, same 1 over k factorial. This is just a copying Taylor series.
i delta x except for instead of plus delta x here we get a minus delta x to the k-th power.
Right.
Okay. So now add them up.
Let me make another page. What? Okay. Let me make another page for that.
Didn't know it does that. Okay. So of course you
can see.
Of course ui is just equal to u of k i delta x.
All right. Only one term. So let's look at the accuracy of this scheme.
So the solution error is 2 over delta x.
Let me just copy them down. Not 2.
It's 1 over delta x times ui plus 1 plus 1 over delta x times ui minus 1 minus 2 over delta x.
By the way, it's squared.
So it's squared.
So the solution error is 1 over delta x times ui and also minus.
So this is plus and also minus partial x squared partial x squared.
And for each of these terms, we are going to expand the Taylor series.
The first term, we look at the first order.
Right. So this one is proportional to u of i, which is also u at ix, i delta x.
This is ui prime.
This is ui double prime.
ui triple prime.
ui quad prime.
So this prime, I use it as shorthand for taking derivatives.
1 prime is first order.
Double prime is second order.
For example, if we just expand the second order derivative, we get, of course, 0, 0, minus 1, 0, 0, etc.
Right.
So this is, I'm writing down minus partial square u partial x squared as a linear combination of all the derivatives.
And this is at xi.
OK.
Another example is when I look at the third term.
The third term, which is also very easy.
The first coefficient minus 2 over delta x squared.
And all the other coefficients are 0.
Right.
And these two terms are a little bit more tricky.
So that we need to follow this Taylor series.
The first term is 1 over delta x squared.
The second term is 1 over delta x squared times the coefficient in the Taylor series, which is k equal to 1.
1 over 1 factorial is 1.
And this is the first order derivative.
And delta x.
So delta x is the only thing that comes out.
All right.
And then the second order derivative, we still have 1 over delta x squared.
And now 2 factorial is actually 2.
So we have delta x squared.
The third term, still 1 over delta x squared.
We have delta x to the cubed and 3 factorial.
And delta x fourth, 4 factorial.
The minus 1 term, the same, except for when we multiply by delta x, we multiply by minus delta x.
When we multiply by delta x squared, we multiply by minus delta x.
Which is the same as delta x squared.
And here, delta x cubed, we get a minus sign again.
And fourth, we get no minus sign.
And this goes on forever.
Right?
So the cool thing is, when we add them up, what happens?
First, let's look at the first term.
When we add all the constant terms together, what happens?
Yeah?
They cancel each other.
They cancel each other, we get 0.
Right?
Minus 2, 1, 1.
How about the second?
0.
Right?
So that's a well-constructed scheme.
We are canceling a lot of things.
We are canceling a lot of terms.
How about this one?
Also 0.
Right?
This and this cancels.
We have half, half, and minus 1.
0.
All right?
So this minus 1 here, coming from here, is the only one that, if you just look at the
scheme alone, that doesn't cancel within itself.
It cancels with the term it tries to approximate.
All right?
Now if you look at this again, the third derivative term, 0 again.
It's great.
But it can go on forever.
Right?
This is the first term that it actually makes a non-zero error.
And look at how small it is.
The delta x squared cancels with the fourth, so we get square here.
And at the 1 over 24th, what we get is delta x squared divided by 1 over 24.
And this is the first derivative.
And the second derivative is delta x squared divided by 12, times the fourth order derivative
of u.
This is the leading term of the approximation error.
Because all the follow on terms, this term is going to be delta x cubed something.
Maybe it's even 0.
This is delta x fourth something.
All the other terms.
But remember, delta x is a small thing.
In our previous example, it's 1 hundredth.
That means delta x squared is going to be 10 to the minus 4.
Right?
We are dividing by 12, and that makes it 10 to the minus 5.
And we multiply it by the fourth order derivative of u, which may or may not be large, depending
on what u is.
So this scheme works well.
But the approximation error is something small.
Something scales, something decays to 0 very fast as delta x goes to 0.
All right.
Any questions about this?
So this scheme also makes it easy for us to construct approximations.
For example.
We derived this particular finite difference scheme from the interpretation of a second
order derivative being the first order derivative of slope.
Right?
We can also derive it completely algebraically by saying that I want to multiply some unknown
coefficient onto here.
Let's say a.
Some unknown coefficient into here.
Let's say b.
And some unknown coefficient here.
Let's say c.
And I want a times ui plus 1 times b plus b times ui minus 1 plus c times ui minus the
second order derivative to be something small.
I want the approximation error to be small.
Then you can derive some linear equations.
This is going to be a.
This is going to be b.
This is going to be c instead.
You want a plus b plus c equal to 0.
Right?
That gives you one equation for three unknowns.
The second you want a minus b to also be 0.
That gives you another linear equation.
Here you want a plus b equal to 1.
That's three equations for three unknowns.
You solve them.
You get exactly the same numbers you're going to get here.
1 over b.
That's the same number.
You get here.
1 over delta x squared.
And minus 2 over delta x squared.
So that also gives you a route to derive finite difference approximations for other operators.
All right.
So you start working on your project today I hope.
And the first question require no knowledge of what I'm teaching here.
It's just a calculus.
The second you are starting to derive schemes to solve the equations.
And I already told you how to do second order derivative.
You're going to be doing first order derivative yourself.
All right.
And many of you may already know what is a good approximation for first order derivative.
If you don't, use this to derive it.
All right.
Any questions?