okay so fortunately there is a almost a hack or modification to the Jacobi
iteration and iterations like Jacobi iteration we can do to make it a good
smoother this is called under relaxation what does it do so under relaxation is
the following so we have performed remember we have said okay so u1 u of k
is equal to u of k plus 1 is equal to Jacobi which is minus d inverse l plus u times
so d inverse not this this is the
solution error so minus d inverse times
minus b plus l plus u times u of k right so that's the Jacobi iteration for for a u equal to b
if we modify the
iteration such that my u k plus 1 is not exactly equal to this but it is equal
to an average between what i would get in a Jacobi iteration and the previous iteration
so what i'm doing is i'm introducing a lambda here i call the relaxation factor
i would be
averaging using this relaxation factor 1 minus lambda times u k so that's the weight on the
previous solution plus a lambda times what i would get if i'm applying the original Jacobi iteration
times minus b plus l plus u times u k
so what i have in the bracket is exactly what i would get if i apply the Jacobi iteration
but i'm weighting that by lambda which if i use under relaxation lambda would be less than 1.
so lambda less than 1 under relaxation
there are other cases where you want lambda to be greater than 1. this is over
over relaxation we are going to see later on applying over relaxation on Jacobi is a very bad
idea but applying over relaxation on some other methods like Gauss-Seidel may be a good idea
let's look at why that is the case
okay so first of all we need to analyze in order for us to study the convergence how fast
does the under relaxation or over relaxation converge for different frequency contents
what should we do first how do we start analyzing convergence we need to derive
a iteration for what quantity the error right we need to derive the error equation
and what is the way to derive the error equation we subtract the iteration
from a similar equation satisfied by the exact solution right in this case we know that the
original iteration is satisfied by the exact solution and so is the original iteration
multiplied by lambda so lambda u would be also equal to lambda times minus d inverse minus b
plus l plus u times u right
just multiplying the same equation that is the split of this split of this is d
uh u plus l plus u times u is equal to b so if you move this to the right hand side and
if you move this to the right hand side and multiply both sides by the inverse you're going
going to get the the equation that is satisfied by u so this is multiplying
lambda on both sides and then split this into two terms u plus u minus 1 minus
lambda times u and then move this to the right hand side what we are going to get
is u would be equal to 1 minus lambda times u plus lambda times the inverse
minus B plus L plus u times u so the original the exact solution u
satisfies a very similar equation to the iteration except for replacing all the
K and K plus ones by the exact solution
now
subtract right so if we define UK to be UK minus you subtracting these equations
would get me ek plus one is going to be equal to 1 minus lambda times ek plus
lambda times the B term because they are the same in both is going to be canceled
out
I'm only left with minus the inverse times L plus
you times you are times sorry you is going to be replaced by UK let's combine
these two terms I would get one minus lambda times identity minus lambda times
the inverse L plus you
times ek
therefore the under relaxation or over relaxation the effect of the relaxation
to the error equation is to modifying this original iteration matrix by a
constant multiplier lambda and then add that with a 1 minus lambda times identity
identity
Now think of what are these two things due to the eigenvalue of the matrix
first of all what is a multiplication by lambda do
what are the multiplication by lambda due to the eigenvalues of a matrix
hh
multiplying by lambda right so a scaled version of the matrix has a scaled
version of the eigenvalues
Why Pat высокih chóney
What is the different ?
of adding an identity to the eigenvalue of the matrix.
Make it more SPD.
It's a constant shift to the eigenvalues, right?
So let me call this iteration matrix by J, right?
So let's call this J.
I'm going to define this J by the original iteration matrix,
which we know the eigenvalues.
They are, so the eigenvalues of J is cosine of J pi over N.
J goes from 1 to N minus 1, right?
Okay.
Now, the eigenvalue of the J lambda, I call it,
the Jacobi iteration with under or over relaxation.
Okay.
So the eigenvalue of J is equal to 1 minus lambda I plus lambda times J, right?
So we know, we basically, we have J multiplied by lambda and shifted by identity.
So if I have J times eigenvector is equal to, I use the lambda here,
so forgive me for using alpha as an eigenvalue.
Okay.
So if J is equal to 1 minus lambda I plus lambda times J,
if Jv is equal to alpha v, then J lambda times v would be equal to,
let's do the math, 1 minus lambda times identity times v plus this lambda times J times v.
And this, because identity times v is just a v,
I get 1 minus lambda times v plus lambda times alpha times v.
So what I get is these are all constants.
I get 1 minus lambda.
So I get 1 minus lambda times v plus alpha lambda v.
Therefore, v is still an eigenvector of the same, of J lambda,
the under-relaxed iteration matrix.
And the eigenvalues, originally being alpha,
they are modified by multiplying with,
multiplying with the under-relaxation factor and adding by 1 minus lambda.
So these are the alphas we get.
That means the eigenvalues of J lambda is going to be 1 minus lambda plus lambda times cosine J pi over n.
Right?
So think of what this lambda does to these eigenvalues.
First, let's imagine we have a previous eigenvalue that is very close to minus 1.
That was our problem, right?
That was our problem of why the J copy iteration is not suitable for multigrid.
If this is very close to minus 1 and we apply a lambda that is close to 0.5.
So let's imagine this is approximately minus 1 and this is approximately 0.5.
What does this do?
We have 1 minus 0.5, which is 0.5, plus 0.5 times minus 1.
We get what?
Or we are averaging something that is close to 0.1 with something that is 1, right?
So this is a weighted average.
You think of 1 minus lambda times 1 plus lambda times the original eigenvalue.
This is a weighted average.
This is an average between 1 and the original eigenvalues.
What does it do to the negative eigenvalues?
What does a lambda that is between 0 and 1 do to the eigenvalues?
Yeah, it makes it, it pulls it towards 1.
Right?
Let me show the effect here.
So lambda.
Let's make.
Okay, n.
n equal to 16.
Let's say we are going to see the same effect pretty soon.
So let's say the eigenvalues are a, they are cosine of 1 to 15 times pi divided by n.
Right?
So these are my a's.
And my lambda, so let's say is link space between 0 and 1.
Actually, let's make it some over relaxation.
0 to 2.
Let's make it 100.
Okay, so what I'm going to do is a, is going to show, I'm trying to plot lambda in the
x-axis and the relaxed eigenvalues on the y-axis.
Let me see.
a is this, lambda is this.
So what I want to do is my a lambda is going to be 1 minus lambda.
Okay.
So I'm going to plot lambda plus lambda times a, which I want to make it a transpose.
Does this work?
Lambda is going to be 1 by 100.
So it's going to be this.
a is going to be like that.
No, this doesn't work.
Okay.
So I need to be lambda transpose times a.
And this will be transpose.
So let's see if that works.
Okay.
So a lambda is 100 by 15.
So let's plot.
Lambda a lambda.
Yeah.
Okay.
So let's grade it.
So here's what we get.
When lambda is equal to 1, when lambda is equal to 1, that means that lambda is equal
to 1.
Okay.
So that's what we get.
That is the exact original Jacobi iteration, right?
Lambda is equal to 1.
This term is 0.
Lambda is 1.
So I get exactly the same Jacobi iteration.
The eigenvalues goes from something very close to minus 1 to something very close to 1.
This is responsible for the very slow convergence we observed.
And this is responsible for very slow convergence of something that is difficult to observe
generally.
But like in multigrid, it's responsible for the slow convergence of multigrid.
If we use a lambda that is greater than 1, what's going to happen?
What do you think is going to happen to the iteration?