so for the remaining time let's go into
MATLAB and try to implement at least
one of the limiters and see how to
integrate what we learned together so
we're going to use Berger's equation
not Berger but Berger's equation as an
example t and u du dt so any finite
volume scheme we are going to compute n
is equal to length of u and dx is equal
to 1 divided by n
so we are going to reconstruct u of i
plus half and left and we are going to
also reconstruct the u of i plus half
right
alright and once we reconstruct this we
are going to apply apply good enough
scheme
to compute f and this is f at the
interfaces and I'm going to say f is
equal to 0 f 0 so that gets us are gives
us all the boundaries we need and the
du dt would be equal to for any final
volume schemes du dt would be equal to f
2 1 2 n- 1 minus f 2 2 n divided by the x
so that's the grand scheme of how to
compute things so before we do any
reconstruction that's compute the ui
minus 1 and ui the ui and ui-1s right so
So let's consider ui plus half left.
We first do ui minus 1 is equal to, so let's still imagine zero bounded conditions.
We put zero and u of 1 to n minus 1.
So this is my ui minus 1.
I'm just constructing this as an array.
All right.
And I also need ui plus 1.
It is equal to u from 2 to n.
And I also put a zero at the end.
That's the value beyond the boundary.
Okay.
So my ratio here would be ui plus 1 minus ui.
Divide by ui minus 1, u minus ui minus 1.
So this is my r.
Okay.
So if I use Van Leer limiter.
So let's just use a general limiter function.
phi is equal to limiter of r.
So I'm going to write a limiter here.
So I'm going to write a function.
phi is equal to limiter r.
Okay.
So for example, if I want the Van Leer limiter,
I would be saying phi is going to be equal to,
let's look at what we have.
It's either zero or 2r divided by 1 plus r.
So let's first compute 2r divided by 1 plus r.
And phi of whenever r is less or equal to zero would be equal to zero.
All right.
Another case we want to take care of is when r is going to be a zero divided by zero,
which is not a number.
So phi of any not is finite.
So if I write r, I'm going to set it to zero.
Because remember when we actually use the limiter,
phi is going to be multiplied with the difference.
Where is phi?
When we use the limiter, phi is going to be multiplied with the ui minus ui minus 1.
So if we get a divide by zero, we are also in r.
When we use phi, phi is going to be multiplied by 1.
So phi is going to be multiplied by zero.
So in that case, when r is equal to not a number infinity,
it doesn't matter what the value of phi is as long as it's not a number.
I am fine.
So this is going to be my implementation of the Van Leer Limiter.
Any questions?
Pardon?
Line 9 has to be dotted by line 9.
Line 9?
Oh, yeah.
Thank you.
All right.
Okay.
So what we're going to do is we're going to do a little bit of a test.
So once I compute the phi, I can compute ui plus half left.
It's going to be, according to my formula, it's going to be ui plus half of ui minus ui minus 1.
ui minus ui minus 1.
And I'm going to compute the next one, which is ui plus 1, right?
times my phi.
That completes my reconstruction of the flux at the left.
Reconstructing the flux at the right is very similar, but I go from the right.
So instead of ui minus 1, so I already have ui minus 1.
So what I need here, the equivalence of ui minus 1 is ui plus 2, right?
So that's the cell away on the right and away from the interface.
It's equal to ui plus 1, 2 to the end, 0.
So I further shifted using ui plus 1.
Okay.
And my r in this case is going to be...
Okay, instead of ui plus 1 minus u, I have ui minus 1 minus...
Wait, is that ui plus 1?
Okay.
So let me write down the formula first for the right reconstruction.
Otherwise...
So ui plus half left.
Is equal to ui plus ui minus ui minus 1 divided by 2.
That's the slope times dx.
Times phi of ui plus 1 minus ui divided by ui minus ui minus 1.
And ui plus half from the right is equal to...
In this case, i plus 1.
i plus 2.
So this is going to be playing the role of ui minus 1.
Ui plus 1 is going to play the role of ui.
And i is going to play the role of...
Not here.
i is going to play the role of ui plus 1.
Right?
So I'm looking at here.
When I'm constructing the left, I'm looking at these three cells.
So when I'm constructing the right, I'm looking at these three cells.
So on the right would be ui plus 1 plus half of...
Instead of ui, I have ui plus 1.
Instead of minus ui minus 1, I have minus ui plus 2.
Times phi of...
Instead of ui plus 1, I have ui.
Instead of ui, I have ui plus 1.
And ui minus ui minus 1 would be ui plus 1 minus ui plus 2.
Right?
Does it make sense?
I'm just flipping the indices.
Okay.
So my r would be equal to this value, ui minus ui plus 1...
...
ui plus 1 minus ui plus 2 times 5. Alright, any questions so far?
Here should be dot multiply, here should be dot multiply. Any other bugs you see
in here?