The example I'm going to give is the one-dimensional Poisson's equation.
The Poisson's equation is the second-order derivative of u plus a known function f is equal to 0.
And let me solve this within the spatial domain of 0 and 1 with the simplest type of boundary conditions.
In this case, we no longer know what the solution u is.
We only know that the solution u satisfies a certain differential equation.
So how do we use the same procedure we discussed before to solve this equation?
It turns out there are two ways to look at this.
The first way.
Is to try to integrate this equation with a function.
Right, so approach one.
So let...
So I'm going to let a function g also...
To...
To be 0 and 1.
To be...
Let's say to be smooth.
Okay.
And what I'm going to do is that because this equation is equal to 0 within the whole domain.
I can integrate g of x times the residual of the differential equation.
Which has to be equal to 0 everywhere.
So this should be equal to 0 within the whole domain.
And because this function is...
Is equal to 0 within the whole domain of .
The integration of this function over space should be equal to 0.
For any smooth function g.
Right.
So basically what I'm going to do is this has to be true for any g.
Okay.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm going to restrict f and g.
Within the space.
Within the same linear space.
So I'm going to restrict.
f is going to be forced to be a linear combination of a certain basis functions.
Phi of x.
And g of x.
I'm going to force it to be the actual basis functions.
J goes from 1 to n.
The reason I can force g to be any of the basis functions is because if this equality is true.
For any of the phi j's.
Then it has to be also true for any linear combination of the phi j's.
Which covers an entire n dimensional linear space.
Right.
Okay.
So if I perform that restriction.
What I'm going to derive out of the equality is.
I replace g with phi j.
Okay.
I'm going to.
I'm also going to replace.
Oh.
I'm sorry.
I messed up.
I shouldn't be replacing f.
I should be.
I should.
I shouldn't be restricting f.
I should be restricting the solution u.
Previously we restricted f because we wanted to approximate f.
In this case we wanted to approximate u.
So we want to represent the solution u.
As a linear combination of.
Of these basis functions.
So we represent u as this linear combination.
So here the u i's are not functions of space.
And phi i's are functions of space.
So we integrate u i.
And the second order derivative is going to be applied.
To the basis functions.
All right.
So.
Again we are going to pull these summations.
Out of the integral.
What we get is summation of i goes from 1 to n.
u i.
Times the integration of 0 to 1.
Phi j of x.
Times the second order derivative of.
Phi i.
D x.
This is the first order.
So we have.
The second order derivative of.
Phi i.
D x.
This is the first term.
And the second term is.
Is phi j.
Times f.
So.
Plus.
Phi j.
Times f.
D x.
Has to be equal to 0.
Right.
The difference between.
This equation.
And the equation we derived last time.
Was that.
The phi i.
Is.
Has been taken a second order derivative.
Well.
Last Wednesday.
We.
When we tried to approximate.
Just a function f.
Basically.
Instead of solving.
A second order derivative of.
Phi u.
Plus f equal to 0.
We were basically solving.
Minus u plus f equal to 0.
Right.
We are trying to approximate.
F with.
A function.
So.
In this case.
We.
We simply.
Replace.
The.
Phi i here.
By the second order derivative of phi i.
So.
The following is the same.
This.
And this.
Is.
Represented.
As.
A matrix.
And a vector.
Respectively.
So.
If I define.
A i j.
To be equal to.
Integration.
Of.
Phi j.
Times the second order derivative of i.
I am going to.
Say.
B j.
Is.
Equal to.
The integration.
Of.
Phi j.
Times f.
Then.
This equation.
Is.
A matrix.
Equation.
A u.
Plus.
B.
Equal to.
Zero.
Right.
And that is something.
I know.
How to.
Solve.