So one thing I want to point out is the discrete conservation properties of any final volume scheme.
So now we have a working scheme, we want to point out its advantage.
And that actually corresponds to your question, which is, can we use final difference?
Yes we can, but we are losing something important in a conservation scheme.
So if we have a differential equation in the conservation law form,
and we can integrate, when we integrate over any interval, not just one grid point,
let's say A to B, where A and B can be very different, U to X,
we know from the conservative form of the equation,
this is equal to F of U at A minus F of U at B, right?
So this is a natural conservation.
So this is a conservation type of expression, because the, sorry, I have a DDT here,
the time derivative of a total amount of stuff is equal to what's going in minus what's going out.
Okay, and in a lot of cases, the numerical schemes may not satisfy that conservation.
So I have, I think last year or two years ago, I saw an interesting cell phone app.
It's called Wind Tunnel.
I don't know how many of you have looked at it.
You looked at it?
Anybody else have looked at the, like it's a free app, iPhone or Android called Wind Tunnel.
It solves the fluid flow equation with, on your screen, and you can draw any shape on the screen.
What's interesting is that it looks very real, actually.
But what's interesting is that you can draw something like a band,
like a bag around the screen, and you're going to see like some flow is going to go into the bag and never comes out.
So things keeps going into this bag that you draw on the screen.
You can play with it after a while.
So that's a very interesting example of a PDU solver not satisfying conservation law.
Do you mind drawing the bag and see if it conserves the mass?
Okay, so you have a screen, right?
And you have flow, I mean, they have visualization of smoke or something.
And if you can draw, let's say you can draw an airfoil with an opening here,
and you're going to see the smoke goes into the airfoil and there is no place for it to come out.
What I'm trying to say is that finite volume schemes would never create something like that.
Because if you have a screen, you can draw a bag, and you can draw a bag around the screen.
If you discretize the equation using a finite volume scheme,
you have dui dt equal to f, so I want to multiply delta x on this side,
fi minus half minus fi plus half.
All right, let me keep writing this.
dui plus 1 dt is equal to f of i plus half.
minus fi plus 1 and half.
Now, what's important in finite volume is that
the way we computed this fi plus half is exactly the way we computed this fi plus half.
Right?
So it's the same number in our code.
So the f interface is a vector of length n plus 1.
The same fi.
But when you add them together, it takes 1 integral.
And once we come to the point where we can spread it out,
the derivative is that if ui is 1,
when ui is an integral of length n plus half,
it's used for computing the derivative of ui and ui plus 1.
Okay, so that's very important.
If you violate that, it's no longer a finite volume scheme.
The discrete integral, I mean, if you sum over these two,
remember this is a cell average, this is also a cell average.
The summation of these two is actually the total amount of u inside these two grid points.
It is equal to one flux minus the other flux at these two ends of this interval.
Although the value of this flux involves approximation, but the form is still the same.
So you can keep writing that all the way to f of n, let's say, at the very end.
This is equal to f of n minus half minus f of n plus half.
If you add all of this together, every pair cancels except for the very first one and very last one.
Although the form of this flux involves approximation,
but the fact that the interior flux cancel each other has no problem.
So, for example, if you draw...
If you have boundary condition saying that the last flux has to be zero at some point,
that's equivalent of if you draw a bag where the end you have no flux.
Then it means that if I have flow goes into the first cell,
then the time derivative of my total mass inside all this volume has to increase.
And in an aerodynamic solver, for example, as the mass increases,
the pressure is going to increase.
And ultimately, it's going to push the flow back out of the inlet of the bag.
So you can't have something that flows into a closed volume indefinitely if you use finite volume.
If discrete conservation of mass or momentum or energy is important for you,
then it's another motivation to use finite volume.
Instead of another way of discretization.
And also, we are going to be talking about it a little bit later.
Another advantage of finite volume is it is a lot easier to deal with non-uniform,
non-Cartesian complex mesh,
which is useful for complex geometry using finite volume compared to finite difference.
Okay.
Finite difference is...
It's very easy to use for Cartesian uniform grid.
As the grid gets more and more complex,
the complexity of finite difference scheme becomes...
Increases very rapidly.
While finite volume scheme, they stay...
We're going to see like in 1D uniform mesh,
it is not easy to do a finite volume scheme with more than first order.
But the same complexity actually carries to 2D,
3D unstructured mesh.
So your complexity won't increase much as you go to very complex geometry.
Alright.
So this is the pros and cons of finite difference versus finite volume.
If you choose a way of discretizing.
By the way, there are schemes in finite difference that also have discrete conservation properties.
But it's not automatic.
You need to be very...
You need to work hard to get that.
Kind of choose your discretization schemes, do a lot of analysis to get that.
While you find that volume is automatic.
No matter what kind of flux you use, what kind of approximation you use on the flux,
it discretely conserves what you are conserving.