so the project is not completely given out yet there is a still a question that is not given
but if you look at the government equations and the government equations particularly looks for
supersonic flows so we have a equation like that it should be equal to zero all right and supersonic
flows means this M infinity means the how much faster is the flow compared to the speed of sound
so it is a number that is greater than one can you see the similarity between this equation and
the equation we just looked at it's similar except for one major difference
it's there is no time right but instead the spatial derivative term have a negative sign
between X and Y and Z because M infinity is greater than one this term is actually negative
these two terms are positive if you move the negative terms to the other side of the equation
which makes it positive it's the same as our wave equation which goes on in time
so we can perfectly treat this as a time integration differential equation but like instead of
integrating time we're integrating X all right so now we are getting to the domain when there is the
difference between now we have this we can see that the difference between what we call hyperbolic
equations and
elliptic equations it's not just the fact that hyperbolic equations has a time in it while
elliptic equation doesn't have a time it's only a spatial thing it's actually more mathematical than
that for example this equation has no time in it but the fact it is a hyperbolic equation means it
means that you can treat the X dimension as a time and solve the equation using time integration
so it's essentially only the number of times tangential to the Nosmosis equation
so let's say that the N is nothing but the decimal point that happened and that we must
integrate the N teddy bit망 to get the percent of times N in our x-ング forecast
so the N possession of the x-eng of thenight is nothing
only the correct solution part of the equation half and half wheel the momentum of and that's
not the case you make an equation which is indeed lambda over the time except that very
nearly przykład
that X after where you put the perturbation and by after it doesn't mean
time it means the X location right so if you you can you can look at some of the
pictures I included these are not linearized equations these are real
experiments so so the existence of this airplane actually is not felt by the
flow for X locations smaller than where this thing is so so if you put a
per base in here so think of this entire airplane as a perturbation this
perturbation is not going to influence the flowfield anywhere that is upstream
so this is characteristics of a hyperbolic equation where you can think
of one of the dimensions as time where the domain of influence only happens
continuing on from国界的波波磁相对比就相反了
after that time.
Several other pictures are like that.
So the question is,
do the transformation of variables
and derive a system of equations you can solve?
And consider a lot simplified two-dimensional problem
and try to gain some intuition from the pictures you use
and derive an analytical solution
for the two-dimensional case.
And design a solver to solve this two-dimensional,
I mean, no, the solver is actually,
so design a solver for the two-dimensional problem
and justify the use of numerical schemes in the solver.
And compare the solution
with the analytical solution you derived.
All right, so play around
with some supersonic flow problems.