Now we have the matrix and given a right hand side we can solve the equation for U.
So let's just try it. What kind of right hand side would you like to try?
Anybody give a suggestion?
A sinusoidal one.
A sinusoidal one? Okay, so you want F to be...
Sine of what?
Huh?
X times Y? So we don't have any X or Y yet. So let's do this. Let's construct the X and Y.
So, is mesh grid in 2D?
Yeah, okay, so let's look at... I think mesh grid is what can help you to construct X and Y.
It returns a 2D grid coordinate based on vectors X and Y.
So, okay, so let's say X is equal to 1 to NX minus 1 times DX.
Y is equal to 1 to NY minus 1.
Come on, minus 1 times DX.
Okay.
And I think that's it. I think just do big X and big Y equal to mesh grid X and Y.
So let's see if I get the right thing.
Big X is going to be a 31 by 31 matrix.
So...
It's actually the opposite of what I wanted to get.
So I want... So this is the first index. I want the first index to correspond to the X direction.
I want the second index to correspond to the Y direction.
So...
So let me just switch them over. I will just do Y and X.
Alright?
So this index corresponds to the X direction. This corresponds to the Y direction.
That's what we had in this indexing, right?
So the first index corresponds to incrementing X.
The second index corresponds to incrementing Y.
So if you look at Y, it's the other way. It's going this way.
Alright?
So...
I think you wanted F equal to sine X times cosine Y or something.
Alright?
So we get an F that is 31 by 31.
How do you convert the 31 to 31 matrix into this?
Huh?
So if you do mat to vac...
Is it...
Yeah, I think reshape is the same as reshape.
Yeah.
I think it's the best approach.
But like, in order to reshape it to into the format of what we want, because MATLAB does it the other way, right?
So we need to do...
We need to reshape it of...
Let's actually make big F equal to sine X times cosine Y.
So that big F is a matrix.
So we need to do small F equal to reshape of F transpose into NX minus 1 times NY minus 1.
And 1.
Alright.
So let's see.
Huh.
Actually, I don't think I can see much from that.
Okay.
So let's say sine of X times cosine of Y.
So in the beginning...
In the beginning of the matrix...
Of the vector, I should have R equal to 1, right?
So I should have R equal to 1 and J increases.
So I should have a very small number because it's sine of a very small X times a slowly decaying number.
So let's see if that's what I get.
Okay.
I think that's right.
Right?
So this is like sine of delta X times cosine of delta X, cosine of 2 delta X, cosine of 3 delta X, etc.
Alright?
So from the ICE inspection, it looks right.
We can also create a surface plot of big F.
Let's do X, Y, and F.
So that's what my F looks like.
So we can do X label X, Y label Y.
That'll give me...
So this is X, this is Y, and the Z axis is of course my F.
Alright?
So I think it's the right trend.
X increases, sine function increases, and cosine function decreases.
So now I have my small F.
Let's do U is equal to matrix backslash F.
I get my U.
Alright?
How do I visualize my U?
I get my U, which is a 961 by 1 array.
So I need to reshape it back to...
a matrix before I can visualize it.
So let's say my big U is equal to reshape of small u.
And again, MATLAB, we need to do...
We need to make it...
NY minus 1 first.
And X minus 1.
Transpose.
Alright.
So when we reshape that way, we transpose first, and then reshape it.
In the reverse...
In the inverse operation, we need to reshape it into the transposed shape of F.
And then transpose it back.
So let's do the same serve, but now with U.
That's what my solution looks like.
Okay?
The Laplacian of this U is equal to F.
So the Laplacian, which means the X...
The second order derivative of X plus the second order derivative of Y.
It's some kind of curvature in 2D.
And the positive Laplacian curves in a convex way.
So curves...
This is what a positive Laplacian looks like.
And if you rotate it a little bit...
Let's maximize and rotate it a little bit.
You should also be able to see that...
The curvature is larger towards this side.
Right?
Towards the...
Towards the X equal to 1, Y equal to 0 side.
So let's do X label, Y label.
So X equal to 1, Y equal to 0 side.
You see, like the...
The bottom of this function shifts...
It's not in the center.
It shifts towards the X equal to 1, Y equal to 0 side.
That's because the curvature is larger in this side.
And if you...
If you...
If you remember the figure we used to look at Y...
So this is what Y looks like.
It's largest over here.
This is what...
Ooh.
What did I do?
Uh...
I think I...
All right.
Okay.
So if you look at this figure, it's...
The curvature is largest over...
Over here.
All right.
So this...
We completed the loop of solving a Poisson's equation in 2D.
And that gives us a solution like that.