ok so let's go to MATLAB and figure out
how to implement this. Close all. So what we
do is let's say we construct a right hand
side. So let's say n is equal to 16 to
start with and let's make f equal to 1.
So this is our right hand side
for f and let's also make the boundary
conditions to be 0. So u of 0 is equal to
u of n plus 1 is equal to 0. So we don't
have these terms when we are approaching
the boundary.
Okay.
And let's make u to be 0s and 1s.
That's our initial guess. Initial guess can
be anything and as long as our Jaccobby
iteration matrix has less than one
eigenvalues, then it doesn't matter what
your initial condition is. You're going to
converge to the right value. If your
initial condition, if your initial guess is
close to the true solution, you're going
to converge a little bit faster but
nevertheless you're going to converge.
So it's pretty commonplace to use a
zero initial guess. Now our next
is to, let's actually multiply this thing
to the other side to make our formula a
little bit cleaner. So this is going to be
minus delta x squared over 2 times f of i
and this is going to be plus half of ui
plus 1k
plus ui minus 1k. Both are half because
these are 1 over delta x squared, these are 2 over
delta x squared. Okay. So now we start,
let's perform one iteration. Okay. So
uk, uk plus 1 would be equal to the
existing, okay so it's going to be delta x,
I haven't completed delta x yet, so
let's imagine our domain is 1 and in
final difference we are dividing this
one domain size by n plus 1, right. So
uk plus 1 is going to be minus delta x
squared divided by 2 times f. Alright so
let's first make this first. So we get a
uk plus 1 and then we add this part. So
this part is going to be calculated like
that. So for i goes from 1 to n. So okay
so I first want to add the i plus 1
part. So if i is less than n, I want to
say uk plus 1 of i plus 1.
Okay so i is equal to itself plus u of i
plus 1 divided by 2. Okay else if i is
greater than 1, you, oh not else, sorry. So
so let's, okay so let's let's initialize
zeros again. So not else if because I, you
if i is in the middle, I both wanted to be added with i plus 1 and i minus 1.
So it should be another if, not else if.
So this is still the same.
This is the same.
And then I'll do an end.
Another if is if i is greater than 1.
u k p plus 1 i is going to be the same thing.
And plus u of i minus 1 divided by 2.
And so that completes our one iteration.
Do we want to look at it?
Okay, let's do that.
u k plus 1.
It's pretty much 0, right?
In fact, I'm concerned it looks exactly the same.
It's 0.
So, oh, sorry, I forgot to add this after.
So I only did this u i plus 1 and u i minus 1 part.
I forgot to add that part.
So, okay.
So I should do it again.
u k plus 1 is equal to the f part.
And then I'm going to do the loop.
Okay, so let's look at this again.
So, right, I guess it's non-zero, but it's too small for this to show.
Okay, it is non-zero.
So we can see that we have to be patient, right?
One iteration doesn't really do much.
So let's make another 100 iterations.
So for k goes from 1 to 100.
So let's first say u is equal to u k.
So we can say u is equal to u k plus 1.
And then we are going to do the for loop over the indices.
And end.
So that completes 100 iterations.
And it seems to be getting a diverging answer.
Should we have added the f?
Oh, yes, we should have added f.
That's right.
But why am I diverging here?
Da, da, da, da.
Plus 1, minus 1.
Okay, so let's start with u is equal to 0s and 1.
So for k goes from the loop.
So u k p plus 1 is going to be.
Uh.
So this should be equal to f.
Or dx.
Uh.
Right.
I think I had one of these sentences before.
So this is equal to.
Uh.
Minus dx squared divided by 2 times f.
Divided by 2 times f.
And then I'm going to go through the for loop.
So for i goes from 1 to n.
If i is less than k, u is added.
And if it's greater than 1.
So that is good.
Okay.
And at the end, I want to say u is equal to u k plus 1.
Uh.
Minus 1.
Okay.
So this time I did 100 loops of the Jacobi iteration.
Let's plot it to see what I get.
So this now looks a lot better as the solution to the Poisson's equation.
Right.
Okay.
So just to compare, let's figure out.
Uh.
Let's.
Let's look at the analytical solution.
The true solution.
Let's look at the residual to see how much the residual is.
So the residual would be equal to.
Um.
Would be equal to.
Let me see.
The f.
Minus.
That.
Right.
So the residual would be equal to f.
Let's do that first.
And.
Uh.
We'll fix that.
Um.
Uh.
So the residual is going to be 3.
So the residual would be equal to.
Uh.
Because we have already had the residual.
Well.
Okay.
So just like the derivative of the residual.
We're going to find out.
The residual.
If u is equal to.
So.
If u is equal to 1.
R i.
Is going to be ri.
Uh.
Minus.
This.
u of.
I minus 1.
Divided by delta.
X squared.
Okay.
all right if I is less than n our eye is going to be our eye divided by minus UI
plus 1 divided by Delta x squared and no matter what I is our eye needs to be
added with the diagonal term so I'm looking at the right hand side minus the left hand side so
we have a plus 2 times UI divided by Delta x squared so here is my R my R looks like point
zero point something so we see that it is not very small yet
right so so remember if we have a zero solution U my R would be simply F which
is our all ones so after a hundred iterations we see that the residual has
reduced from the magnitude of F which is equal to 1 to something like point 2 so
it has reduced a lot but not quite yet what does that mean we need to increase
K so let's
do another thousand iterations okay and we are going to look up our history for
what we had have done before so from here to here now we have done another
thousand iterations let's hold on and the plot the U again
so the new one is the red solution now we have seen that the blue solution
although it qualitatively approximates the solution it's the magnitude is not
that right yet so so the red solution has gone even lower all right so let's
figure out what is the residual now so again let's use what we let's try to use
our history R is equal to for I goes from 1 to n
so the computation of R and it over here all right so with another thousand
iterations we get something much better right so all the other residuals are 10
to the minus 9 okay so so that means the red solution should be pretty much the
analytical solution
you shouldn't we shouldn't find a difference between them so let's
confirm that so we are going to construct the matrix now explicitly
right so a is going to be minus 2 times identity of n divided by Delta x square
AZ equal to a plus diagonal of 1 and minus 1 1 and I'll shift it up to 1 by 1
and then we have the red solution which is the negative integral of the red solution
and I'll add another lower diagonal entry so I'm going to say you exact is
equal to a backslash F now I'm allowed to use matrix solve oh yes thanks so I
will do this and divide by Delta x square okay now I'm supposed to be right
okay thanks for her thanks for pointing out the buck so you exact is equal to a
backslash F and let's hold on again and plot you exact by let's do diamonds okay
and what do we have okay we have it's very hard to see but we have the
diamonds overlapping with circles I can see it
okay
yeah so so basically we get pretty much the same solution as these Jacobi
iteration after a thousand iterations all right any questions on these