The whole conservation law actually generalizes to multiple dimensions.
So let's start with the conservative form of conservation law in multiple dimensions.
We have partial u, partial t, plus, now we have multiple axes.
We have x and y and z, for example.
But no matter how big the dimension we have, we can write it as the divergence of a flux vector.
Where the flux now is not a scalar flux, as it should be, a vector in two or three dimensional space.
And it's the divergence of that vector that determines the time evolution of that solution u.
And of course...
Of course the primitive form is taking chain rule on this second term.
And taking chain rule, we get df vector du, a scalar, dot with the gradient of u.
That is equal to zero.
And again...
This is a wave speed, except for now my wave speed is a vector.
It not only denotes how fast locally the wave at that also it determines towards which direction
does the wave
propagate.
Okay, and we also have the integral form.
The integral form again is
derived by integrating
over any domain, any continuous domain,
this differential equation.
So for example in 3D space, this is going to be dv, d volume, is equal to zero.
Okay, and
first of all, let's integrate the first term and move the differential to time out.
So, if we take the third term and move it to the third term, we have integral of dv, dv, dv, dv.
So again, if u is density in three dimension, this is the total mass encompassed in this volume omega.
The second term...
We can't use directly a fundamental theorem of calculus.
Yeah, Gauss's theorem.
So the integral of a volume of a divergence is equal to what?
Surface integral.
Is equal to a surface integral exactly over, let me denote partial omega as the surface encompassing the volume,
dot a normal vector ds,
where this is a surface integral over the surface, is equal to zero.
If you write it the other way, just to put a minus sign on the second term and move it towards the right hand side, it's
equal to zero.
So, we can see that...
And for example, I think it's easier to move the minus sign to here, so that we have a minus n.
So, n, the normal in Gauss's theorem is unit normal pointing outwards or inwards?
Outwards.
So, minus n is going to be a unit normal pointing inwards, right?
That means the rate of change of the total mass is going to be a unit normal pointing inwards.
Right?
Okay.
So, the total mass inside the volume is equal to the flux, is equal to the total flux into the volume.
Right?
Of course, the f can have the opposite sign, can point towards the different direction as minus n, the inside of the volume.
In that case, f represents a flux out of the volume.
If f is aligned, has a positive inner product with minus n,
f represents a flux into the volume.
All right.
So, this is how the conservation law works in multiple dimensions.
Any questions?
So, we will shelf this multi-dimension conservation law for later on when we discuss finite volume in multiple dimensions.
This lecture will focus on only the one-dimension scalar conservation law.
Okay.
So, the first thing we are going to do is to look at the scalar conservation law.
And the purpose of this is for us to have an intuitive understanding of how the solution in 1D looks like,
and for us to derive our finite volume scheme.
Okay.
Question?
Are the Fibonacci and the conservative equations saying something different physically, or is it just a matter of . . . ?
Right.