We only talked about u0 is equal to a fixed value, let's say y.
And in this case, this boundary condition is going to appear in our right-hand side.
And d dt of my solution u vector is equal to a matrix times u vector plus a constant term.
And the constant term u0, the u0 is going to appear here as u0 over delta x squared.
Okay.
And today we are going to introduce the...
Newman boundary condition.
So this is called the Dirichlet boundary condition under the name of a mathematician.
And we are also going to talk about Newman boundary condition, that is du dx at, let's say, x equal to 1.
The right-hand side is equal to, let's say, z.
This is called Newman boundary condition.
Newman boundary condition is going to affect...
the discretization of the right-hand side.
So the partial derivative of u at x equal to...
at x, let's say, n minus 1 is going to be discretized as u of n plus u of n minus 2 minus 2u n minus 1 divided by delta x squared.
Right?
Okay.
And we already said that one way to discretize this is saying u n minus u n minus 1, a consistent
way of discretizing this, which means delta x goes to 0, the approximation error goes to 0.
This can be used to approximate the derivative.
Now we know this is equal to z.
So that establishes a linear relationship between u n and u n minus 1.
So if we plug this into here, what we get is u n is going to disappear and become u n minus 1 plus z delta x.
And plus u n minus 2 minus 2 u n minus 1.
So you can collect these two terms and instead of minus 2, I'm going to erase this and this
becomes minus 1.
Right?
So that's one way of dealing with the Newman boundary condition, which instead of setting
the value to something, you set the derivative to something.
So that's only an x equal to 1.
Right?
Okay.
So what's the x equal to 1?
The Newman boundary.
The Newman boundary condition, this is when I'm setting the boundary condition at the
right, when at the last point.
If I have a Newman boundary condition at the left, it's similar.
I'm going to use u 1 and u 0 as opposed to u n and u n minus 1.
Right?
Okay.
So if you look at this.
So if you look at this formula, this has two effects.
One effect is there a z term.
Right?
So z over delta x, which is going to go to the constant term in this equation.
All the others are 0.
Second is that it is modifying the coefficients of u n minus 1 specifically.
So all the rest of this scheme get minus 2 over delta x.
Minus 2 over delta x square.
But the last, very last one is going to get minus 1 over delta x square.
Right?
All the other terms stay the same.
So it is modifying this.
Okay.
And it is also adding that.
So Newman boundary condition has the effect of both modifying the matrix and adding something
on the right hand side.
Yes?
So you have a first order approximation for the boundary condition, but that costs the
whole solution, the first order algorithm?
That's a very good question.
So here I have a first order approximation.
Okay.
So I have a first order approximation just on one point.
Right?
And for many equations, including this one.
So the answer is equation dependent.
For this particular equation, it will not affect the quality of the entire solution.
Right?
But that's only for specific equations.
You have to do analysis for different equations.
And if you just want to be safe, you can derive a second order approximation for the boundary
condition also.
All right.
Any other questions?
So is that n by n now as opposed to n minus 1?
This is still n minus 1 by n minus 1 because we get u n minus 1 and u n minus 2.
An alternative way.
So there is a lot of ways to deal with boundary conditions.
A different way is to extend the solution all the way to u n.
And if you do that.
. .
You should be using both.
I mean you can use both the differential equation and the boundary condition to derive the evolution
of the last grid point.
D u n d t.
Yeah.
If you want to take that approach, we can talk about that.
All right.
Yeah.
You have a question?
So z is just now a function of time.
Right?
Z, yeah, is just another function of time.
That's right.
Okay.
Yeah.
.
If you use a center difference to approximate the derivative at u n, it actually changes
things because it will involve u n plus 1.
And u n plus 1, there is no way you should include u n plus 1 in the solution.
So in order to cancel u n plus 1, you also need to discretize the differential equation.
. .
The differential equation, the heat equation at u n itself, at the right boundary.
So now you have a differential equation, you have a boundary condition, both involves u
n plus 1.
Use them to cancel it.
So that's how you would do it if you want to use center difference.
.
Any other?
Pardon?
.
Sorry?
You would have another term in the Q represent that's both at the right
boundary different.
Yeah.
Okay.
So let me say.
So alternative, .
.
Is.
. I'm also going to derive the equation for d u n d t, which is equal to u n plus
1, minus u n minus 1, plus u n minus 1, minus 2 u n.
. And I have the central difference approximation.
over 2 delta x equal to z, right?
So that means u n plus 1 is equal to u n minus 1 plus 2 z delta x.
I plug it into here.
That will give me u n minus 1 plus 2 z delta x.
So that is replacing u n plus 1 plus u n minus 1 minus 2 u n over delta x squared.
So we're going to see instead of combining with u n, we're combining with u n minus 1.
So we are still going to change both the matrix and right-hand side, but in a slightly different way.
We are also adding the vector by one additional entry to include u n also as a variable to solve.
So that's the best way to do it when you want to use a central difference to approximate the derivative.