So we have a function of u, u of x and t at a particular t as a function of x.
We are going to discretize the domain into x0, x1, etc. to xn.
So these are a bunch of grid points monotonically increasing.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to only remember ui, which is defined as u at a particular xi.
And ui is a function of t only, and u is a function of x and t.
So now we can see that the time derivative of ui is what?
Well, because ui is just a function of t, I should write it as dui dt.
It's equal to partial u of xi t partial t.
Right, so if we can derive dui dt as an algebraic function of ui and probably other ui functions,
we get a system of uis.
We get an ode.
We get a system of odes.
A coupled system of odes.
And that we can solve.
Okay, so let's continue the derivation.
By the pde, this is equal to kappa times the second order derivative of u at this xi and t.
So the question is, now what?
How do we approximate this?
How do we write this as a function of ui?
Probably ui minus 1, ui plus 1, and et cetera.
Right, how do we write this as a function of these u's?
So here, the second order derivative has a very nice approximation.
This is because a second order derivative is the first order derivative of the function
of ui.
So we have the derivative of the first order derivative.
And the first order derivative on this function is the slope.
And if we discretize this solution on these grid points, remember these circles we saw
on the computer?
We have the slopes.
We don't have the slope on the grid points, but we have the average slope in between the
grid points.
Right?
We basically, we can link any of these two circles, and we get the average slope.
And now, this average slope approximates the first order derivative.
So taking the difference between the nearest average slopes, we can hope to approximate
the second order derivative.
So, we can do this.
We can do this.
So let's write down the approximation.
So the approximation can be written as the difference between the nearest slopes divided
by the difference between the location of these nearest slopes.
So the nearest slope can be written as ui plus 1 minus ui divided by delta x.
So delta x is the spacing between all the uniform slopes.
So the nearest slope can be written as ui plus 1 minus ui into the point delta x.
And then delta x is the spacing between all the uniform grid points.
The uniform.
In the simplest case for finite difference, we use the uniform grid points.
And this is the slope.
Let's say this is the ith grid point.
This is the i plus one, and this is the i minus one grid point.
And now what we have written down is, we have the slope.
The slope is now 0.
And we introduced the slope.
We have the slope.
And now, this is the slope.
And now, we have the slope.
this slope and we also need to minus ui minus ui minus 1 divided by delta x. So
that's that slope. We divide that by the spacing between these two slopes which
is again delta x and we collect the terms. What we get is ui plus 1 plus ui
minus 1 minus 2 times ui divided by delta x squared. That is a standard way
to approximate the second order derivative using finite difference. Now
with that approximation we get this being left hand side and this being
right hand side. That's an ODE we can solve.
We get dui dt equal to kappa times ui plus 1 plus ui minus 1 minus 2 ui
divided by delta x. And that is true for
i equal to 1 2 3 2n minus 1. And on the two sides we have boundary conditions
which we will talk later. The simplest type of boundary condition is u0 which
is u at the left hand side of the domain has to equal to a specific value at the
left and un which is the value at the right end of the domain is equal to a
different specific number.
Thank you.