Okay, we already discussed the truncation error in finite difference.
So the truncation error is how much error we are making in approximating all the differential operators in the equation.
So in our previous case, we did two equations.
It's equal to kappa times pi square u pi square x square.
And the truncation error, because we are not approximating the time derivative term, we're just treating it as OD, we are only converting from PD to OD.
The truncation error in that process of truncation error is how much error we are making in finite difference.
So the conversion is defined as ui plus 1 plus ui minus 1 minus 2ui divided by delta x minus, we also have a kappa, minus pi square u pi square x square.
Right?
That's the truncation error.
So this is the error in approximating the PDE.
It is not the error in the solution.
What do I mean by the error in the solution?
The error in the solution is the difference, as I call it, e.
That's the error in the solution.
It is the difference between the ui you get minus u at i delta x analytic.
The word analytic.
A total error in the solution is known as a total time error.
The relative expression is used a lot because when we compare a numerical solution with an analytic solution, for example the straight line, we know at the end of the evaluation, we use u analytic as the real solution, the actual solution, the exact solution, so some people also use the exact here.
And.
In your project you also are going to derive an analytic solution before you even start coding.
But in a lot of cases, there is a constant of time, that's the result is also given to the solution owner.
It's a function function as a function again.
Right?
Yeah.
Eat it.
literally keep telling me to do it Triangle.
is no analytic solutions to start with so we may also think of that as a exact
solution some solution that you can't really derive but it's still there is
the exact solution of the partial differential equation so now the
solution error is what's the difference between the numerical solution and the
exact solution and this is different from the truncation error it can be
quite different okay and it is different because of this so if you solve if you
solve the equation in two ways right if you write down
a
the differential equation for the analytic one, this is actually, let me just write it as A,
this is the equation satisfied by the analytic solution.
And the actual numerical solution satisfies a different equation.
It satisfies, let me use hat to denote the numerical solution,
to distinguish from the analytical solution.
It's equal to kappa times the finite difference operator,
or the discretized operator.
So this is the equation satisfied by these two different equations.
Okay.
Now, if you subtract,
the right-hand side,
the left-hand side equation from the left-hand side equation,
what do you get?
If you do that subtraction,
what you get is,
the left-hand side is the derivative of u hat minus the derivative of u analytic.
Or, if you collect this derivative,
it's actually,
it's actually partial e, partial t.
Right?
Okay.
And now, the right-hand side is different by kappa times ui plus 1 hat,
plus ui minus 1 hat, minus 2 ui hat,
divided by,
uh,
delta x squared,
minus partial squared ua partial x squared.
Okay.
So this term,
is it the truncation error?
Is it?
So can somebody see the difference between the right-hand side of this equation and the
truncation error?
So if the right-hand side is just the truncation error, that's great, because I know that if
the truncation error first of all is small, then the solution error just grows by a rate
that is defined by the truncation error.
So if the truncation error is going to be bounded, for example, by 10 to the minus 5,
then my solution error is going to be bounded by 10 to the minus 5 times t, which as long
as t is not huge, I'm happy.
But unfortunately, it doesn't work like that.
If you look at the right-hand side, what's the difference between this and tau?
Is this equal to tau?
Yes?
Well, there's a ua there instead of just u.
Exactly.
There is a ua here instead of u.
The truncation error is defined by plugging the same u, the same solution, to two u's.
So there's two different operators, one analytic, one numeric.
Well, the right-hand side of this error equation is by plugging two different solutions into
two different operators.
It's plugging the numerical solution into the numerical operator, and the analytic solution
into the analytic operator.
Okay, so there is one step between this and tau, and that is the step that can mess up
a lot of things if you are not careful.
And that's what makes things like stability very important.
So that step is the following.
First of all, I want to look at, I want to basically make the truncation error, I want
to construct, I want to manufacture a truncation error in this.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to minus a ui plus 1 analytic.
Plus, sorry.
Plus ui minus 1 analytic, minus 2 ui analytic here.
This is manufactured.
Then plus the same thing.
I'm subtracting and adding the same thing, which is basically doing nothing, making the
equation still hold.
Right?
You see what I'm doing here?
I'm subtracting this term and I'm adding the same term into the equation.
Alright.
So now where is the truncation error?
Do we see something that is actually equal to the truncation error here?
The second line, right?
This is now plugging the same analytical solution, both are ua, into two different operators.
So this is the truncation error.
But we also have a first term.
We also have a first term that is actually plugging in two different solutions into the
same discrete operator.
And these two different solutions, the difference between them is actually e.
This u hat minus ua is actually e.
So the time evolution of the error has two terms.
One term is the truncation error.
Another term is plugging in the error itself into the discrete operator.
And the first term is why stability of the discrete operator is very important.
Because if the operator is not stable.
That means even.
A very slight truncation error is going to be exponentially amplified by the discrete
operator and your whole solution error becomes huge.
Your solution becomes garbage.
Alright, we are going to continue discussing that next lecture.