very good and now let's try to use this to solve the Poisson's equation okay so
so now we have these basis functions and remember in Poisson's equation we have
the AIJ's being the integration of the derivative of a pair of basis functions
plus a boundary term right and in particular we are if we have the zero
delicious boundary condition so if we know you and zero is equal to u at 1
equal to 0 what do we know about these linear combination coefficients
so if we want to if we want to represent a u of X equal to summation of I goes
from 0 to n ui of phi i of X we know that the first term can be 0 can be
removed from this linear combination and the last term can be removed from the
linear combination right
so essentially the effect of the this particular boundary condition is
reducing the dimensionality of the linear space it reduces the first and
last basis to be redundant right you don't need any contribution from the
base first basis and you don't need any contribution from the last basis or
equivalently you can eliminate these two functions from the linear combination
so basically we have the basic set so then we basically instead of I goes from
0 we have I goes from 1 to n minus 1 right so that removes two basis functions
two basis functions
ok now why not
we remove theses basis functions we only
have the interior head functions whose whose values are 0 at both X and
x equal to 0 and x equal to 1 so so the so the boundary terms the boundary terms
we have phi j times the derivative of phi i at 0 and 1 is equal to 0 and 1 hier boat
okay so here we are finding the MAS EST Nash V if we let the variation go from 0 to n you will see that the derivative fromostic解 from 0 and it can play off to the term with the difference in and if the asking which branch row average is equal to 1 and x which one mimic whose values represent the finals whose values are at 0 andasion equals to zero and x equals 1 so we now set a boundary conditions to equal to 0.
is equal to 0 for all the interior points for the all the interior basis
functions right for for J equal to 1 all the way to M minus 1 C J times the
derivative of C I to X is equal to 0 so we have a I J is equal to integration of
V I DX and the derivative of V J DX so we only have a I J equal to that we also
have B J equal to no derivative just the P J times F DX okay so let's figure out
what the derivative of V I is equal to 0 for all the interior points for the all the
interior points for the all the interior points for the all the interior points for the
so for the matrix we are looking at the integral of the derivative of the
product now the pro the integral of the product of the derivative of two basis
functions and because of the locality of the basis functions so both VI and VJ
are nonzero only zero so we can see that the derivative of the product of the
monetary duty SSD complete using no linear Fish I
this stoichiometric passion of this say pattern so now the D and the relative
molar of their premiums is equal to zero we show the hermit Europeans are general
Association and I D viewer k
or their support, the region in which they are non-zero, has no overlap,
then their product is going to stay zero over the entire domain.
Right, so remember we have, if this is x i, this is x j, we have many subintervals.
Because x i, if you think of the derivative of x i, phi x, so this is phi i, this is phi j,
they are both hat functions.
The derivative of phi i and phi j are like what?
The derivative of phi i is a constant positive value here and a constant negative here,
and zero.
Everywhere else.
And the derivative of phi j is positive here, negative here, and zero everywhere else.
So if you multiply the derivative of phi i with the derivative of phi j,
the product is zero in the entire domain,
because there is no interval in which both of the derivatives are non-zero.
So for most of pairs of i and j, aij is going to be zero.
aij is only non-zero when i and j are close enough.
How close do they need to be for this entry to be non-zero?
Well, of course, yeah.
They have to be immediate neighbors in this case, right?
So if they are immediate neighbors,
one of phi i is like that,
phi j is going to be like that.
So they have one element of overlap
in which the product of the derivatives are going to be non-zero.
Or if i is equal to j, right?
If i and j are equal,
then the derivative are the same,
and they are non-zero in two adjacent intervals.
So aij non-zero if i minus j absolute value less or equal to 1, right?
They are either immediate neighbors or they are the same.
So if a matrix is non-zero only for absolute value of i minus j less or equal to 1,
how does the sparsity pattern of the matrix look like?
It's going to be a tri-diagonal matrix, right?
Okay, so good.
Let's try to construct this tri-diagonal matrix for one-dimensional space.
All right.
, so here again, let's use the interval x to be a link space,
0, 1, and n.
Let's choose n to be just a 10 to start with, n equal to 10.
Okay, so we have,
we actually only have nine intervals in this case, right?
Because x goes from 0 to 1,
and there are nine intervals in this case.
So we have to put n in between.
So let's choose n equal to 9, right?
Okay.
So on that space, we have nine basis functions.
If we know the solution has zero boundary conditions.
If we know the solution has non-zero boundary conditions,
we need more basis functions.
Now we have nine basis functions.
We want to construct the matrix A, which is, let's set 0, 9.
In the beginning, right?
So we know most of the entries are 0, so we set it to be 0.
Let's first construct the diagonal entries.
So how big are the diagonal entries of this matrix,
which corresponds to i equals to j?
So the diagonal entries are entries corresponding to
aii is equal to integration from 0 to 1.
The derivative of phi i squared.
And we know it is non-zero only in two intervals.
Either the interval from xi minus 1 to xi,
and the interval xi to xi.
And the interval xi to xi.
What's go on?
It's all linear.
So the all- punches.
Then i equals O are from 1 to 1.
So when we compute, y equals 1,
where's our investigations coming from?
Divided byuffy.
All our stuff is goes regular.
And we can choose what over Here we do an encryption theory.
Anamour has proved it is just an assumption for the
product end Execution we can do.
And if this is the value of method of one over x- of the
answer is f.
So far, very similar.
But we have to connect the type, the 얘.
And we want the definition.
And we want the definition for policy n 0.
Both, have all to be true.
Or we can write the!!!
For Я And this is .
And this- this is even better.
Thank you so much for your answers.
x i plus 1 minus x i right so in this case all our axes are the same but we're
going to evaluate to the X anyway so it's X 2 to n minus X 1 to n minus 1 and
now we have the squared values in both domains and we also want to multiply
this by the length of this integral so after multiplying by the interval
which is X i minus X i minus 1 the square is gone again and once we
multiply by this interval the minus 1 is gone and the square is gone so this
a ii is equal to X i minus X i minus 1 plus 1 over X i plus 1 minus X i right
so this is a ii
so our DX right now is the length of the right so so this is a a ii is going to
be a summation between two adjacent intervals so I think let me see
right okay so I I made a mistake here when I'm constructing the matrix a so so
should the matrix a be a length be a 9 by 9 matrix or 8x8 matrix should be 8x8
matrix right because I only have oops I only have n minus 1 interior grid points
Okay, so it's an 8x8 matrix, and so the diagonal entries of A are, I should be making, so diagonal is a function that constructs a diagonal matrix from a vector,
should be dx, so 1 over dx, 2 to n, plus 1 over dx, 1 to n minus 1.
So A has its diagonal entries assigned, right, so they are all 18.
Now let's figure out the off-diagonal entries of A.
Okay.
The off-diagonal entries of A.
The off-diagonal entries of A, A i, i plus 1, is going to be equal to an integration from 0 to 1,
the derivative of phi i times the derivative of phi j, which is i plus 1, partial x dx.
And this, because phi i is non-diagonal,
is non-zero at interval between x i minus 1 and x i plus 1.
And phi i plus 1 is non-zero in the interval between phi i and phi i plus 2.
So their product is only non-zero between x i and x i plus 1.
And their derivatives are what?
This derivative in between x i and x i, i minus 1, is something we derived before,
minus 1 over x i plus 1 minus x i.
Now this derivative is positive, because it's on the left of the basis.
But the value is the same, it's also 1 over the same interval length.