So the GST scheme is a scheme that chooses in between these two...
So we know that adding a dissipative flux proportional to delta x cubed times the third-order derivative of u
is appropriate for smooth regions of the solution.
And adding what we added before, a dissipation proportional to the second-order derivative,
a much stronger dissipation because it's proportional to delta x instead of the much smaller delta x cubed,
is appropriate around shock waves and the local extremis.
So the GST scheme is simply a scheme that chooses in between them
according to the same limiter we have been using to reconstruct the solution.
So the first step is to construct a limiter phi that is equal to 0 or 1
if 0 is non-smooth and 1 is smooth, and they can also go in between.
So we can use the same limiter we used in our scalar conservation law.
And second step...
is to construct a second-order derivative...
so second-order dissipation flux,
which is proportional to the first-order derivative times the maximum value of the characteristic speed.
And third step is to construct a numerical dissipation proportional...
to the third-order derivative that is going to give us a fourth-order dissipation.
And then combine them using the value of phi.
In such a way that if phi is equal to 1, then we are purely using the third-order derivative.
And if phi is equal to 0, we are also going to be using the first-order derivative.
Alright, so for example, we can...
we can multiply...
we can have this value, the third-order derivative...
to be also always times 1, and the second-order derivative to be times 1 minus phi.
And that gives us the appropriate behavior of...
when phi is equal to 0, we turn on the stronger dissipation.
And when phi is equal to 1, we turn off that stronger dissipation.
So that's...
that's what...
that's how the GST scheme deals with system of conservation laws.
Achieving second-order accuracy, but still being non-oscillatory around shock waves.
It computes the limit of the same as what we compute before.
Based on local extremis and the ratio between slopes between different solutions.
And construct a second-order and fourth-order dissipation.
And perform linear conservation.
And then we can use the combination of them,
trimming the second-order on and off,
according to the value of the limit.
So this is the most advanced material we are going to go into in finite volume schemes.
So with this...
this also applies for...
this also applies for multiple dimensions.
The only difference in multiple dimensions is that...
the gradient reconstruction.
So here, we are constructing the gradient by just taking the difference between two adjacent cells.
In multiple dimensions, you need to take more than two cells to reconstruct a gradient.
Usually you take multiple cells around you and perform a least squares type of estimate for the gradient value.
Because in 2D, for example, the gradient gives you two values, right?
So in x and in y.
But like the number of...
the number of surrounding cells may be more than two.
So...
so you have more equations to satisfy than unknowns when you are trying to calculate the gradient.
If you have exactly two adjacent cells, like in a...
then you can solve two equations for two unknowns, being the gradient.
If you have many, many cells around you, you have an over-determined system,
and you use these squares...
to get the gradient.
But all the other stuff are the same.
Okay?
In multiple dimensions.
Yes?
I'm not very clear how to use the signature to decide how to do the third-order dissipation.
Oh, that's a...
that's a good question.
The third-order dissipation can be always wrong.
That's...
that's something...
that's the simplest way to determine...
the third-order dissipation.
Right?
It's always wrong.
Because if we don't have a shock wave, it's...
it can be there, providing stability while giving us at least a second-order accuracy.
When shock wave is...
when you're around a shock wave, it's also okay to have this term in,
because the second-order proportional to delta x term is gonna be over-realmedialized.
Okay?
overwhelmingly strong so you don't have to you don't have to diminish the third
order term when you're around the shockwave