If u0 is equal to u, it's still going to be u, exactly.
This is because we just wrote the equation without the superscripts, right?
Without the superscript, the equation is exactly satisfied by the solution to the linear equations.
So if u0 is already u, then the left-hand side is u1.
And u1 has to be also u in order for this equation to be satisfied.
Well, unless d is degenerate, unless d has zero entries, it's a diagonal matrix, right?
So if all the diagonal parts are non-zero, then u1 can only be u.
And therefore, if u1 is equal to u, u2 also has to be u.
If u2 has to be u, u3 also has to be u, etc.
So if you start it with the right solution, you'll always end up with the right solution.
Of course, that's a big assumption, right?
So you almost never start with the right solution.
So what do you get?
What do you get if you don't have the right solution to start with?
So let's define.
Let's look at now the error equation.
So the error equation is looking at,
so if I define solution error ek to be the difference between the solution I have minus the real solution,
well, in practice, I never know what ek is because I don't know the true solution.
But if I can derive a governing equation for the evolution of ek,
we can analyze is the solution error becoming smaller and smaller or becoming larger and larger as I iterate.
And we want to construct the method or derive conditions for the method so that ek is going to,
you know,
decreasing as I increase k.
So how do we derive the equation for ek?
We subtract this equation with the superscript.
We subtract the equation without a superscript from the equation with the superscript.
By doing this, the left-hand side would be du k plus 1 minus du.
The right-hand side would be b,
minus l,
u,
k,
minus u,
u,
k,
minus b,
minus l,
u,
minus u,
u.
Right?
This is just subtracting two equalities.
Both are true.
And simply by linearity and the definition of ek,
the left-hand side becomes d of ek plus 1.
And the right-hand side,
the b,
fortunately,
cancels.
What we are left with is l plus u,
and I think we have a minus sign here,
times ek.
So the last thing we want to do is further simplify this by multiplying a d inverse.
Remember, the method only works if d has non-zero diagonals.
So let's multiply a d inverse on both equations,
both equations.
So the left-hand side becomes ek plus 1,
the right-hand side becomes minus d inverse times l plus u times ek.
Good here?
So we can start analyzing whether the ek would increase or decrease over time.
What determines if ek is going to increase or decrease over time?
The eigenvalue.
Yes, the eigenvalue.
Right.
So the eigenvalue is going to be the eigenvalue of the equation.
The eigenvalue of this matrix.
This matrix is so important it has a name.
It's called the iteration matrix.
So this matrix determines, actually, the stability of this matrix determines if the ek is going
to increase over time or decrease over time.
Okay.
So because if this matrix, if the iteration matrix, well, the iteration matrix of Jacobi
iteration or Jacobi iteration matrix can be expressed as eigenvalue recomposition v times
lambda times the inverse, okay, then if we can say E zero, our initial error, which of
course we don't know, can be expressed as a summation of a times vi where vi
is a operated function.
v i is the columns of the matrix v.
Okay, the same expression can be written as the matrix v times a vector a,
so a1, et cetera, to an.
Right, so this is a, so if the iteration matrix is,
has a full set of eigenvalues, we can basically write it like that, right?
Write any vector to be v times a vector corresponding to the linear combination of the eigenvectors that gives you that vector.
Yes?
Why isn't that the lambda?
Shouldn't that be the lambda matrix?
Aren't we, like, decoupling?
Why is it lambda here?
Why not?
Here?
Which equation are you looking at?
Sorry, yeah, right there.
Okay, yeah, this is, we are just trying to express the initial error in our initial guess
as a linear combination of the columns in v.
Yeah, sorry, I didn't think of that.
Right, so if we can do that, then e1 is going to be v times lambda times v inverse times e0.
Right?
Which, by this expression, is v times lambda times v inverse times v times this vector a.
Okay, and this v inverse and v cancels.
So we get v times lambda times vector a.
We can keep going.
Okay, now, instead of v times a,
we can keep going.
Okay, so e1 is going to be v times lambda times a.
We can do the same trick again.
e2 would be equal to going through the same thing.
We would have v lambda v inverse times v lambda a.
And again, this cancels.
We get a v times lambda square times a.
And we can keep going, right?
So, e to the kth index would be v times lambda to the kth power.
times a. So as long as the diagonal entries of lambdas are all less than 1,
right, or if it's complex, its magnitude has to be less than 1, and then
this ek would ultimately diminish to 0. We would be happy that we have a
convergent iterative method which means ek is going to go to 0, and what
does ek goes to 0 mean? my uk is going to converge to u.
So although I don't know what u is, I mean when k is sufficiently large, I have
a sufficiently accurate approximation to you. Alright, and also
here we are lucky that we can check how well we are converging because we also
have the residual that is we can check conversions by looking at the residual
K equal to B minus a UK so this should be zero if UK is already you right so
this is a good criterion for convergence and by the way the convergence here is
different from the convergence of a numerical method of a finite difference
discretization or a finite element discretization when we talk about
convergence in finite difference we are thinking oh okay so let's decrease our
grid size by a factor of two
should my numerical solution approach the analytical solution right so that is
the kind of convergence we are talking about in finite difference or finite
element or finite volume but here convergence has a different meaning
although we all use the word convergence it actually means different things
convergence here means the convergence of the kth iteration to the discrete
solution
of a PD right so so the because a u equal to B is already a discretized
differential equation so even if I get the exact u here the u would be a
discrete solution and this UK is an approximation to the discrete solution
we are talking about how does UK converge to the discrete solution here
well that makes sense so that's the first thing we are talking about here
well that means when you solve the equation using intuitive methods you are
making two approximations here one approximation is of of course the
discretization of the PDE the numerical solution only approximate the analytical
solution up to an approximation error and the second is that you are that of
course both involves spatial discretization and time discretization if
you have time so so remember you can go to the internet and you can go to the
computer and you can go to the computer and you can go to the computer and you
have the spatial terms also you have time derivative squarization terms and
now if you have space and time squarization you count that as two
sources of errors now this is a third source of error that is when K is not
sufficiently large you not even have an exact solution to the discrete equations
right you can estimate how much error you have by looking at the residual but
then remember that's a another source of approximation another source of error
here