Okay, so that's how to run a parametric sweep.
You add a global parameter.
You use that parameter to drive any part of the model, including the geometry or any physical
calculations or even mesh nodes, mesh density, and then you can compute and then compare
the results.
I do want to show you the very last step, was converting from model to an app.
I won't go into too much details here because I think we are getting closer with time.
So I have 14 more minutes, right?
To 1055?
Okay.
So what I'll do is I will show you app building 101 or even 000.
So what I'll do is I'll pick one model that's already built and solved in COMSOL in the
... Let's see.
So first of all, how to get here.
When you ... After you install the trial of COMSOL, go to ...
Okay.
... File, Application Library.
Here's the collection of examples we have built with each of the module.
So before you want to build a molecular flow problem, don't do it yet.
Go into one of the example, open the PDF.
Each of the example comes with a PDF including a background introduction of that particular
example plus some meaningful results and analysis plus a step-by-step instruction of how this
model was built.
So duplicate a couple of them.
Just to familiarize yourself with the workflow and where to find out different options.
Or hopefully there is even an example that's similar to exactly what you want to do.
And then make changes on that and start building your own model.
So what I'll use right here ... Well, so first of all, before you attend Wednesday's class,
I would strongly recommend you to go through the COMSOL multi-physics, which is the base
package and the equation-based examples here.
So some of those, Tammy will be explaining a lot more details, but it doesn't hurt to
just have a preview of those.
Okay.
So right now, to demonstrate the app building, I'm going to use one under multi-physics and
it's called the BossBar.
I'm going to open that model.
If you do want to know how to build this BossBar, which is another dual heating problem, that's
intro booklet.
There are two examples you can work through.
Again, step-by-step instructions.
The second one is this BossBar one.
I mentioned that this example, although it's electrical and heat transfer so far, it can
easily become a fluid flow problem.
Because you can add a surrounding box and introduce convective cooling, which is a lot
of times happens in especially older generation laptop when you have a fan inside that helps
you have the cooling of the actual component.
So you can add fluid flow on top of that.
That's what I mean.
So here is the working model.
Again, it's soft.
It has colorful images.
It's the actual current plus heat transfer.
I want to use this one because it already has a defined parameter list that controls
the different parts of the system.
So how do I convert this model to an app?
If you are using Windows and you have the console ribbon on the top and you'll see the
first button here is called Application Builder.
Hit the Application Builder button.
Now you are switched from Model Builder to Application Builder.
There is a button to switch you back, again, on the Home tab, the first tab here.
So the two key concepts here I want to introduce is a new form and a new method.
A new form is essentially the layout of your user-defined app.
So you add a new form, you tell CommSol what you want to include on that front panel.
It's like LabVIEW for those of you who know.
So, for example, I want my user to be able to change a few parameters.
I want them to be able to see what is the temperature plot.
I want to give them some buttons, for example, a compute button.
So that's it.
So that's the layout of the app.
I could move things around.
It's essentially a PowerPoint.
I could resize the graphics window.
And then when you hit test application, it'll just work.
You could either run the app through a CommSol license or CommSol server license.
The demo.comsol.com link I gave earlier allows you to upload and run apps.
So anywhere you are, as long as you have internet access, you don't have to use a Windows machine to run an app.
Any platform, including your iPhone, would be able to run an app.
So you can just log into that website.
Either upload or if you already saved it out, then you can just hit compute.
Change one of the parameters.
It'll work and it'll give you the results.
This is not, well, this is the very simple version of it.
You can also add a method.
So method is essentially a JavaScript environment.
So I myself don't know any Java.
So how am I going to demonstrate it?
I'm going to record a code.
So now everything here shows in a round box, a red box.
So I'm going to switch back to Model Builder.
Say if I share.
I'm going to change any part of the model from 6 to 8.
I'll do something else.
Change the mesh to user defined.
Build a mesh.
And I could stop recording, go back to my app builder.
Everything I did will be recorded as a JavaScript.
So at least you know where to go.
And now instead of 8, I'm smart enough to know I can change that 8 into a different parameter and that'll still work.
And then on top of that, you can add more things.
So.
I'll show you one example that everybody knows and the beauty of it is actually play some sound.
So I'm going to find.
Yeah, so every application.
So the ones with the app interface is in the application folder.
Each of the module has an application folder.
So the ACDC example with the app interface that's actually in that folder.
So I'm going to show you a tuning fork.
Directly hit run app.
Don't save the change.
So this is a tuning fork app.
It runs in two modes.
You can tell Comso how long the tuning fork forks are.
The prone length.
And it computes.
It's going to tell you the natural frequency.
So that is what a
455.6 Hz sounds like.
The other mode it works on is actually a combination of structural mechanics and optimization.
So I want to.
I mean.
I want to.
You know maybe.
Next to a 3D printer.
I want to say I want to.
50, 90, 490 Hz.
Tell me how long that the prone length should be.
It's going to take slightly longer because of the optimization algorithm here.
And by the way to add that optimization.
Literally one expression in one step of the solver.
Not complicated at all.
So you can see that.
It's going to be.
A little bit.
Slightly higher pitch.
So if you have good ears you can tell the difference between 450 and 490.
Or if you are tuning your violin you can maybe use the app as well.
All right so that's the very last step here from the model to the app.
So app is essentially a model plus a user interface.
And by user interface we mean not only just the front cover of it.
Like the W.
But also the back wires.
Which is what makes the buttons work.
So you can associate different.
Commands with the different buttons.
Trigger them to do different things.
So the app builder is only including Windows because it so far uses the Windows native technology.
But once you have the app as I said you can run across all the different smart devices.
So the server I mentioned.
So once you log in it's actually.
Nothing you need to set up.
So you basically.
I've set you to be the user.
Authority.
So you can run any of the.
Apps that's been uploaded out.
We use them for workshop demos a lot of times.
You can upload your own.
And then you can run your own.
Apps from now.
So for show and tell right.
Okay so.
Next thing I just want to say a few quick words about.
We'll show you some colorful images.
Before the end of the presentation.
So for the electrical category.
The ACDC module as I mentioned does a lower frequency or even stationary and transient problems.
So.
When you simulate.
I know you are from different engineering courses.
So when you're simulating like conductors, resistors, inductors, capacitors, calculate capacitances.
Or the transformers, generators.
They can use ACDC module.
Anything that's involving the full Maxwell equation.
So the wave propagation that is RF module.
When you have the.
You know when the system size, the simulation domain size is much larger than the wavelength.
Computational effort goes up.
Very very quickly.
So usually the rule of thumb is you have your.
10 wavelengths by 10 wavelengths by 10 wavelengths.
For the full Maxwell equation.
You probably want to have a machine with 64 gigabit of memory or more.
So.
Basically it scales very quickly because for each of the wavelengths you want to have at least 5 quadratic elements.
So when you go beyond that system size.
You use an alternative approach. Either beam envelope method.
A slow invariant beam capturing the wave.
With the capturing.
Faster wave in each of the wavelengths.
Or the ray tracing.
Technique in the ray optics module.
Plasma module that works on all the different dimensions.
And then you can couple with the existing coil designs as well.
It basically covers the ICP, the inductively coupled plasma, CCP, the capacitively coupled
microwave plasma.
And also the DC discharge plasma as well.
So the.
So the low temperature.
9 qubit.
And then the MAMS module. I mentioned this.
Basically a combined capability from ACDC and structural.
Plus the unique airfo-mechanics in space.
So some of the examples here are antenna communications on an airplane and also in the windshield wipers in the car.
And yeah this example is actually quite a popular one. It's called thermal lensing.
So we have ray tracing but the lens actually.
Expands because of thermal effects.
And then you have that the shift of the focal.
Then the mechanical branch.
So the.
No matter what dimension it is. You can have the 1d beam and truss network.
Or you can have the 2d membrane or shells. You can have a 3d solid.
Or a combination of those materials.
As long as they are linear materials. You can use structural mechanics module for it.
Then the different non-linearity.
Using the non-linear structural materials module.
I do want to emphasize that if you do deal with piezoelectric actuation in any of the cases.
Then the structural mechanics module.
Can deal with any type of orientation of the piezoelectric activity.
A reinforced concrete beam in picture number one.
And let's see what else.
Fluid structure interaction way in that the satellite panel.
So basically that's another pretty fun coupled in space in COMSO.
Which saw fluid flow and solid mechanics.
And the moving mesh mechanism.
The arbitrary log around Eulerian method.
The moving mesh in COMSO.
There's also.
Comparing to the moving mesh.
There's also something called a deformed geometry.
The difference is that moving mesh captures the same material frame.
Which means that there's no addition or removal of material.
To introduce that shape change.
You're literally deforming certain existing.
Sixth-max geometry.
So when you have a.
For example an.
Electrodeposition.
Or corrosion problem.
Then that's a deformed geometry.
Because you're adding materials.
Or moving materials.
Or some growth of materials.
I don't know if you have.
So far in the lecture.
Where the level set and the phase field method is.
So basically we have.
Well I'll talk about it in the next slide actually.
We have two phase flow.
If you want to track where the interface.
The surface tension induced.
And the momentum induced.
The shape change of the meniscus.
Then you could use either the level set or phase field method.
Which is essentially another set.
Or two additional.
Deformed volumes.
On top of the Navier-Stokes equation.
And the.
Additional parameter.
Basically when.
Larger than 0.5 is one phase.
More than 0.5 is another phase.
And it's a diffused in phase.
As opposed to the third method in.
Tracking the in phase.
Is the moving mesh method.
Which you have an x-ray mesh.
So the level set and phase field.
Solved on fixed mesh.
And moving mesh actually disturbed the.
Perturbs the mesh nodes.
Limitation of moving mesh is that.
You cannot merge or split the nodes.
You cannot make nodes disappear.
So basically we have a.
Joclet.
Merging or breaking.
Problems.
That you cannot use the moving mesh.
But the other two methods.
Still work.
They have different other concepts.
In terms of the.
Solving other types of physics as well.
So the.
Just want to briefly talk about examples here.
The first one is the.
Heated floor.
So it uses the.
Piped flow module.
For the non-isothermal pipe flow.
The pipe flow can actually do piped acoustics as well.
And you can specify different pipe cross-section shapes.
And the geometry.
Heat transfer.
So that's a hidden tube.
Exchanger.
That you can have.
Because both the heat transfer part and fluid part are based on.
So the flux calculation is most accurate.
And the coupling is the most accurate as well.
So some simulator conditions.
You use in your heat sink.
So that's the corrosion.
And the.
Plating that I mentioned.
So that's the electrochemistry.
On top of the.
Deformed geometry.
You know.
For the mesh.
And then there's some surface reaction.
And the.
Dark curves.
For the.
Sexy photometry.
So I do want to.
Quickly mention that optimization module. A lot of times people use.
Two different scenarios. One is called the shape optimization.
That's the top one. Which is actually.
Acoustics problem with straight walls on the horn.
In the beginning.
And then you allow five.
Points. Physical points to move on their boundaries.
To make the corrugated shape.
To get a maximum sound effect.
So again. You cannot have mesh nodes crossing each other.
So.
You'll end up with the same topology.
You won't go from a sphere to a donut.
If you do want to go from a sphere to a donut.
Any number of holes. You use the topology optimization.
That basically.
Just specify what the bounding box. And you can have shaded material anywhere.
Alright. I think.
Yeah. That's pretty much it.
So just want to emphasize the resources that you can use.