So we have integration from a to b phi j times f minus summation of i goes from 1 to n, a i phi i dx equal to 0.
So let's pull these things out.
So the first term is phi j f times dx.
And then the summation can be pulled out of the integral.
a i's are not a function of x, so it can be pulled out of the integral.
And the integral becomes integration from a to b phi j phi i dx is equal to 0.
Alright.
f is a known function.
If we can construct an explicit set of faces, phi 1, phi 2, etc.,
then we can compute this integration.
So we can write the integral for any f.
Right, so let's define a vector b that is equal to integration of a to b phi 1 f dx,
integration a to b phi 2 f dx, all the way to integration of phi n f dx.
Okay.
Also, if we can construct an explicit form of phi,
we can write the integral for any f.
So integration of phi 1, phi 2, etc.,
we can also define a matrix A.
That is the integral of pairwise products of these basis functions.
Integration of phi 1, phi 1 dx, integration of phi 1, phi 2 dx,
integration of phi 1, phi n dx.
Da da da.
This is integration of phi n, phi 1 dx, etc.
It's actually integration of phi n, phi n, dx.
Right?
So we can get this matrix.
Now, this is a matrix.
This is a vector.
This equality becomes a times a equal to b.
Right?
So the function approximation within a linear space becomes ax equal to b, which we know how to solve.
The process of finite element actually in general is like that.
It is to construct the right-hand side and the matrix by performing integrals of basis functions.
And known functions.
Right?
So basically, you do integrals either numerically using quadrature or analytically if the function is simply enough.
To construct a matrix and the right-hand side.
We solve the matrix to get linear combination of the basis functions.
And the linear combination of the basis functions is going to give us g star that we know is the optimal.
That satisfies all the...
That satisfies this.
Linear equations for any g prime.
G prime we call test function within the linear space.
And because of these linear equations comes out of a projection.
We know that the g prime we get actually minimizes the distance between g in the space and the particular function f.
So in solving differential equations, we are not approximating a particular function.
But we still will be able to use the concept of projection to minimize something.
Right?
Usually the residual of a differential equation or some other quantities.
We minimize a certain quantity that we derive from the differential equation.
And the minimization turns out to be a projection.
Projection turns out to be a system of differential equations.
Using a basis, the system of differential equations turns into a matrix.
We solve the matrix equation.
We get the linear combination coefficients.
And by recombining the basis functions, we get to the solution to the differential equation.
That's generally how finite elements work.