Yeah, the question is, if I have non-zero boundary conditions, what do I do?
So let's just take an exercise and put the same function and make, let's say, the boundary
condition to be non-zero on one of the sides.
Which side do you want?
X equal to zero side?
All right.
So let's first go back to our whiteboard.
But if at x equal to zero, which means r equal to zero, the u is something, right?
So let's, for example, u of zero j is given and not zero.
All right.
How does it affect our equation?
So.
So it affects our equation only for i equal to one, right?
Okay.
Because all the other cases, so we have given solution here.
We have given solution here.
It only is included in the discretization of i equal to one.
So we only need to consider changes in the first n y minus one rows of this matrix equation.
And because this is given.
Because.
Because these numbers are given.
We should actually be moving these numbers to the right-hand side of the equation.
Because it's known.
It's not part of the unknown.
It's not a linear combination of the unknowns.
So moving to the right-hand side of the equation is this term.
Should be moved to here.
It's minus of u zero j divided by delta x squared.
Okay.
So let's do that.
So.
So what I get would be.
Let's use another color to be sure.
What we get is a minus here.
U of.
Here is zero one divided by delta x squared.
Minus u of zero two divided by delta x squared.
And minus u of zero and y minus one divided by delta x squared.
That's going to be our bonding condition.
So what kind of u would you like to see here?
So let's say u x zero is equal to.
Huh?
One.
Just equal to one.
Okay.
So it should be ones of n y minus one one.
Right.
So that's what we.
That's the length of the vector we have.
So what I should do is my f is equal to f.
Not f.
But f from one to n y minus one.
Should be equal to the existing f.
Minus u x zero divided by dx squared.
Right.
So my f is changed only on the first few rows.
Of.
Yeah.
Right.
So let's do that again.
My big.
No.
My small u.
Is equal to this.
My big u.
Is equal to the ray shaped.
And let's make another figure.
And surf again.
Oh not f.
But u.
Wow.
This is weird.
Okay.
But anyway you can see that.
The solution at x.
At x equal to zero.
Let's do the labels again.
x label y label.
Enter.
x equal to zero is now approaching one.
So let's rotate it.
So that like I'm aligned with the.
x axis.
Come on.
It's very hard.
Right click.
X z view.
Right.
Okay.
Great.
We can see that if you.
If you extrapolate over here.
We have the solution goes to one.
At the left boundary.
All right.
Also is your question.
Okay.
Very good.
Any other questions.
This is u.
This is my solution u.
With the modified boundary condition.
So boundary condition you can see it has a huge effect on this.
Previously.
This is my solution.
And if I do the same.
X z view.
Right.
So.
I have a solution that of course goes to zero.
As x goes to zero.
And the whole thing is negative.
And on the order of minus point oh three.
And now.
My whole thing is actually positive.
And the has order one.
All right.
Any other questions.
Yes.
I'm going back to your question.
Okay.
So.
I'm going back to your code.
When you were adding the.
The diagonal that's offset by.
m y.
Minus.
One.
Yes.
These two.
Right.
Why did you.
Make the ones.
Matrix or vector is.
Size that you did.
The.
N x.
Minus.
Two.
N y.
Minus.
One.
That's a good question.
Let's go back to.
The.
Z.
Y.
And x.
Minus.
the matrix. So let's go look at the matrix. So this 1 over delta x squared is what I'm
adding, right? So it goes all the way to here. And let's count how many do we have.
So in the first block, in every block, we have n1 minus 1 of this 1 over delta x squared.
And how many blocks do we have? On the diagonal part, we totally have nx minus 1 blocks. That's
on the diagonal blocks. But on this, what we call upper diagonal block, we have one
less block than the number of blocks we have on the diagonal.
So that makes nx minus 2 blocks. And each block has n1 minus 1 entries. So the total
number of entries is n1 minus 1 times nx minus 2, which is that, right? Does that answer your
question?
Yes.
Okay.
Any other questions?
Yes?
Are all figures represented?
We are not plotting the boundary cells exactly, because we are only plotting our unknowns.
And the boundary cells also need a solution.
because it's known, it's not part of the unknown.
But on the x-axis, which
up into 1, so should there actually
be a gap between where our figure ends and where the 1
ends?
That's a good question.
Yeah, that's actually a good point.
I must have made a mistake here.
So that's my mistake.
dx and dy shouldn't be 1 divided by nx minus 1 and ny minus 1.
It should be just divided by nx and ny.
So let's modify that.
That's a very sharp observation.
dy is equal to 1 over ny.
So let's see, where should we repeat?
We should be, let me close all the figures.
Right, so sharp observations like that
is very helpful in debugging your code.
When you see something wrong, you see it in the beginning,
as opposed to when you see some complication later on.
So that's very good.
I should be doing, constructing the diagonal blocks
and the constructor matrix.
I need to redo them.
And also reconstruct the x and y.
And also I want to reconstruct the f and small f.
And now I need to compute the solution u and reshape it.
And then surf and xy label.
All right.
Now let's rotate it.
OK, I need to first click this and right click,
set on to xz view.
And now that's the right plot.
All right, thank you.
And if you want to include the boundaries,
you can add one more row, one more column,
onto both x and y and also u.
And then plot it again.
All right, thanks for debugging that for me.
Any other questions?
Any other vox you found?
So when we have a boundary condition of y and x,
it seems like for some part of the surface
is negative.
Oh, OK.
So I think I understand what you mean.
You see in some part of the domain,
it seems to have a negative curvature.
So let's take a look at that also.
So where was that?
OK, so I constructed ux0 f and solve that again
and do that again and do that again.
Wait, this.
Right, so this is what we have.
And you're asking, are you asking this part of the?
Yeah.
It looks like it has a negative curvature in this direction.
OK.
So it's a positive curvature in this direction.
Right?
But if you rotate it, it seems to also have a positive curvature
in the x direction.
Right?
So the Laplace thing is actually the curvature in the x direction
plus the curvature in the y direction.
And if you remember in here, when you get x close to 0,
the curvature is sine x times cosine y.
Sine x is almost 0.
So the curvature is almost 0.
That means your x curvature and y curvature is the same.
And y curvature is supposed to cancel out each other pretty much.
Right?
So in order for the function to make up
to the boundary condition of 1, it
needs to have a strong x curvature, which
means you need a negative y curvature to compensate.
Sure.
And we have a look at f.
Oh, can you take a look at f again?
Figure of f.
That's f.
At x close to 0, you get almost 0.
Right?
I don't mean f.
I mean the new right-hand side.
Oh, the new right-hand side.
It means small f?
Yeah.
Small f is one dimensional.
So I can plot small f.
But it'll be something like that.
So small f for the first block is very, very negative
because of the boundary condition.
Right?
So this part is different from all the rest.
All the rest actually looks pretty much 0 compared to that.
But I'm sure they are not really 0.
They are.
Right.
They are not really 0.
But it has much less magnitude than the first block
due to the boundary condition.
Yeah?
So just to be more general, should we also include the points at the boundary
as unknowns as possible?
So should you include the points at the boundary
if you have more complex boundary conditions,
which makes the boundary points also unknown,
it is appropriate to include the boundary points also as unknowns.
Yeah.
That's right.
So you need to distinguish what is known, what is unknown
in the data.
Yeah.
Yes, yeah, .
That is the main thing.
Uh oh.
dité¡
Hello, take the public feedback for the first time after the
transcript.
One of the things it oil07
is that guys,
I have this question now which
have rows of a matrix that only has a diagonal term, that means I'm setting the
value at that point to the corresponding value in the right-hand side. So that is
also a potential trick you can use if you find it easier to code.