Let's first construct the diagonal block.
Okay, so first of all, how big are they?
How big is each of these diagonal blocks?
ny minus 1 by ny minus 1, right?
Okay, so let's first construct these entries on the diagonal.
So before we do that, we need to compute dx is equal to 1 over nx minus 1.
dy is equal to 1 over ny minus 1.
So my diagonal block is going to be identity of ny minus 1 times minus 2 divided by delta x squared minus 2 divided by delta y squared.
All right, so my diagonal block.
Is just like that for now.
Okay, so I need to field in the upper and lower diagonals by 1 over delta y squared.
So I'm going to teach you a different trick as I did last time.
This is equal to diagonal block plus a diagonal entry of 1.
So first of all, how many entries do they have?
They have two entries, which is ny minus 2, right?
So first of all, I construct the ones of ny minus 2 rows and one column.
So it's basically a column vector of ny minus 1 ones.
I'm going to divide it by delta y squared.
Okay, so I get the same size of row vectors of 1 over delta y squared.
I'm going to make it.
I'm going to.
So this is the second.
This is the first entry of the argument for diagonal.
The second entry is 1.
That means I don't want the exact diagonal.
I want it to be shifted to the.
I think 1 is upper diagonal.
I'm not sure.
Let's take a look.
Yes.
You see, this upper diagonal has changed to 9.
Which is 1 over delta y squared.
All right.
So that works.
Now I need to fill in the lower diagonals.
What should I do?
Minus 1 on this.
So I'm going to use the same command here.
But the second argument to diagonal is going to be minus 1.
So that helps me fill out the lower diagonal entries.
All right.
Okay.
So now I get a diagonal block like that.
How many of these diagonal blocks do I need to have?
Because we can limit them to holes bit Ooo.
So I can cup generated twohoods.
That's it.
Okay.
So let's continue reading.
Let's see this.
Let's take a look at that.
So usually salography command will be just greaxed.
In that case.
Basically, we will be reading what we need to see and how much will take into account in nat looks like alpha and 1.
Then we in the sample.
We just inherited same approach to theaken.
But instead of just talking about how could I methodically sporty trong the default method?
Then.
So if A is an identity matrix, B is this 2x2 matrix of 1, minus 1, minus 1, 1s.
Doing a crown of A and B is going to put the matrix B in a diagonal format of,
basically repeat B by 4 times and put them on diagonals.
So if you look at this example and think of our case, what should we do?
Which matrix is our B? Which matrix is our A in this case?
And yeah, B is going to be this matrix we just constructed, right?
We want to put that as blocks, blocks, blocks, right?
And A is identity.
So let's say my big matrix is equal to,
crown of identity of nx minus 1 and this diagonal block.
So now let's take a look at our big matrix.
So we have a block over here, we have a block over here, and a block over here, right?
Perfect.
So we have completed construction of the blocks.
And now we need to add the upper and lower diagonals.
So what should we do?
The lower diagonal of B1 delta y squared.
The lower diagonal, which one?
That lower diagonal.
Here?
Yes.
It's 1 over delta x squared, right?
It should be 1 over delta, or that one, B1 over delta y squared.
So this lower diagonal is offset by ny minus 1, right?
So if you look at the grid,
it's a range of, right?
It's shifting in a zigzagging fashion.
A shift by ny minus 1 in this case.
So if you go from here, you shift it by ny minus 1.
It's going this, this, and this.
It is the same as shifting the x, shifting the i index by 1.
So this near lower and upper diagonal is shifting y, the index in y, by 1.
This far lower and upper diagonal is shifting the index in x by 1.
So it should be divided by delta x squared.
All right.
So the way to add them,
we can use the same command
as we used to construct the lower and upper diagonals of the
diagonal blocks.
Except for the size of the matrix is going to change.
So now,
it's how many non-zero entries is there in the upper and lower diagonals?
It's now,
it's a lot bigger.
It's now nx minus 2 times ny minus 1.
Right?
So they correspond to blocks of ny minus 1 sizes.
And there are nx minus 2, one of them.
So I'll put this at 1.
And it's also shifted, not by 1,
but by ny minus 1, exactly.
So now, if we look at the matrix again,
it added an upper diagonal entry over here.
Right?
Oh, yes.
I forgot.
So let's repeat this again.
Just to reset.
And I need to divide by dx squared.
That's right.
So I get nines.
And lower diagonal,
I just need to put a minus sign on this.
Right?
So I get the lower diagonal again.
So one interesting thing to visualize the matrix is
a command called spy.
So let's spy on the matrix.
Okay.
So you get a plot of the sparsity pattern of the matrix.
It tells you where in the matrix it's going to be non-zero.
So when the matrix gets too large,
you won't be able to look at this again.
But spy can still do that.
So let's use an example.
nx is equal to 32, let's say.
ny is equal to 32.
And let's...
Where can I look at the command line history?
Now...
I'm going to compute this again and this again.
I'm going to...
construct the diagonal blocks.
And I'm going to use Kronecker product
to construct the big matrix and add lower and upper diagonals.
All right.
So I got a matrix that may be too big to look at.
But if I can spy on the matrix again...
What I get is this.
So...
So you can barely see,
but you can still see this upper and lower diagonal
that is far away.
And you can see, like, the middle line seems to be slightly thicker
than the upper and lower lines
because it's actually three lines.
You can zoom in.
You can zoom in and you can actually see three lines.
And you see the gap here.
Right?
The gap is when the grid transitions from the end
of one of these...
X columns
and switches to the next X column
starting from J equal to one.
All right.
So you don't have a coupling between this and this
on this row of the equation.
So that's...
what this...
gives you.
All right.