So remember, the starting point of a scalar conservation law, discretizing a scalar conservation
law is the what form?
Is the integral form because this is the only form that makes sense.
The only form that doesn't involve d dx of any discontinuous functions.
Right?
I mean, if you remember when we do finite difference, we are using Taylor series to
analyze the accuracy of our discretization.
And in the Taylor series, we, no matter how high order the scheme is, we have a remaining
term that is proportional to delta x to the whatever power times the certain derivative
of this function.
Right?
For example, a second order scheme, the error term would be proportional to delta x squared
times maybe the third order derivative.
So, the third order derivative of the function may be the fourth order derivative of the
function, depending on what is the differential operator.
But the thing is, when you have a discontinuous solution, the third order derivative is what?
Is infinite.
Okay?
The fourth order derivative is infinite.
So the order of accuracy doesn't, Taylor series order of accuracy doesn't make any sense anymore.
So no matter what you do, you get potentially infinite amount of error.
And use the integral form.
Use the integral form to avoid the potential problems with finite difference.
F of u at b minus f of u at a equal to zero.
Okay?
And let us divide the whole equation by b minus f of u at a.
So, we have the integral form.
So we have b minus a.
So, if you divide this, the integral of the solution over a small range by b over a, we
get the average.
The average value of u inside b and a.
So d dt of u bar, okay, over b and a plus f over the left, on the right side of the
domain.
Okay?
So e to the right minus f left equal to zero.
A plus f over the right minus f left equal to zero.
Apply, oh sorry, over b minus a.
So apply this in a domain discretized in small intervals.
Delta x, two delta x, three delta x.
And this is N delta x.
How many, how many of these averages do we have?
So be very careful.
We just go wrong.
We need some more.
No, we don't want any more.
about the distinction between finite volume and finite difference. In finite
difference, depending on boundary conditions, we may have n-1
unknowns, we may have n-plus-1 unknowns, we may have n unknowns if the two sides
have different boundary conditions. For finite volume, we always have n
unknowns, the number of intervals. So let me write this as u-bar-1, so
the first self-average u-bar-2, etc., u-bar this would be n, what I have is
d u-bar-i dt plus b-minus-a would be delta x, right. And this is the flux at the
right side of the interval, i, which I call i-plus-half because it's
writing
between the interval i and i plus 1. Now we use integers to denote the cells, and
the grid points now become like second-class citizens. So we use the half-fractional
numbers to denote them. Like in finite difference, the grid points are first-class citizens. We use
integers to denote them. In finite volume, that's not the case. We reserve the integers to denote
the cells and the boundaries. They are less important. We use fractional indices.
Minus f of i minus half equal to zero. All right, so this is our finite volume scheme,
and this is exact. So there is no approximation yet in this derivation.
Now let's start our approximation.
The approximation needs to be there because the f is evaluated at the grid points.
So this f i plus 1, for example, is equal to f of u at x i plus half, right? x i plus half is
the grid points. And we don't have them in finite volume. We only remember the cell averages.
So we have to do some kind of interpolation. So this is what we have to interpolate.
So there are two types of interpolations. One type is to interpolate the u, the solution,
and apply the flux on top of the interpolated solution.
The other way is to compute the flux directly on the cell averages and then interpolate the flux.
So either way is a perfectly fine finite volume approximation.
For example, I'm just going to give a very elementary example that is we call the central flux scheme.