okay now our next demo is what if we have a function f that is not linear
okay remember if we have a function f that is not not a constant what we have
to do is to integrate this function within every interval right so so let's
give an example of if f is equal to let's say sine of pi x so sine of pi x
within 0 and 1 is going to be a sinusoidal function that goes up and
down and I constructed this such that we also are going to have an analytical
solution right we also going to have an analytical solution that is actually
unique to the problem so we're going to have an analytical solution that is actually
equal to sine of x times a coefficient because the second order derivative of
sine is actually minus pi square of sine right so we also have an analytical
solution and the BJ in this case is going to be split into two parts X X J
minus 1 so this is J to X J of a solution that goes from 0 to 1 which
means that we have a solution that is going to be a sinusoidal function that is
going to be a sinusoidal function that is going to be a sinusoidal function that is
out my X is going to be X minus X J minus 1 over X J minus X J minus 1 so
that's the form of the V J times sine of pi X DX plus X J to X J plus 1 and the
form of the function is going to be X minus X J over X J plus 1 minus X J on
also times sine of pi X DX so let's see how do we construct this function yes
5J oh yeah 5J is this hat functions right these are Phi 1 Phi 2 so each function is one over here
uh it is one at a particular grid point and zero at all other grid points it's piecewise constant
all right so this is
so this is our general equation of Ùn into f of jed and v .
In this particular equation we can even disease a sign coming out of a
illion point gV J into G and let's assume this is
the sign we set the function as a z wheels so we can use this for adding onion dice here
So for example, on the first interval, we can compute we have x1, which is 0, and x2.
So let's use these two grid points.
So let's compute the Gauss quadrature points and weights within that interval.
The way to use this is x and w.
These are x is the location of the Gauss quadrature points, and w are the weights.
And first of all, we give an n, which is the number of quadrature points.
In this case, let's try a quadrature points of 5 points.
And a and b are the intervals, which we give it x1 and x2.
So it gives me the x and the weights.
So x, as you notice, are a set of numbers that lies within x1 and x2.
So the maximum is 0.093, which is close to the right-hand side of the interval, but not quite.
The minimum is 0.046, which is close to 0, but not quite.
And the weights are a little bit larger in the middle than at the two ends.
So it's the spacing. The spacing is more sparse in the middle and more tight at the ends.
Alright.
So this can be used to compute the integral over the first interval.
So let's do this. Let's do x left, w left.
We are going to have a right pretty soon, because in order to compute the first entry of b,
we need to integrate over two intervals.
So we have the left.
So we have the left of both entries, and how do we approximate the integral?
Is the function we need to integrate this particular function at the grid points
times the weight corresponding to the grid point, and just sum over these five points.
So let's compute the number. Let's call it b of left.
Okay.
It's equal to
the grid point x left minus x of 1
divided by x i plus 1,
so in this case x2 minus x1.
This is the form of the basis function.
And times sine of pi times xl.
xl are the Gauss quadrature grid points.
And I multiply this value with the Gauss quadrature weights.
So these are going to give me five numbers.
If I sum over the five numbers,
this is going to give me the value of the function.
But the weights shouldn't be negative,
so I must give it...
Okay, so let me see.
So f of x is defined in a and b.
I simply evaluate it.
So what did I do?
I give it xa is x1 and b is x2.
So I must have...
I see.
Good point.
Okay, so I should have x equal to...
Okay, let's do this again.
Right, okay.
Now I have the original x.
I can do this.
So my weights are now positive.
And my xl is what I...
expect.
So now let's compute b left is equal to the same number.
This is the integral of the function I wanted to integrate in the first interval.
Okay, so I can also have...
my x right and w right being...
the Gauss quadrature points and weights in the second interval.
Okay, so this is my second interval.
And then I can also compute the right side of the quadrature.
Being summation of x right minus x2.
This is actually...
Wait.
It's xr.
I think I made a mistake in here.
What I needed actually is xi minus xi plus 1.
Because this basis function has to be zero at xi plus 1.
Right?
Okay.
And there should be...
There also should be...
Should there be a minus sign?
Yeah, there should be a minus sign here.
So it's actually xi plus 1 minus x.
So this is going to give me a 1 at xj and give me a 0 at xj plus 1.
Right?
So it's a function that goes downwards.
Okay.
So now let's compute this function.
xr should be...
It should have x3 minus x1.
So it's going to be x3 minus xr divided by x3 minus x2 times sine of pi times xr times the wr.
Okay.
So this is going to give me the right side of this b1.
Right?
So I can have a b1.
It's going to be equal to b left plus 1.
So this must be right.
Of course this only computes one entry.
So let's do a loop of computing all these entries.
So let's go for i goes from 1 to n minus 1.
Okay.
And so what I'm going to compute is b left.
b left is going to be...
Oh, sorry.
I need to first compute the question.
So I'm going to compute the quadrature weights.
The quadrature weights on the left is going to be in between i and i plus 1.
Right?
And my x right and w right should be the quadrature points between i plus 1 and i plus 2.
So this gives me the quadrature weights.
And my...
My integral on the left side of the...
The integral on the right side of the grid point should be...
The value of the basis function should be xl minus xi divided by xi plus 1 minus xi.
So this is the linear function that goes from 0 to 1 when x goes from xi to xi plus 1.
Times sine of pi times xl times wl.
So this is correct, I think.
Okay.
And br is going to be equal to the summation of x now i plus 2.
Right?
Because I'm looking at the interval on the right side of this grid point.
And I have xi plus 2 minus xi plus 1.
This is right.
And my bi would be equal to bl plus br.
All right.
Okay.
So now I have the complete b field.
Let's do it again.
u is equal to a inverse times b.
So now I get my u again.
Let's close my previous plot.
And plot this u again.
Hmm.
This time I got something wrong.
Okay.
Got something that is not as good.
So let's plot my analytical solution again.
My u, phi, instead of equal to the quadratic.
We have sine of x, phi times pi divided by pi squared.
Okay.
And let's hold on.
And plot my analytical solution.
Let's see how they match.
Okay.
So I don't really get what I expected.
Can we find a bug in the code I have in the for loop?
Oh, yes.
I changed my x vector.
I need to redo the a matrix.
Yeah.
Thank you.
So let's do this.
My diagonal term is equal to the integral of x.
So I can do this.
Okay, together.
So we have x equals i, plus my diagonal terms and a equals a.
So let's, let's this first, a is equal to a, plus my diagonal terms and a is equal to
a minus, no, I don't have these two times.
Ok.
So that's my new a matrix.
Yeah.
Ok.
Thanks.
So, let's do this again.
And ...
Um.
these and these are still correct this is the correct main diagonal right so we
get a matrix that yeah looks looks like half the properties we expect all right
so u is equal to a backslash B and let's try to plot this time solution
let's plot it as what color let's plot it as a black okay so now the black line
matches the analytical solution a lot better right so let's let's close this
again and so this is numerical solution this is
you
analytical solution sorry let me hold on and plot the numerical solution again so
now my numerical solution matches the analytical solution a lot better so we
have demonstrated how to use finite element to solve the Poisson's equation
with zero boundary conditions both for trivial right-hand side and for a
non-trivial right-hand side all right and Gauss quadrature with five points
seems to be very good already
finally these are the bombs ok here you add any
aggravating