We have used Gauss-Seidel as smoother.
And we have the purpose of the smoother is one is to improve the solution, right?
And another important role of the smoother is to remove the high frequency content of the solution error.
So that the residual can be interpolated to the causal grid.
So this is the single most important role of these few iterations I performed in the beginning of the multigrid cycle.
So for example, if instead of Gauss-Seidel iterations I'm performing here,
if I change them to Jacobi iterations,
what do you think is going to be the effect to the multigrid algorithm?
Let's try that.
Jacobi.
So let me remove all these breakpoints and
I'll also make
this to be Jacobi.
Okay, I'm not going to change the causal grid iteration because it's going to be, no matter using Gauss-Seidel,
it is going to basically give us the exact solution.
Okay.
Now I just changed the pre- and post-smoothing operations from Gauss-Seidel to Jacobi.
And let's see what is the effect.
Let's also make a bunch of zeros and perform one multigrid cycle.
U is equal to multigrid of U and B.
That's IMP.
And show a few.
What do you think we're going to get?
We get something that is a little bit less accurate than what we had before.
Right?
Maybe we just perform one iteration.
Let's do this again.
Doesn't really help.
Right?
So what's happening?
Why is Gauss-Seidel working but Jacobi is not working?
For this, we again have to dive into the eigenvalue and eigenvector analysis of Gauss-Seidel and Jacobi.
So do we remember when we performed many, many Jacobi iterations,
what is the mode that converged the slowest?
What is the solution error after many iterations?
It was the low frequency mode, exactly.
But for Jacobi iteration, it is not only the low frequency mode that converges the slowest.
There are some other modes that also converge very slowly.
What do you think is that mode?
So let's think in 1D.
1D.
So X.
We have grid point over here.
And the matrix.
Let's just write down the discretization.
So U of I minus 1 minus 2 U I plus U I plus 1 divided by delta X square equal to F of I.
And to make the Jacobi iteration, we are assigning this to K.
This is the lower diagonal part.
This is the K plus 1.
The diagonal part.
And the K, the upper diagonal part.
So the Jacobi iteration is moving the K plus 1 part, keeping that on the left-hand side,
and moving the known to the right-hand side.
So we have minus delta X square over 2 F I plus half of U I K.
And the U I K.
U I minus 1 K, U I plus 1 K.
It is very intuitive that if I have a mode that is very, very smooth,
this particular iteration being the average of the two neighboring grid points would converge very slowly.
Right?
So particularly if I write the error equation,
if I define E I K plus 1 to be defined as U I K plus 1 minus U I,
which is the exact solution.
My E I of K plus 1 would be equal to,
this term gets cancelled if I subtract the iteration with what is satisfied by the exact solution.
What I get is E I K plus 1 is equal to the average of E I K plus 1.
So I have the average of E I plus 1 K and E I minus 1 K.
That means if I have a very, very smooth solution,
so let's say this is my,
I have a very smooth solution error.
Excuse me.
So if this is E I K,
in my next iteration, what is going to be my solution error?
What is going to be, let's say, blue is E I K.
K plus 1.
My solution error is going to decay very slowly because my E I K plus 1 on this grid point would be the average of these two.
So I would be drawing a straight line and my E I K plus 1 would be here.
So see how slow it decays.
To figure out what is the blue line at this point,
I would be drawing a straight line between the neighboring grid points.
E I K plus 1 would be here.
I would be drawing a straight line and the E I K plus 1 would be here.
As long as this line still has some curvature,
my E I K is going to decay as K increases as I'm taking these averages.
But you can see the smaller the curvature of the E I K is,
the smoother it is,
in other words, the slower it will decay.
But this is one opposite of the spectrum for Jacobi iteration.
There is another type of solution error that also would decay very slowly.
And that type of error is the extreme opposite of a smooth solution.
It is the most non-smooth solution you can imagine that also decays very slowly.
Why is that?
Let's try it.
Let's try to imagine I have a solution x.
And this is solution error.
If I have a solution error that is as non-smooth as you can imagine,
that is one positive, one negative, one positive, one negative,
another positive, another negative, another positive, another negative, like that.
A grid by grid oscillation.
So let's see.
If this is E I K,
and I use another color to denote E I K plus 1,
what is going to be E I K plus 1 for the second grid point?
It's going to be the average between these two, right?
So I would get here.
E I K plus 1 for this grid point would be here, right?
So I would get an error that is going to be,
like this, like that.
Right?
So I would get a grid by grid oscillation again on the opposite direction.
Great.
So this is actually not better.
The convergence rate is actually not better
than if I just have one smooth solution.
The most non-smooth solution possible you can find
have a very similar convergence rate
to the most smooth solution,
except for every iteration,
the solution area flips its sign.
All right.
Okay.
That can also be seen mathematically
through,
through the same analysis as we did before.
And mathematically,
the eigenvalues
of Jacobi iteration matrix,
they are cosine
of
J
pi
divided by N,
right?
Where N is the number of intervals
and J is the mode.
Last time we focused on the mode
that corresponds to J equal to 1.
That corresponds to the most smooth solution.
But equally difficult to converge is
J equal to N minus 1.
Why is that?
This is because
when J is equal to 1,
cosine of pi over N is very close to 1
when N is large.
But when J is equal to N minus 1,
cosine of J pi over N is very close to what?
Minus 1.
That's right.
So I have an eigenvalue that is close to 1
that contributes to the slow convergence
of the non-smooth part.
I also have an eigenvalue very, very close to minus 1.
And it's minus 1 that contributes
the flipping of this solution error.
I have an eigenvalue close to minus 1
that contributes the slow convergence
of the most non-smooth part.
The reason we don't see it as much
in the solution error
when we perform Jacobi iterations
is because usually
in the initial guess,
usually in the solution error
of the initial guess,
the most high-frequency content
is usually smaller
than the lowest frequency contents.
So although the high-frequency content
converges as low as the low-frequency content,
because initially it is small,
finally it also is a lot smaller
than the low-frequency content.
But in multi-grid,
that actually becomes very important
because as we perform iterations
on the coarse grid,
we know we are reducing
the smooth portion of the solution error
very, very fast.
So the ability of the smoother
of the five iterations,
we did in the beginning
and then at the end of the multi-grid,
to reduce the non-smooth portion
of the solution error
becomes very, very important.
And not only it is important
in reducing the most non-smooth
part of the solution,
because we are applying
the same iterations
on the successively coarser grids.
And on the coarser grids,
the most non-smooth portion
of the solution is actually
contains everything, right?
So no matter what frequency,
how smooth or non-smooth it is,
at a certain grid,
it can be close to the most non-smooth
part of the solution.
So if your iteration
is like the Jacobi iteration,
not very good at reducing
some non-smooth features
of the solution,
then it is not a good smoother.
Okay, it is not,
a good thing to use in multi-grid.