Alright, last lecture we discussed how to estimate the error in finite element solutions.
How much error it was caused by limiting the space of solution from the infinite dimensional space
in the weak form of the differential equation to a finite dimensional space,
which we can represent as a linear combination of a few basis functions
and derive a set of algebraic equations for the linear combination coefficients.
So the error estimate we have looked at are mostly a priori error estimates
because the precise form of the error is going to depend on the particular solution,
not the approximate solution.
So finally, in the last lecture, we derived several facts.
One is that in the energy norm, the finite element solution was the optimal
in how much error it has.
And in both H1 and L2 norm, the finite element solution is optimal up to a certain factor,
up to a certain finite factor that doesn't depend on the grid size.
That enables us to bound the finite element solution error
by one particular type of approximation, which is piecewise linear interpolant.
And the precise error of the piecewise linear interpolant actually then depends on the curvature,
which is the second order derivative of the actual solution, not the finite element solution.
Therefore, that is a priori error estimate.
The form of the error depends on the actual solution.
And this lecture, we will talk about a posteriori error estimate,
which we are going to derive a form of an error estimate
that actually depends on not the real continuous solution, but the discrete solution.
That is some error estimate we can actually compute.
Right?
So in order to introduce that kind of a posteriori error estimate,
the posteriori estimate cannot be actually applied to the entire solution.
It can only be applied to the entire solution.
Right?
By instance, we first need a form of a posteriori error.
By instance, we first need a form of an error estimate.
Right?
So, for instance, we used this producer.
Right.
Right?
There is a
right?
Right?
where we get our final admin solution.
What we're interested in is not usually the entire solution.
We are interested in a particular final number of quantities
computed from the solution.
And here I'm going to write this as L0 of U.
What are some examples of this L of U?
In aerodynamics problems, this may be the lift or drag of an airplane.
In heat transfer problems, if I'm interested in solving for a temperature field
that concerns the damage due to heat to some material,
I may be interested in the maximum temperature in a certain material.
So these are quantities I'm interested in.
This is the quantities that...
tells me why am I solving this PDE.
Okay, so that is L0 of U that, let's say, for example,
give me just one single number.
L0 itself is a linear function.
So it is a linear...
functional...
of the solution.
Alright.
So the error estimate...
should approximate the difference between L0 operated on the finite element solution
minus the same functional operated on the real solution.
So here I'm trying to estimate
if I spent a million times more computation effort
getting a much better approximation,
how much difference does that make to my...
quantity of interest?
If the difference is minor, is more compared to, let's say, other uncertainties from the setup of the problem,
let's say the material properties, etc.,
then I shouldn't spend this additional effort solving the PDE to much more accuracy.
But if the error turns out to be large,
and it's large compared to other sources of uncertainty,
and I have the computational resources, then I should spend...
the computational time refining the grid and getting a more accurate solution.
Right.
So this is what we are trying to approximate.
And the linearity of the output functional allows me to...
say this is actually equal to L0 operated on...
U-H minus U.
Right.
So that's simply linearity.
So how do I estimate that quantity?
To estimate...
that quantity, I'm going to introduce another equation.
I'm going to introduce what's called the adjoint equation.
Remember, what are the place...
what is the place that a linear functional appeared before?
It's the right-hand side of a weak form.
Right.
So the trick in this a posteriori area estimate...
is to introduce or invent another weak form...
that uses this L0, which is a different linear functional...
from the L in the differential equation.
So I'm going to introduce another equation that uses this L0...
as the right-hand side of the weak form.
Particularly, I'm going to introduce an adjoint equation that is A star,
which is different from this A also.
I'm going to tell you what A star has to be a little bit later.
So let me call this U hat being the solution of this different differential equation.
And V has to equal to L0 of V.
For all possible Vs, remember this L0 has to be operated on the difference between UH and U.
So this V in this differential equation should belong to the space of XU.
Right.
That's the space where U has to belong to.
So the test space of this adjoint equation is the primal space,
is the space of, is the solution space,
the also called trial space of the original differential equation.
Okay.
And it turns out that my U hat, the solution...
whose solution U hat should be in...
the XV should be in the space of the test functions in the original differential equation.
Okay.
So how is this going to be helpful?
Let's try to use the manually constructed differential equation
to figure out how do I further derive this.
So if I have this, then my...
I know that for all V in this XU, this weak form is equal.
So that allows me to substitute this particular UH minus U into V.
This is going to give me A star of U hat and UH minus U.
Right.
Okay.
Now here comes to what this A star has to be.
So the reason it's called the adjoint equation is that A star and the A in the original equation,
they are adjoint operators.
So A star and A are so-called adjoint.
In that the definition of adjoint is that A of U, V is exactly equal to A star of V and U.
For...
All pairs of U and V.
So this is U, this is V.
If these As are matrices, what does adjoint mean?
They're just transpose.
Exactly.
So A star in finite dimensional sense would be just transpose of A.
Okay.
So now we know that A star of U hat and UH minus U
is equal to...
A of UH minus U and U hat.
Right.
So here we use the original differential equation.
Before that we are going to expand it using the bilinearity of A.
So first of all, U hat is a member of XV.
So by the original differential equation, by this original differential equation, if V...
If I substitute V by U hat, what I get is this is equal to L of what?
U hat.
Right?
Okay.
So therefore, this whole thing is equal to A of UH, U hat minus L of U hat.
Or, so let's look at what is the consequence of this equality we derived.
The error in the output linear functional, okay, is equal to the left-hand side minus
right-hand side.
If you look at the original equation, okay, this is the original equation.
Left-hand side is A of UV, right-hand side is L of V.
Here, this is A of UH and U hat.
This is the right-hand side L of U hat.
So this is the residual of the original differential equation.
When I substitute the solution U by the finite dimension or finite elements,
solution UH, and I substitute the V, the test function, by this solution of the adjoint
equation, U hat.
So, remember, this is just the A of UV minus L of V.
So this is A of UH of this.
For V is particularly equal to L of V.
And this is particularly equal to U hat.
So why is this a posteriori error estimate?
Because this formula involves UH, not U.
Right?
And this formula is up to now exact.
We make no approximation whatsoever.
The only approximation we are going to make is to V, because here, V is still the exact
solution.
The exact solution of the adjoint equation.
Right?
So, we are going to solve V using numerical method and substitute that V into this error
formula.
And we get an error estimate.
I mean, it's an estimate because I'm solving a numerical approximation for V, not the exact
V.
If I have the exact V in some way, then I have an exact formula for the error.