So now this lecture will assume you have made the wise choice of a stable scheme.
Then the error, the truncation error, now actually matters.
And most times when you use a code that somebody else wrote,
hopefully they are wise enough to choose a stable scheme, so you get reasonable numbers.
And then it's up to you, to the user of the code, to figure out is the solution accurate enough,
or what kind of error is in the solution.
And that's something we'll talk about in the beginning of this lecture today.
So the concept we are going to discuss today is called modified equations.
It is based on the fact that when you,
you discretize a differential equation using a numerical scheme.
The numerical scheme turns out to be, maybe it is a fairly good approximation
to the differential equation you want to solve.
But most of the time, it is actually an even more accurate discretization
of some differential equation that maybe you didn't want to solve.
And that equation, the scheme is actually,
actually approximating even better is called the modified equation.
For example, let's start with the pretty obvious example.
Okay, let's start with the differential equation du dt plus a constant capital U.
So capital U is a constant,
small u is a function, a solution of the PDE equal to zero.
And we all, up to now, we should all know what the solution to this equation looks like.
Right? What does the solution to this equation look like?
So let's say U, let's just say U is greater than zero.
What does the solution look like?
It's a translation towards which direction?
To the right, exactly.
Okay, so it's a pure translation to the right.
The solution should maintain its original shape.
So let's say if I have a periodic domain, the solution should maintain its shape forever.
Forever, right?
But in practice, let us discretize this differential equation using
one of the more stable schemes we discussed in the last lecture.
A scheme that would even be stable using forward Euler.
What is that scheme we ended up deriving?
du dt plus U times what?
Backward.
Backward difference, or upwinding, right?
In this case, the solution adverts towards the right.
The upwinding direction is towards where the wind comes from.
That's towards the left.
So towards the left, that involves U and U .
Right? U is towards the left.
So minus divided by delta x, you do Taylor series analysis.
That is the appropriate discretization.
That is first order accurate.
Okay.
So that is equal to zero.
And if you did that in your class, that would be great.
But if you didn't, let's...
If you did it in your project, that's great.
If you didn't, let's code up a scheme like that and figure out...
And let's take a look at the solution to see how the discretization modifies the behavior
of the equation.
So let's say du dt, upwind.
Okay.
This is T and U.
So we are...
Let's still use od45 to integrate this equation to make sure the time derivative doesn't really...
So, so od45 has a lot more accurate time derivative than the spatial discretization we are using.
Right?
So, so let's use od45 to try to remove a lot of the time discretization error and focus
on spatial discretization.
Okay.
So u is periodic, and let's assume u is in the domain of 0 to 2 pi.
The first u is at grid point 0.
The last u is at grid point 2 pi minus delta x.
Because the solution at 2 pi is actually exactly equal to the solution at 0,
so we don't have to remember that.
But so n is equal to the length of u, and dx is equal to 2 pi divided by n.
So n grid points, in this case, periodic domain, n grid points, n intervals.
Because we didn't store the solution at the very end.
So du dx is equal to two things.
Because we are looking at towards the left,
and the very first grid point when we are looking towards the left
is actually the very last grid point.
So the first grid point is u n minus u 1 divided by delta x.
So that's the very first grid point.
And the rest, I can write it as u of 2 to n minus u of 1.
So u n minus u 1 divided by delta x.
So this is a kind of, we call a vectorized way of coding
that works very well in MATLAB or Python or any of the interpreted language.
If you're coding Julia, you don't have to do that.
It's still fast.
But if you have MATLAB or Python,
vectorizing a calculation like this,
instead of going over a function,
instead of going over a for loop,
is going to be a lot faster than going over the for loop.
So this is basically looping for i goes from 2 to n.
This is u i.
This is u i minus 1.
Right?
Yes?
Yes.
The first line should be u 1 minus u n.
Thank you.
All right.
So yeah, u i minus u i minus 1.
Yeah, u i minus 1 is actually u n in this case.
Okay.
So my du dt is then equal to,
according to this formula,
minus big U times,
let's put,
let's, for example, say,
okay, u is equal to 1.
Just to,
just to serve as an example,
minus u times du dx.
All right.
So that is our function.
And let's use od 45 to integrate that.
And so, for example, let's say x is equal to 1 to,
so that's 0 to 99.
For example, let's use 100 points divided by 100.
So that is our x.
We should multiply by 2 pi.
Right?
So, so that is our x.
And the way we start,
what kind of function do we want to start?
Let's just start with,
with a bump, right?
Let's start with a bump and see how the bump evolves.
And u 0 is,
I mean, a good way to,
an easy way to make a bump
is to take a sine function.
So sine of,
sine of x over 2.
So x goes from 0 to pi.
So, so x, x goes from 0 to 2 pi.
So x over 2 goes from 0 to pi.
So a sine bump.
Let's take it to the 16th power.
Okay.
So if you plot x and u 0, you see like a bump.
That's also a periodic function.
All right.
Okay.
So now we have our initial condition.
Let's say t and u is equal to,
oh, by the way, let me ask you,
if I want the analytic solution to advect over the entire domain
and come back to exactly the same location
so that the analytical solution is going to look like
the same as this one,
how much time should I integrate the solution for?
The length of the domain over u, right?
So length of the domain, u is like,
length per time.
So u is 1.
The length of the domain is 2 pi.
So I want to integrate by 2 pi.
Okay.
So tu is equal to od 45 of at dudt upwind.
What's the second parameter?
Is it time?
0 to pi.
And my u 0.
So that is da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da.
I'm not consistent.
I think again, I have this.
I should be doing this instead of that.
Okay.
So I think it's probably because u is a vertically oriented factor.
So let's do that again.
Now we have a u.
So u, od 45,
obviously determined that this interval is too big as a timestamp.
So it automatically divided this interval from 0 to 2.
It evened out the interval.
And算 out that kilogram.
And the less the less we keep on doing attempts till the end
when it actually comes to the end,
we get this dash output
of which u, 0, and Entscheidung function f,
so f k's objective being equal to z.
And the third case is we to knowing,
in this case,
What do you call x-axis sum into a ?
That's the one.
That's the first case.
But then again,
since the YouTubers just go through the steps,
what else does this have?
That's our numerical solution after this thing
at x over one period.
Analytical solution again should be exactly the same
as the blue one.
Numerical solution, the red one.
Can somebody tell me like, what's,
what do you, can you describe,
qualitatively describe the difference
between the analytical solution which is blue
and numerical solution which is red?
It diffused out.
It's almost as if we are solving not the advection equation
but an advection, diffusion equation, exactly.