So let's draw this case. Even if I draw a very jaggy case, the solution decays.
And you can see different components decay at different rates.
The very jaggy components decay very, very fast.
And the relatively smooth components decay very slowly.
And at this point, it looks almost like a constant plus a small amplitude sinusoidal wave.
A sinusoidal wave is k equal to 1 and minus 1, right?
So at this point, and the k equal to 1 and minus 1,
they decay this.
This is among the slowest decaying components of the Fourier series.
And even that slowly decays at the end, we're going to see it's going to be a constant in space.
So that is the behavior of the heat equation in periodic domains.
All right.
Any questions?
Pardon?
Can I have kappa to be positive?
Can I have kappa to be, you mean negative?
So here, yeah, so here the kappa is positive.
If you have kappa to be negative, what happens?
Instead of exponential decay, you have exponential growth, right?
That means if you have a sign error in your code,
that makes kappa somehow negative, what are you going to have?
You're going to have infinity pretty soon, okay?
Because for the larger case, the exponential growth now is going to be very, very fast.
Actually, the finer the mesh is, which means the larger k can be containing your solution,
the faster you are going to grow to infinity if you have a negative k.
So that can be, that is the result if you have a negative k, okay?
Exponential growth is very fast.
In a computer, within a few iterations, you are going to see numbers like 10 to the 100,
10 to the 200, and the floating points can only go up to 10 to the,
double precision floating points can go to 10 to the 300.
And beyond that, you're going to get infinity, okay?
Okay.
That's what you're going to see in computer code.
And if you do some operations with infinities, you're going to get not a number.
So in your code, I'm sure at some point you are going to see infinities and not a numbers.
That can be a cause of exponential growth,
very fast exponential growth in your computer code.
All right.
Any other questions?
Okay.