So first of all, we need to define the so-called Sobolev space.
So the Sobolev space is an extension of the L2 space.
And if you did functional analysis, you know like L2 space is all functions whose square is integrable.
So it's all the functions where the integration between...
So usually you define an interval, right, in between A and B.
So let's say actually omega because this actually extends to multiple dimensions.
So integration over omega of f squared dx is bounded, so less than infinity.
So this is a class of functions that defines a space because...
defines a linear space because if f and g...
So first of all, if f is in L2 space, if you scale it by a finite number,
the scaled function is also going to be in the same space
because the integral of a square is just going to be also scaled by a constant.
Also, if you have f and g within both within L2,
then integration of f plus g squared dx,
we have f squared plus 2fg plus g squared dx.
Okay.
And using...
Using Cauchy-Schwarz inequality,
the integration of fg dx is less or equal to...
Well, half of integration of f squared plus g squared, right, dx.
And therefore, this...
If the integration of f squared is finite,
integration of g squared is finite,
then the integration of this and this and this are all finite.
Therefore, this is going to be...
Less than...
This is going to be less than infinity if f and g both are square integrable.
So this is basically a proof that shows that the L2 space is a linear space.
Satisfying the criterion.
So if f is in...
So let's say if f and g both in L2 space,
then af plus bg is also in the same space.
Because scaling doesn't change...
I mean, scaling a member in the space cannot go out of the...
Cannot cause the member to go out of the space.
And also linear combination cannot...
Summation cannot force the member to go out of the space.
Right?
So the Sobolev space is an extension of this.
So the Sobolev space, we're only going to be talking about h1 here.
And the extension to h2, etc., we can see later,
is that all the functions f, such that the integral...
I'm also going to define omega here.
The integral of not only f, but also the derivative of f.
So let me just call it gradient of f.
It's fine.
It's finite.
In one dimension, this gradient is just the df dx.
So this is basically because both f squared and the gradient f squared,
they are positive.
The sum of these is less than infinity,
which basically means that the f is square integrable,
and the derivative of f is also square integrable.
Right?
So this is the equivalent to f...
Well, f integrable is...
It's the same as saying f is in L2.
And the gradient of f is also in L2.
So is it a bigger space than L2 or a smaller space than L2?
It's smaller because some functions in h1 doesn't belong to L2.
Right?
All functions in L2...
Sorry, the opposite.
All functions in h1 belongs to L2,
and some functions in L2 doesn't belong to h1.
Somebody think of an example of a function in L2 doesn't belong to h1?
A function that is in L2, but the gradient is not in L2.
Something on the vertical line?
Like, so you have a...
Okay.
Something that has a vertical line.
So a function like that.
Right?
So that's a very good example.
So it's a...
We have a function that is discontinuous.
Right?
So a function that is discontinuous belongs to L2,
but doesn't belong to h1.
Right?
That's a good point.
So discontinuous...
function...
can belong to L2, but not h1.
Another example is f equal to square root of x
for x in 0 and 1.
Of course, the function is square integrable.
Square is just x.
Right?
But the derivative is 1 over square root of x.
I mean, half of 1 over square root of x.
Square root, you get 1 over x,
and it's not integrable within 0 and 1.
I mean, the derivative is infinite at 0.
All right.
Okay.
So both of these are in L2, but not h1.
And we can define all other h's,
like h2 is f's,
whose square, the function itself,
and...
and also, like, the squares...
the second order derivative also has to be finite.
So now it's an even smaller space.
Right?
So as you increase this index,
more and more derivatives are required to be
not only exist, but also square integrable.
So you get more...
smaller and smaller space.
And this is...
the...
and also it's...
it's more than just differentiable, right?
Because square root of x, for example,
it's actually c infinity.
It's...
it's...
it's going to be differentiable always.
But, like, it's...
it doesn't even belong to h1.
So...
so...
so functions that are not just differentiable,
but its derivative are...
cannot go to infinity too fast at the boundaries.
Okay.