So another example let's give is Jacobi iteration in two dimensions.
So let's try a two-dimensional matrix and do another exercise to figure out
what the iteration would look like. So the two-dimensional Poisson's equation
would look like U plus U plus U plus U
plus U minus in this case we have 4 times U
because we have derivative in both i and j directions and the delta
squared.
So delta here, let's say, let's put delta x.
So the assumption here is delta x equal to delta y, right?
Otherwise, we have different coefficients.
This is equal to Fij.
Okay.
And here, can we identify what are the lower diagonal parts and what are the upper diagonal parts?
It depends on how I order the vector.
Right.
But in Jacobi iterations, it actually doesn't matter which part is lower diagonal, which part is upper diagonal.
Why?
Because they are all moved towards the right-hand side.
And only what is left on the left-hand side?
The diagonal part.
Right.
So let's just pick out the diagonal part.
This one is diagonal part.
And everything else goes towards...
Towards the right-hand side.
So what we have is Uij.
And let's also divide both sides by 4, like minus 4 over delta x.
This would be equal to minus delta x squared over 4 times Fij.
And then the rest is plus Ui plus 1j plus Ui minus 1j.
Uij plus 1j plus Uij minus 1.
Uij plus 1.
The whole thing divided by 4.
Right.
So now look at the similarity.
So previously we have this form and now we have this form.
It seems like my Uij for the next iteration, k plus 1,
is some contribution from the...
Right-hand side of the matrix plus some kind of average.
Right.
In previously just divided by 2, now divided by 4.
An average of the 4 nearby entries.
So this is, in some sense, characteristic of the Poisson's equation.
Because the Poisson's equation, you get a smooth solution.
The solution is a slight contribution from the...
Right-hand side, which is on the order of delta x squared,
plus an average of the nearby solutions.
This is what gives a smooth solution that has a curvature equal to what you want it to be.
Alright.
So going back to MATLAB and let's make it a little bit cleaner by giving a script.
jacobi Poisson.
2D.
Okay.
So to start, we are going to...
Actually, let's also use this opportunity to look at an interesting phenomenon,
like how the error reduces in Poisson's equation, in jacobi iteration.
So let's use a picture over here.
So the picture is a little bit of...
There is an interesting story about this.
If you look at this...
If I want to open it outside MATLAB...
So this is the picture we want to use as the solution to our Poisson's equation.
It's kind of a standard test case picture in image processing.
So let's just use this one.
So what we have is an error using your import.
No.
We want to do import wizard.
Ah...
This is 128 by 128.
Uint8.
So let's create variable matching preview.
Finish.
So we just loaded the matrix into memory.
The matrix is called the LNBW.
So let's say uexact.
We want to construct a Poisson's equation whose exact solution is what we just loaded.
So it's a matrix.
So it's a matrix 128 by 128 by 3.
But we don't want the color.
So we'll just take the first entry.
Okay.
So if I run it...
And let's...
I am sure it is visualizing uexact.
So that's our variable now.
Okay. So we are good.
So with that uexact, and let's assume a zero boundary condition, let's construct a right-hand side.
That is going to give us this solution.
Right?
This is a method of manufactured solution that is used also in PDs when you try to validate your solver, look for convergence.
So you manufacture a solution and construct the right-hand side so that the solution you have is the solution you expect to get.
So my b would be equal to zeros.
So the shape...
Well, I would just say 128.
That's something we know.
And okay.
So I think I also want to make uexact to be float of uexact.
Otherwise, my uexact is going to be integers.
So let's run this.
So my uexact...
Okay. I think I need to be doing double.
Okay. So now that works.
My uexact is going to be containing now...
They are still integers, but the type is now double.
Okay.
So my b is equal to that.
And let's put my delta x to be 1 over 128 plus 1.
So that will be my grid spacing.
So what I then have is my b...
Okay. For i goes 1 to 128.
For j goes 1 to 128.
My bij is going to be...
Okay. So let's here make a trick.
So let's here make a u expanded.
Also, which is a u including the boundaries.
It will be zeros, 1, 30.
So I'm adding...
I'm padding some zeros on all the boundaries.
So that makes my...
So that I avoid a bunch of if statements in computing b.
And u expanded would be 2 to n minus 1.
2 to n minus 1 would be assigned to uexact.
All right.
So that's a proper way of putting the boundary conditions.
So b of i, j would be equal to u expanded i, j plus 1.
So all the indices are going to be shifted by a little bit.
So okay.
So if we don't want to be shifted, we can make b equal to zeros, 1, 30.
And then our i is going to be going...
i and j are both...
Both are going to...
Going from 2 to 129.
Right.
So we are iterating over the interior grids.
So aij is going to be u expanded i plus 1, j plus dot, dot, dot.
u expanded i minus 1, j.
Expanded i and j plus 1.
Copy and paste.
j minus 1.
Lastly, we want to minus 4 times u of i, j.
i, j.
The whole thing should be divided by delta x squared.
Right.
Okay.
So that way we compute the b that is required to make u exact the solution.
So now let's run it.
It does give us what we want.
So if i am show the b, that will be something we don't understand.
But it is the right-hand side that is supposed to give us the exact solution.
Okay.
So let's apply...
So now let's apply the Jacobi iteration method to solve for b.
Okay.
So initially let's make u that is equal to zeros, 130, 130.
So it's okay to include also the boundary conditions because we know it is what it is.
So let's start with the u that has the correct boundary condition.
So we have the u that is equal to 0.
And we have the u that is equal to 0.
And we have the u that has the correct boundary conditions.
Okay.
And for k, let's do...
Previously we had a thousand iterations.
So let's do a thousand iterations.
So a thousand iterations.
For each iteration, we are going to follow our formula.
So u of k plus 1 would be equal to minus delta x squared divided by 4 times my right-hand side,
which we called b instead of f.
Right?
Okay.
And then we are going to apply this, which we can copy what we had in this iteration, paste it.
We want to indent it correctly.
Then instead of this iteration, I'm going to say u k plus 1 ij is equal to...
is equal to itself plus...
this would be u...
divided by 4.
And I'll get rid of the expanded.
The solution u is also expanded.
But like we called it, the expanded solution.
So this is our previous iteration u.
Right?
So I think we are following the formula we had before.
Is it this, this, this, this?
Right?
I think we are correct.
So let's run this to see what we get.
We have...
Did we run this before?
So we get a u and u k plus 1.
Okay.
So we see it's an array of 130 by 130.
The boundaries are zeros.
Because we never changed them.
And the interior has a bunch of numbers.
So let's look at what u is.
Uh-oh.
So looks black.
So what does that mean?
Uh...
Get a bunch of 40.
So this doesn't seem right.
Okay.
So let's look at what we get wrong over here.
You get to assign u to be u k plus 1.
Oh, yes.
I forgot to assign u equal to u k plus 1.
Thanks.
So practically, we did a thousand.
But like we only did one iteration.
Because we never changed u to be the next iteration.
So let's first try it with 100 iterations to see what we get.
Okay.
So that's done.
So we are looking at a continuous array of numbers.
That seems to be a lot better.
So I am sure of u.
Okay.
It does give us something that looks like the original picture.
But I think the coloring was wrong because these numbers are not properly scaled.
So I am sure it's very sensitive to the type of the numbers.
Okay.
So let's look at the type of the array.
So if the type is integers, it assumes I have 0 to 225.
So like the proper color.
If the array is floating points, I think I need to scale them to 0 to 1.
So what I should be doing is I am sure u divided by 255.
That should be the proper scaling.
Okay.
So now we are looking at something that resembles the original solution.