if you do Fourier series analysis to a fourth order derivative right you are
taking ik to the fourth power what is that like
so the first order derivative to Fourier series analysis you get a purely imaginary eigenvalue
that that means oscillations preserving the magnitude right second order derivative you
get minus k square that means decay
third order derivative you get still purely imaginary but you have k cubed so it advects
it different frequencies oscillates more differently and in in terms of advection that means different
frequencies are advected at different speeds
fourth order derivative you get k to the fourth and usually the sign unless you have an unstable
scheme the sign over that k to the fourth
the
the error term should have a negative sign otherwise you should have you're going to
get unstable scheme alright if you have a stable
scheme you should have minus k to the fourth as you eigenvalue
what is that what does that dissipation that's right and it dissipates your higher
frequency even faster than than k square okay but the good thing is that term is you should
scales with Delta X cubed. So with enough grid you only see the effect of that
dissipation on very high weight numbers. That's why it's more accurate.
Yes?
If we try upwinding on this unit instead of trying it on the bump, would we have dissipation
for higher terms which are at the corners of that shape?
Are you asking if I use the first order upwinding on this one, what do I get? Let's try it.
Okay.
Let's do K because it looks more obvious. That. So the height, yeah, basically dissipates
things away. All right. Yes?
But all those terms, they're still going to be the third order and also in this
scheme as well.
It's just far less pronounced.
Yeah.
The middle one is againол
I'm going to measure something else, and then
you can hedge in some ways depending on you're...
Okay.
So let's...
Yeah, see what I'm trying to do here, which is the fifth-placeかった-type fraternal
Disseduction.
It's fine, affecting the rest of the paid.
when you have higher wave numbers.
So you almost don't see that in the black solution.
So if you really, really zoom in,
the black solution is not going to be symmetric.
All right, it has slight asymmetry,
but it's very hard to spot.
If you have an analytical solution
of a black-trim dissipation equation,
the black wave should be completely symmetric.
All right, any other questions?
Are there formulations that avoid all of these errors?
It'll be ideal if you can find the scheme
that avoids any kind of errors.
But like, unless for very simple equations,
there is going to be numerical errors.
And the dissipation and dispersion error
is just a way we classify different types of errors.
So dissipation error,
both acts a lot stronger on higher wave numbers.
It's just dissipation error,
but the error artificially damps down,
removes these higher wave number components.
And dispersion error,
it doesn't remove them,
but put them in the wrong place.
So that's kind of, in general,
how we classify the effect of these numerical errors.
Yes?
If you switch back to the analytic derivation,
I had a question about what happened
to one of the terms.
Yes?
Can you scroll up slightly,
going from...
Oh, okay.
Sorry, I misread the notes.
Thank you.
Okay.
Any other questions?
No?
All right.