So that promotes the fact that like the coarse grid iterations are almost free
in 3D, promotes the use of this so-called W cycle. Okay, in 1D it doesn't, it makes
more sense to perform the V cycle as we did before. So this looks like a V. The
W cycle, it looks pretty complicated because on every, so basically it
replicates this by effect of two and then on every V it replicates this by
effect of two, right? So that looks like, that's what makes it looks like a W.
But if you think of in the code, this is very easy to do. If I want to perform a
W cycle, what do I do?
The only thing I do is I just, I just do this.
The only thing I do is I just do this. The only thing I do is I just do this.
The only thing I need to do is that. Okay, so that would be a W cycle. I'm performing two
multi-grid iterations when I'm going to a coarser grid, right? So this is at the
finest grid, I'm going to the coarser level and this is one call to this
multi-grid. This is my second call.
And it is also customary to, so yeah, so this is, so what I was doing is this S is
performed twice, one pre-smoothing, one post-smoothing in the coarse grid. But like, it doesn't make much difference.
So this would be one call, the second call to the second finest grid. And when I mean
multi-grid call of the second finest grid, I'm also making one call and two call.
To the third finest grid. And so is here.
So this is a hierarchical, almost like a fractal structure I'm calling here.
And in the code, this is what I would be doing if I want to use a W cycle multi-grid.
If you use W cycle multi-grid, well, just to do the same thing here, the result wouldn't
expect to be a lot more different from just the V cycle. It's probably a little bit better.
But remember, the coarser grid solution is almost free, right?
And in 1D, let's take a look at the cost analysis of the W cycle.
So in 1D, it doesn't make that much sense to do the W cycle multi-grid as I just did
before.
Because the cost of the cost of n grid point, if I keep doing this, would be proportional
to n plus two times the cost.
So this is the iterations I perform on this grid.
Two times the cost of the coarser grid.
Right?
Okay.
And if the cost of this, if I perform that iteratively, that'll be two times n over
two plus two times the cost of n over four.
Right?
Oh, I shouldn't be...
Right.
So, okay.
If I keep doing this, this will be n plus n plus n plus et cetera.
So the...
Okay.
So the cost is going to be proportional to the number of levels.
However many levels you have in the multi-grid, the cost is going to be proportional to the
number of levels instead of bounded by a factor of two.
But starting from 2D, this makes a lot more sense.
Because in 2D, the cost of n total grid points is equal to n plus two times the cost of n
over four.
Okay?
Right?
So, if I do this iteratively, I'm going to get n plus n plus n plus n plus n plus n plus
n plus n plus n plus n plus n plus n plus n plus n plus n plus n plus n plus n plus n plus n
n over four plus two times the cost of n over sixteen.
And if you expand this, it'll be n plus half n plus a fourth n, et cetera.
So it's the same as our one-dimensional V-cycle cost.
Okay?
Okay.
This is less or equal to, I mean, strictly less than 2n.
Right?
So, doing a multi-grid cycle in 2D is you're going to get a cost that is bounded by twice
the cost of the fine-grid operation.
And in 3D, it makes a lot of sense to do the multi-grid because the cost of n is going
to be n plus two times n.
So, if you do the math, it'll be the same series as the two-dimensional V-cycle.
This is going to be strictly less than 4 over 3 times n.
Right?
So, even doing the multi-grid cycle, you're going to get a cost that is going to be less
than 4 over 3 times n.
Okay?
Okay.
even cheaper. You can imagine. Yes, this is the reason they put gamma here. I copied
this from another lecture notes is because they basically have a loop
here. So for gamma goes from 1 to 2, you do that. Right, so that's the
gamma you would be having in the plot. So you are iterating here and this is
what the gamma shows. Alright, so it's a yeah. Any other questions? And you can do
a super W cycle if you make gamma goes from 1 to 3, for example. I don't see
anybody doing that in fact, but like can probably do that.
Okay, but I do see a lot of people doing this. So this is what people call a full
multigrid. It is motivated by the fact that an initial guess is actually
pretty important for the convergence of many problems. And for linear problems,
it's relatively easy to do.
It's not that difficult to just use a zero initial guess and especially for
nonlinear problems, it's very important to have a good initial guess. So what
this does is that instead of starting from the finest grid, you
start from the closest grid. And on the closest grid, you don't start solving the
error equation because you don't have the residual from the fine grid. You
start by solving the equation, the partial differential equation itself on
the closest grid. And then you perform an interpolation. They call prolongation, so
restriction and prolongation is the technical terminology they use in
multigrid, representing these two interpolations. So prolongation is
interpolating from cost, interpolating the solution from cost to fine grid.
Restriction is interpolating the residual from fine to cost grid. Right, this is
always what you'll be doing. So in the
prolongation, interpolate the solution from the cost to fine grid. And that solution is
used as an initial guess for the finer grid. So this is then performing one V
cycle on the second closest grid. And that solution is going to be used as an
initial guess. The interpolated solution is then used as the initial guess for the
third closest grid. And then performing one iteration on the closest grid, you
would get initial guess for the finest grid. Also, you don't have to do exactly
one V cycle before you jump to the final grid. So this is a customary of what
people have been using for full multigrid. And you start solving, for
example, a 13 by 7 problem performing one, two, three, four, five multigrid cycles,
as an initial guess for the final grid. So you perform a few iterations, a few
multigrid cycles on the second closest grid as an initial condition for the next
final grid. So here, every point is one multigrid cycle. And basically because,
especially for 3D problems, these closest grid iterations are
almost free for you.
Right? So it's a, you can converge these closest grid solutions to pretty small residual
and use that as an initial guess for the final grid. Yes?
Why does the residual norm go back up?
Why does the residual norm goes back up as you start a final grid solution? What do you
think? Any people?
Yeah.
Take a guess. Huh? Interpolation, exactly. Because at here, this is the, this residual
is different from this residual. This residual is the residual of a different equation, of
the equation on the cost grid. While this residual is the residual of a final grid equation.
I mean, if you look at this, this is at the same point. So this is the same solution,
just interpolated to the final grid.
I'm evaluating the solution on a different mesh, on a different equation, different discretization.