So let's give that a try. So let's make another file, function dudt wave, and the t of u still, we have dudt.
So this u may not be a good, let's do phi and psi.
So let's give that a try. dudt of phi and psi.
I'll just write that as dudt.
So n is equal to length of phi psi over 2.
So because phi and psi,
is going to contain a variable that is discretized.
That is, so here I use the u and k, but this is,
yeah, so it contains the discretized phi and psi for all the spatial grid points.
Okay.
And phi is going to be equal to phi psi from 1 to n,
and psi is equal to phi psi,
from n plus 1 to n.
So this is basically splitting the input variable into the two different variables.
Does it make sense?
So let's use central difference.
And actually let me just copy what we did in this case.
Except for here we du dx.
And in this case we need d.
d.
d is equal to phi dx.
I would also want to say dx is equal to 2 pi over n.
And let's do a find and replace u with phi.
Replace all editor current file.
Looking okay.
Okay, here I actually saved it as dudt, so just to make it better, I will just rename
it as ddt, because we are not using u here.
Okay, ddt, not central, yeah, ddt central.
I opened the wrong file, yes, I opened the wrong file.
So this is still ddt central, I wanted ddt wave.
Alright.
How do you do a replacement only in the selection?
Anyway, so before I figure that out, I will just do a manual replacement.
Okay.
That's it, right?
So we have dphi dx and dpsi dx.
Both figured out.
And now our dphi dt is equal to dpsi dx, dpsi dt is equal to dphi dx, right?
That's our derivation of the wave equation.
Okay.
And the ddt is going to be, first I'm going to put, so in the beginning I have psi phi
in the beginning, so dphi dt and dpsi dt.
So that's my output of the function.
Alright.
So let's start with a phi being dpsi.
Okay.
So that's my output of the function.
Alright.
So let's start with a phi being dpsi dt.
Okay.
So I'm going to start with the same as my u0, maybe.
Oh, my u0 was a bad one, right?
So let me see.
U0 is equal to, let's set my phi zero to be that, and the psi zero to be phi zero multiplied
by zero.
So this corresponds to a wave that is initially phi.
Okay.
So now it's going to be a wave that is a very small wave.
initially flat because du dx is initially equal to zero so the whole thing is flat the whole
solution is zero but with the initial velocity with the initial d ud t right that is like this
wave okay so let's do a t and uh phi and psi equal to od 45 of ddt wave zero so how long do
we want to integrate it still just uh let's let's do pi just to see what do we get and we put phi
first and psi second oh zero great
okay now we solved it
this is our solution we are only interested in the very last part so let's just plot it uh to see
x and phi psi and and one to a hundred right so that's our phi
oh i didn't
close the previous one
that doesn't look good
i must have made an error somewhere
okay so let's plot phi zero what is phi zero psi zero is zero okay let me see ddt wave
to end n plus one to the end
so if i do this from one direction to the other
my λ 1 to the partial and when i do this from one direction to the other dangling to for right i'm wouldn't
so if I do this from 101 to 200 what is it giving us?
I don't know if it makes a difference but when you parse the 5 aside from the initial
values you're referring to a vector index and you're providing a matrix so instead of
the semicolon you can call the ODE.
You mean when I'm doing here?
Yeah, I don't know if that would...
Oh, thank you, yeah, that's right.
That's right.
That's what I should do.
Okay.
So let's see, plot the...
Now...
Now that's a lot better.
Okay.
And let's plot the side...
Okay, okay, that's good.
So let's do an animation of how this is going to work.
So let's do T...
Let's do I goes from 1 to 1000.
Let's actually keep this going.
So let's do this.
Okay, sorry.
So let's do 5 psi 0 equal to what we had in the beginning.
Okay.
And...
So let's do T and 5 psi is equal to that ODE 45.
Okay.
And let's only time integrate it for a short time.
So 0 to, let's say, 0.1.
5 psi 0 as initial condition.
And I'd like to hold off and plot x and 5 psi...
Okay.
Let's do 5 psi 0.
So we are going to overwrite the initial condition using the last solution of ODE 45.
And we are going to plot x with 5 psi 0, 1 to 100.
Let's use blue and hold on.
Plot x 5 psi 0 of 101 to 200.
Let's do red.
And let's pause for a little bit.
Pause.
Do I need to draw?
Maybe I don't.
And...
So let's see what do we get.
So that's the solution of the wave equation we see.
Because it's periodic, basically the wave goes out and comes back from the other side.
So remember when we look at the eigenvalues of the matrix, we get 1 and minus 1.
Right?
What that means is that similar to a linear advection equation which only has one velocity going towards the right,
in this equation we essentially have two velocities.
One going towards the right with velocity 1, another going towards the left at velocity 1.
It's a superposition of linear advection equations with 1 and minus 1 velocities.
And of course now we are seeing, because we are doing this for so long,
and using central difference, which error is taking its toll over here?
Dispersion error.
Dispersion error, right.
So we are seeing some of the frequencies are probably not at the right place anymore after evolving for so long.
But because we are using central difference, we are seeing that the frequencies are probably not at the right place anymore after evolving for so long.
But because we are using central difference scheme, there is not much, actually not any dissipation error in this numerical solution.
The wave keeps going.
Alright.
Any questions about this?
Yes?
What is the physical difference between a dissipation error and a dispersion error?
What is the physical difference?
Dissipation, it's...
So I think there is a...
So the physical meaning of what is dissipation, right,
I mean when you say dissipation error, that means you have a numerical error, not physical, that acts like a dissipation.
So...
Right.
Dissipation means it is diffusing things.
It is like the dissipation of heat, for example.
Dissipation of heat is if you have a very hot object, the heat is going to dissipate.
It means it is going to transfer the high temperature region into the lower temperature regions.
Entropy increases.
The hot thing is going to cool down and the cold thing is going to heat up due to dissipation of heat.
Dispersion is different.
Dispersion maintains how much energy or how much almost kinetic energy you have.
But like you have different components of the energy.
You have different components of the energy going into different places.
That's roughly my understanding of what dissipation and dispersion means.
Yes?
.
Yes.
How do I go back to you?
Good question.
The best way to go back to you is to look at both of the solutions.
For example, you have du dx.
Right?
If you integrate over the spatial domain for du dx, you are going to recover the solution u up to a constant.
And exactly what constant we are recovering, we need to look at the other component, du dt.
To decide from the last time step what is the constant.
To the next time step, what is the constant?
Right?
So we know, for example, we know the evolution of du dx.
We know the value of du dt.
So we know the averaged, spatially averaged du dt.
And that is going to give us how the constant term, how the average of u is going to evolve as a function of time.
So you need to combine, again, combine these two solutions to recover the u.
Any other questions?
Yeah.
Thank you.