So now let's discuss how to solve this equation. We have a set of linear equations and it can be potentially a huge number of linear equations.
So if nx and ny are both on the order of 100, you get like 10,000 equations. If both are on the order of 1,000, you get like a million equations.
So how to solve a million coupled equations?
So the best way is to put it into matrix form.
And one of the things I think you'll learn through going to this class is learn how to put equations into matrix form.
Once you put equations into matrix form, it suddenly becomes easy to solve with computers.
Okay.
And there was a person who was a professor in computer science who said that computers are really good at only two things.
One is moving and transforming data.
The other is solving linear equations, like doing linear algebra, basically.
And doing linear algebra requires you to transform whatever problem you need to solve into matrices.
And this is what we are going to do.
Is to transform this equation into a matrix.
So first of all, how big does the matrix have to be?
So let's write out the matrix.
So you can see I planned this to be big, right?
So this times the solution is equal to a right-hand side.
How big is the matrix?
So let's say given this number of equations and this number of unknowns.
It's the same, right?
So it's n times columns.
n times rows.
The number of equations stands for the number of rows.
Exactly.
The number of unknowns is the number of columns.
So before we write down this matrix, let's first write down the unknowns.
And the right-hand side of the equations.
So each equation is one line corresponding, one row corresponding to the matrix.
And the right-hand side should be equal to the corresponding right-hand side of the equation.
So let's write down F11 here.
And of course there are two ways to order the right-hand side.
You can start with F12, F13.
Or you can go ahead and write F21, F23.
Sorry.
F21 and F31.
So let's here adopt the C or Python type of indexing.
So we go F12, F13 all the way to F1 and Y.
Minus one.
Yes, thank you.
And if you are using...
So this is basically how a C or Python put an array.
Put an array into memory.
Because computer memory is actually a 1D, a huge 1D array.
And if you want to represent a 2D or 3D array of data or matrix, you can arrange the matrix,
arrange the data in the matrix in two ways.
One is you arrange the second index first or you arrange the first index first.
If you use C or Python, you change the second index first.
And you can do that.
So you start with the first index first.
And after you cycle through all the second indices, you begin to increment the first
index by one.
In Matlab or Fortran, it is the other way.
You increment the first index first.
And after you cycle through the first index, you start to increment the second index by
one.
So either way is fine.
I don't have any preference of one way or the other.
F22, F23, et cetera.
So either way is fine.
Food galaxii, et cetera.
So you can think of there is a mental or a logical separation here.
But the computer actually doesn't care.
And I will write dot, dot, dot.
The last one is gonna be F of nx minus one, one.
And all the way to F, nx minus one, and y minus one.
So as we arrange the equations that way, it makes sense arrangements to arrange the unknowns
in the same way.
F11.
And Y.
So u11, u12, etc. to u1, ny-1, u21, u22, all the way to u2, ny-1, etc.
Going through all the u's.
And finally, we have u of nx-1, 1, and u of nx-1, ny-1.
Can somebody look at the equation and tell me what the matrix is going to look like?
It's going to be very sparse. That's a very good observation.
Why is it sparse?
Because the matrix, each row of the matrix, has nx-1, ny-1.
And only how many of them are non-zero?
Five, right?
If i and j are away from 1 or nx-1, ny-1, five of them are going to be non-zero.
If they are close to the boundary, if i and j are close to the boundary, even less are going to be non-zero.
Right?
So at most, five in a row is going to be non-zero.
So let's set an example.
The first row, we are considering something equal to f11,
which means this equation has to be i equal to 1, j equal to 1.
Which indices are going to be non-zero?
I mean, which entries on the matrix is going to be non-zero?
Is the first entry going to be non-zero?
Because we have this term and this.
This term in the equation, right?
So u11 is going to appear in the equation.
Right.
And the coefficient is going to be minus 2 over delta x squared minus 2 over delta y squared.
That's right.
And if you think a little bit carefully for all the other i's and j's,
the same coefficient are going to appear on the diagonal.
Right?
In the matrix, the diagonal.
So this means the corresponding entry of the unknown
is multiplied by the diagonal entry
and equal to the same entry on the right-hand side.
Which means we are looking for the term of ij in this linear combination.
Right?
The same ij that appears on the right-hand side.
So this is always going to be the same number up to,
all the way to the last one.
Minus 2 over delta x squared minus 2 over delta y squared.
Okay.
A big task is done.
We've figured out the diagonal entries.
And let's, let's, let's cross out these diagonal entries from this equation.
We already took care of these two.
By going through the right-hand side, we also took care of these two.
And now we have four terms left.
Okay.
So we have two terms left.
Again, if we focus on the first row again,
what other terms are non-zero?
The one immediately to the right-hand side of the diagonal is going to be non-zero
because of which term?
Because of i plus 1j or ij plus 1?
ij plus 1.
Right.
Because we ordered the f.
And u.
Because we ordered the u's in this way.
So u of 1, 2 is going to be corresponding to this term.
Right.
This is u of 1, 2.
So the coefficient of this one is, of course, 1 over delta y squared
because we are looking at this term over here.
Okay.
Is there any other terms that is going to be non-zero?
The one below the diagonal.
But that is another row.
We are focusing on the first row.
There are two more.
So first of all, if j is equal to 1, this term is gone.
Oops.
Right.
So if j is equal to 1, this term is 0.
And if i is equal to 1, this term is also 0.
So we don't need to take care of these two terms.
They only...
The only term left is ui plus 1 and j.
Where is that?
Exactly.
You need to skip over a bunch of zeros and comes to the entry...
Comes to the...
Which entry?
N-yth entry.
Right.
So this is the N-yth entry.
And I have 1 over delta x squared.
All right.
Okay.
Now look at the second row.
Now j is equal to 2.
We have the same 1 over delta y squared on the upper diagonal.
Because we still need to take care of this term.
This is u of 1, 3.
Now we have one more term on the lower diagonal that corresponds to this one.
That is also 1 over delta y squared.
Okay.
And the delta...
1 over delta x term is also going to be shifted by 1 because j is shifted by 1.
All right.
And this goes all the way up to here.
Or here.
So let's consider this as the first block.
Of the matrix.
The first block of the matrix...
Has...
The first block of the matrix, if you don't consider this 1 over delta x squared,
is going to have the same tri-diagonal structure as the finite difference in 1D case.
Right.
But in addition to that, we get a diagonal block.
We get another block that appears over here.
That is just the 1 over delta x squared on the diagonal of the block.
And now the question is, when we get to the last entry...
When we are looking at the last entry, f of 1 and y minus 1.
We have...
The same thing minus 2 over delta x squared minus 2 over delta y squared over here.
We have the same thing 1 over delta y squared over here.
Do we have a minus...
Do we have a 1 over delta y squared over here?
On the right-hand side of this?
Diagonal is multiplied by u of 1 and y minus 1.
The upper diagonal 1 over delta y squared is multiplied by this.
So ui of j plus 1.
But ui of j plus 1 in this case is u1ny.
u1ny.
Which is 0.
So we don't need to put anything here.
In fact, if we put anything here, it will be wrong.
Because it will be multiplied by u of 2, 1.
Right.
So we are already at this point.
Well, actually, yeah.
We are already at...
So let's say 4 is ny.
We are already at this point.
This is my est here.
But if we move up here, we need to get more information.
So u1 is also aκι plus px.
We also need to multiply.
This is min which is also aki.
We added tu which is also 30
minus b1 in the final .
And, u1 is much like ui here.
We just use all the multiplications and nodes together.
Why we also don't need to make laugh a few times.
Moreover, c is a יש.
u1 and y minus 1 and u2 1 right so the ordering of the grid points are this
this this jump over to here and this this jump over back to here and this and
this over here and this point is not coupled to this point so there is
nothing here so the so the second I index or the second column of in this
plot is the same but we are gonna have a block that is the same as this and in
addition to a 1 over delta x block over here we also get a 1 over delta x squared
block over here all right
and
so so at the end we are going to get
what's called a penta diagonal structure so we get one diagonal over here one
diagonal immediately above one diagonal immediately below and one diagonal that
is an y minus 1 away from the diagonal and we also get another diagonal and Y
minus 1 below
the
diagram from the diagonal and we also get another diagonal and y minus 1 below the
main diagram.