Any questions so far? Yes?
How does that function to the quadrature points ?
Because of that, and I know you said they're a little more sparse in the middle of the interval,
and they're tighter on the edges, but how does it decide that?
The algorithm for computing Gauss quadrature points has evolved for basically 100 years.
It was initially proposed by Gauss. At that time, there were no computers, and they had to calculate by hand what the Gauss quadrature points were.
But because Gauss quadrature points is already very useful with five points,
they actually spent a lot of time calculating the quadrature points.
So they were manipulating the Gauss quadrature points for up to, say, 10 points by hand.
Basically solving n plus 1, no, not n plus 1, solving these two n nonlinear equations to get these two n numbers.
So the two n numbers are the locations, n locations and n weights.
And the two n equations you have to solve are the fact that when you plug in any polynomial
of order 2n minus 1, which have 2n degrees of freedom, right?
So you have the constant term, you have first order term, up to 2n minus 1th order term in the polynomial.
So you have to solve two n equations, get two n unknowns.
And people did this by hand, like up to something like 10 points.
But after the computer was invented, there has been a series of advances in algorithms of how to compute them.
So it turns out there are much smarter ways.
Than just solving these two n equations.
And a lot of the nowadays, one of the quite very simple and pretty accurate algorithms is used what's called orthogonal polynomials.
So there are a set of orthogonal polynomials whose zero point.
So in this case, if you want to integrate a uniform function,
the polynomial corresponding to these axes are called the Legendre polynomials.
So Legendre polynomials is a set of orthogonal polynomials you can compute.
You can compute every polynomial from a linear combination of the previous two polynomials times a simple function,
like x squared and remember what.
So once you know the n and n minus 1th order polynomial, you can compute the n plus 1th order polynomial pretty fast.
And if you can have an algorithm to find the root of the polynomial,
these are exactly the Gauss quadrature points.
Now you have the roots of the polynomials, then getting the weights.
If you know the x, then getting the weights is simply solving a set of linear equations,
which turns out to be pretty easy.
But these are sufficient usually for the number of quadrature points we want to use in finding elements.
But people have invented the...
algorithms that can scale to a lot more points.
There are even people who invented algorithms that goes to like a million points in Gauss quadrature.
These are pretty...
It's pretty rare to see applications that needs a million points in Gauss quadrature,
but like you can do that.
All right. Any other questions? Yes?
Why don't we have to pre-calculate the Gauss quadrature?
Why don't we have to pre-calculate the Gaussian points and weights for each set of our element?
Right. That's a good point.
So in practice, you don't. You just need to shift them and scale them.
Okay. And that would be done in that for loop?
Yeah. What's done in the for loop?
So if we are recalculating these quadrature points,
but in practice, a lot more computationally efficient way is to shift them and scale them.
So for example, if I do...
For example, if I do that, right?
So I get a bunch of axes and weights.
And if I also do that, I also get a bunch of x and weights.
But they are exactly...
So first of all, the x is...
They are exactly linear to each other.
For example, if I can do a figure and I can plot xL and xR,
you can see they lie on a line.
So they lie on a perfect line.
They are just a shift and scale of each other.
Also, if you plot the weights,
they are also going to be...
They are also lying on a simple line.
The weights, they are...
Because the weights go up and down,
so the first weight is exactly the same as the last weight.
And the second weight is exactly the same as the second last weight.
So this is why there are only three points instead of five.
But the ratio between the weights is basically the ratio between the length of the intervals.
Right?
And the ratio between the axes
are also the ratio between the length of the intervals.
And the shift is basically where my left point is.
So yeah, you can just...
A simple way is just to calculate the Gauss quadrature points and weights
for a reference interval.
A lot of people choose 0 and 1 or minus 1 and 1.
And then shift and scale them for your arbitrary intervals.