So today we will be talking about equation based modeling using console physics.
On Monday what you will see was a general introduction and using the built-in
physics based interfaces to solve different physical problems but
sometimes the models you want to solve might not be already built in into the
software but you might have your ordinary differential equation or partial
differential equation that models that process and so what we're talking about
today is how to enter those equations and how to pick the appropriate
interface and how to couple different PDs together if you have a couple of PDs
system. My name is Tamis Sagan, you can call me Tami. I work in the console as an
application engineer.
Primarily I work for Microsoft and I work for Microsoft and Microsoft is a
traditional software development company that is primarily focused on
structural mechanics and equation based modeling. So today we will be mostly
talking about equation based model. Now, console under the hood is really a
system for solving partial differential equations numerically. This can be linear
equations, nonlinear equations, scatters, systems but the idea is if we build the
if we build the infrastructure to solve an arbitrary system of PDEs or ODEs and algebraic
equations then we would be able to handle a lot of problems that are encountered in science and
engineering. Some other software sometimes start with solving a certain area saying okay we want
to solve a heat transfer problem or we want to make a fluid flow or we want to make structural
mechanics simulation package and the way we went about it is we want to make a PDE solver
and an ODE solver and anything most problems coming down form anyway then you can handle
them. So some of the more popular partial equations here the Maxwell equations at the bottom Navier-Stokes
equation at the top heat transfer, chemical interaction engineering, acoustic, Schrodinger's equation, the
elasticity equation.
So
the way this works then is under I mean on top of these PDEs we build physics based interfaces
for structural mechanics or electrical chemical thermal fluid and whenever you are designing any
device or analyzing most realistic problems there is going to be more than one of this
involved. If you are doing fluid structure interaction
you would need to couple structural mechanics with fluid flow. This happens often for example
if you are doing biomechanics and you want to analyze flow in blood vessels and then also
analyze stress in the arteries and couple that then you would need to do fluid structure
interaction. Or if you have doing a chemical reaction problems where the reaction generates or
consumes heat,
and also where reaction kinetics is temperature dependent you want to couple equations for chemical
and reaction with thermal equations. So there can be more than one of this that are combined and a lot
of this commonly understood multiphysics couplings are already built in into a console and a lot of the
problems that you might be interested in solving are already built in. I hope much of this will be
understood by the next lecture. Thank you.
One day you did the micro-remister beam example. This is what me and did.
It transfer electrical and I think structural mechanics and the couplings you needed there
were already built in so you just needed to click and add them and console would add the
necessary equation. But when you are doing research, when you are doing development,
often the equations you are interested in solving may not be part of what is built in
or maybe part of the solution. So I think that's a good question.
Maybe part of it is built in but there is a missing part. Maybe you are doing a structural
mechanics problem where the material behavior has a certain evolution law and that material
evolution law is not built in but structural mechanics in general is built in. So then what
you can do is just add your evolution equation as a PDE and couple it with the existing physics-based
interface. That is how most of our users do work when they
use equation-based modeling. It's rare that people will do everything from scratch using
equation-based modeling but obviously you don't want to reinvent the wheel. Part of it is already
there and the part that's missing you can add using user-defined equations. So
user-defined equations you use them when what you're interested in solving is not
in there or sometimes you're actually just curious to work directly with the equations.
Other times maybe you are a professor and if you are a grad student then just give it to them and
they should make it for you. But in any case we'll be talking about how then to implement your own
equations in Comsol. So the way it works is there are multiple templates for entering the equations
for ODEs, for PDEs and there are more than one ways.
So the first way is to use the equation-based model. So you can use the equation-based model
to enter PDEs. We'll talk about them. But the biggest thing is that you don't need to write
subroutines or anything like that. You just write your PDEs directly and that makes it faster for
you to try out different ideas when you're going well maybe the equation behaves this way. Maybe
there is this term I want to keep or maybe there's this other term I don't want to give.
So whenever you do that if you can directly prescribe your equations it makes it easy.
And these equations can be nonlinear, linear, transient or stationary. You don't have to
worry about that. Of course since you are taking a take a numerical analysis class you won't worry
about that. But in a more when you're using software to solve physical problems to solve to
develop a device.
So the first thing that you want to do is quickly test your ideas. And then of course later on you
can tweak once you have made the major decisions about your physics. So the way we will go about it
today is we'll talk about the mathematics interface first. Then I will focus on partial differential
equations, how to prescribe partial differential equations and boundary conditions when you are
using equation-based modeling.
So this is a very simple process. We will start with the first one. So we will start with the
differential and algebraic equations. Then we will do a demonstration of a thermal curing problem.
This is a heat transfer problem with a slightly non-standard material evolution law. So the way we
would normally solve this console is use the built-in equation the built-in heat transfer
interface for the heat transfer part.
So we will start with the thermal curing and couple them. But today for the for medical reasons what we will do is we'll do all of it using equation-based modeling.
We'll talk a little bit about what happens when you're working with axisymmetric components.
We'll talk a little bit about integral equations. We'll talk about verification.
And validation when you are using any of the built-in physics-based interfaces such as heat transfer
or structural mechanics or microfluidics or pipe flow in console. And this is true about other
packages as well. They would have done a verification of the fact that they have implemented
the right equation and whether it fits.
If weather works correctly by comparing it with either analytical solutions or experimental data.
Now you are putting your own equations and you don't have anything like that to rely on the
veracity of your equations. So we want to talk about how is it that then you can test
you are doing the right thing. You are solving the equation correctly.
And finally we'll go to the next slide.
So I will give you homework. Your professor wanted us to give you homework so we'll do that.
I will be asking you questions along the way and feel free to ask me any questions.
Don't wait until the end if anything in this whole conversation just stopped me and asked.
I have a couple of hats that I will give away either for good answers or really good questions.
And I'll let you decide.
Any questions so far?
Asking if you can get the hats isn't a good question.
Any other questions is legit.
Okay.
So let's start with how console deals with this.
When you, you have seen this Monday when you start a new problem.
You have to select the physics after you have specified your special dimension with everything.
3D, 2D, 1D, or 2D over 1D axis and metric.
You select the physics.
And here you see the ACDC, which are different interfaces for electrical and magnetics,
electromagnetic in general, or the fluid flow, heat transfer, semiconductor structural mechanics.
And at the end there is this node mathematics.
And that is where you go when you want to add your own equations rather than using the built-in
interfaces.
Now when you go to the mathematics interface, then there are choices within it.
So you could be specifying PDs, you could be specifying ODEs, you could be doing optimization
and sensitivity analysis.
We have this classical PDs branch.
That is really a replica of the PD interfaces.
But things like this.
And then you have the other interfaces.
Things like Laplace equation, Poisson equation, Helmholtz equation.
People often use them.
So we want sort of a prepackaged option for those.
So that's what you get under classical PDs.
If you are solving a problem with a moving domain or with a moving interface, we have
a mathematical level set and phase field interfaces that you can use.
So for example, if you're having a heat transfer problem with space change.
We already have a heat transfer with space change interface built in.
But this is when you are adding your own phase field or level set type mathematics.
Then the form branch for solving problems on moving domains and other interfaces.
So what we will be talking about today is what we get in the PD interfaces and in the
OE and DA interfaces.
And as you see there in the PD interfaces.
You have a couple of different options to specify your PDs.