In the last lecture, we have a known function f of x that is known.
And we are just trying to construct the best possible approximation of f
within a finite dimensional space.
So we first define a finite dimensional space.
A finite dimensional space means a space of functions, a linear space of functions.
And linear space means any linear combination of two functions in the space is still in the same space.
So a finite dimensional space means any function g that can be represented as a linear combination.
i goes from 1 to n.
I call it gi.
Of vi of x.
And so that is for any g1, etc. to gn.
So this is a space that is equivalent in some sense to the n-dimensional space of real numbers.
So for any combination of n real numbers,
you can construct a unique element.
In the space.
By using these real numbers as linear combination coefficients on a particular set of bases.
So here,
phi i, i goes from 1 to n,
is a basis.
Right?
So once we have that basis,
we can construct the best approximation of f.
So,
we can use the best approximation of f in x.
The best approximation of f in x can be obtained by minimizing the distance f minus g,
such that g is in that space.
So the distance in this case is the L2 distance,
where the distance, the square of the distance, is defined as the integration function of the n-dimensional space.
So, we can use the best approximation of f in x,
which is defined as the integration from this domain.
So, we need to specify that f is in a particular domain.
So, and the L2 norm of the difference between two functions,
is the integral of the square of the function.
And then take a square root.
Now because of we are having a square here,
the square root cancels,
and the square of the L2 norm is simply the integral of the square root.
of the function.
Okay,
and now,
we can further expand it to integration f minus integration of g .
So, we are minimizing,
now instead of g in x,
we are minimizing g .
i goes from 1 to n.
We are minimizing over these coefficients,
because we can represent g using linear combination of the basis.
So, g .
i,
phi,
square,
dx.
And we turn that optimization problem into a set of linear equations.
How do we turn that into a linear equations?
We use perturbation analysis.
Last lecture,
we perturbed this function g a little bit.
Right?
And we derived the condition that the minimizer has to ensure that
the distance between f and g is going to be orthogonal
to any function
in the same linear space.
Right?
So,
through a perturbation or variational analysis,
we found that
in order to have this minimized,
we must ensure that f minus g,
which is the linear summation,
has to be orthogonal to any function in the same space,
which any function, of course, includes the basis.
So, this times any of the phi j's has to be equal to 0.
And this turns into a linear equation a times g equal to b.
Okay, so this is the procedure we used last lecture.
To construct the best approximation of a known function.
Of course,
if we know what the function is,
we can basically use the analytical form
without having to construct an approximation.
So, the real utility of this procedure,
exactly the same procedure,
is in solving differential equations,
where we actually don't know the solution a priori.
We only know the solution satisfies a certain differential equation.
It turns out we can use the same procedure
to solve differential equations.