Okay, so yesterday we worked on the multi-grid algorithm.
So the algorithm started with computing the residual of the matrix.
So let's go back to the code we wrote by the end of our last lecture.
So what the first part is doing is to compute the residual of the matrix.
We initialized R to be a zero vector, and for every grid point we computed R to be the right-hand side,
minus the action of the discretization on the vector u0.
So this is the residual. This is b minus a times u0.
So in fact...
I'd like to actually put this into a function.
So if we put this into a function called residual,
that'll make the code a bit cleaner.
So the residual takes a u0 and b, and it should return a R.
And we can move this part.
The whole part into the residual function.
Right, so that computes the residual.
And we can call this R is going to be equal to residual u0 and b.
Right, so the first step of the multi-grid is to compute the residual.
And usually in a regular multi-grid, there is a...
Before computing the residual, we usually perform a few iterations to pre-smooth the solution.
We are going to talk about why do we need to pre-smooth the solution in the general setting.
Last lecture we didn't pre-smooth the solution.
The multi-grid worked.
But let's add this into the multi-grid to perform a few pre-smoothing.
And the pre-smoothing is a very important part of the solution.
So pre-smoothing is the same as what we performed here.
So basically perform a few Gauss-Seidel iterations.
Okay, before we compute the residual.
So that is, we are going to take u0 and perform a few Gauss-Seidel iterations.
And I'll call this pre-smoothing.
And then after pre-smoothing, we compute the residual.
Okay, I don't need any comments here.
And then we interpolate the residual to the cost grid.
So because we made a...
Let's make it 5 and 5 to keep the computation cost exactly the same as before.
All right.
Okay.
After we interpolate...
So this is the...
These two lines, line 10 and 11, are interpolation of R to the cost grid.
In this case...
The cost grid actually has grid points that lies exactly on every other grid point of
the fine grid.
Therefore, the interpolation is a trivial interpolation.
We just take the value at these grid points.
And then...
Not perform iterations.
Iterations.
Then we perform iterations on the cost grid.
So this is...
We performed smoothing on the fine grid.
We computed the residual.
We interpolated the residual onto the cost grid.
In multi-grid, this is...
This has a special name.
Going...
Interpolating the residual from the cost grid to fine grid...
From fine grid to cost grid is called restriction.
So this restriction operator is actually...
This is interpolation.
Okay.
And now we are at the cost grid.
At the cost grid...
At the next cost grid...
We perform another smoothing operation.
Right?
So this is when this didn't happen.
This is when we are at the cost grid.
Then we perform Gauss-Seidel iterations.
But otherwise, we go into another multi-grid call.
And the other multi-grid call, we go back to here.
And we would be performing the pre-smoothing again.
Okay.
Right?
So let's actually make a few breakpoints on this.
And we'll take a look at...
So we'll make a breakpoint before the pre-smoothing.
After the pre-smoothing.
Okay.
And then after we compute...
After we go into the cost grid.
And we'll come over here.
The interpolation...
Before the interpolation.
After the interpolation.
And after the post-smoothing.
Alright.
So we will make a few breakpoints.
And we will step through the multi-grid algorithm to see how it works.
So again, we are going to load the same B matrix we loaded in our last lecture.
So B is going to be here.
Here we are going to make u equal to zeros the size of b.
Okay, and let's start.
So u is equal to multi-grid of u and b.
So the breakpoints didn't work.
Oh, okay, so I think I opened the wrong file.
Let me see.
Let me save this.
I think I opened the file from the last lecture.
So let's save it to the current lecture.
Okay, replace it.
Okay, so let me make the breakpoints again.
Before pre-smoothing, after pre-smoothing,
and after interpolation,
after the coarse-grid solution,
and
after
interpolating to the fine-grid,
and at the end of the iteration.
Okay, so let's make u equal to the zeros again,
and do our multi-grid.
So this is in the beginning of the multi-grid,
and our u0 should be completely zero.
So if I do imshow of u0,
I get a blank black image.
So this is my initial guess.
Now let me continue.
So,
we performed a few pre-smoothing operations,
only five, right?
So now, when I perform imshow,
what am I expected to get?
I get,
do you see a very faint white lines appearing on the screen?
Right?
So, what this does,
the five iterations of Gauss-Seidel,
has smoothed,
not the solution a little bit,
but the solution error a little bit.
Right?
So this is the effect of the smoothing.
It reduces the solution error a little bit,
and especially it reduces the high-frequency content of the solution error.
Remember, the solution error is the difference between the true solution
and the solution we are getting right now.
And therefore, by reducing the very smooth,
by smoothing the solution error a little bit,
what I'm doing is,
the very sharp content of the solution is going to appear on my screen.
Right?
Okay.
So, now my solution error is a little bit smoother.
That also, in this context,
means the residual is a bit smoother.
So, what I can do is,
I can then compute the residual and,
and interpret it.
And interpolate the residual to my Gauss grid.
So, come over here.
My residual is now on my Gauss grid.
Right?
And then, if I continue,
what am I going to be at,
at the next time?
Which line am I going to be?
If I click continue,
am I going to be at line 22?
I'm going to be at line 3,
because I will be calling multigrid again, exactly.
So, next time, I'm at line 3 again.
Okay?
And let's look at what is my U0.
What do you think is my U0 in this case?
Is it going to be an interpolated solution of what I have here?
No.
It is 0.
Because here, what I'm doing,
is I'm solving the error equation.
I'm trying to correct the solution,
I had before, I had in my final grid.
So, I computed my residual,
and I started from 0,
trying to solve the error equation
of A times delta x,
equal to the residual,
and I started with 0.
If you don't believe me,
I am sure of U0 here
is going to be completely black.
It's a smaller image,
and completely black.
Right?
Okay.
So, now, if I perform a,
a continue,
and I finished doing 5 iterations of pre-smoothing,
what I get is,
again, very faint lines.
Maybe you don't see it,
but like, there is a very faint lines.
Let me, let me multiply by 10.
You may see a little better, right?
So, it's a,
you get the high frequency content of the solution,
but on the coarser grid.
Okay.
Now, I computed the residual and interpolated again.
So, now, I have to do the same thing
to the even coarser grid.
Next time, I'm going to be at 3 again
on the even smaller grid.
So, of course, my U0 is again going to be 0,
because now I'm solving the error equation
of the 500 by 500 grid, right?
So, now, I am at 256 by 256 grid.
Now, after the smoothing iterations,
let me do IAMSHOW on this again.
I get an even smaller image,
and still these contours.
But remember, these very sharp contours on the small image,
when I go back and interpolate to the coarser grid,
it'll be the smooth portion of the solution on the,
so, go back to the finer grid,
it'll be a smooth features on the finer grid.
Right.
Okay.
So, keep going.
Next step, I'm at an even coarser grid.
Let me go this for a few seconds.
Let me go this for a few steps.
What is my N now?
My N is now, I'm at 64 by 64.
And if I keep going,
I'm at 32 by 32.
Keep going, I'm at 16 by 16.
Okay.
Here.
And now,
I'm at 8 by 8.
So, here, if we look at the solution on the 8 by 8 grid,
we get something that is,
like that.
So, it's very hard to,
basically we get like almost the most smooth portion,
like that.
Right.
So, we get the very smooth portion of the solution.
And finally, when we,
when we are at a coarser enough grid,
I think we are at four,
we are at four now.
So, we'll still go through.
Okay.
So, when, so here, right.
So, N on the finer grid,
my size is equal to four on the coarser grid,
it's even smaller.
So, here, what I did is I performed a 10 Gauss-Seidel iterations
on the coarser grid.
And I come over to here.
So, now, I'm interpolating my DU.
To the finer grid.
So, my DU,
my DU here is,
let me just type DU.
So, my DU here is going to be a three by three matrix,
three by three array.
Right.
So, the boundaries are zero.
And this is the only solution I get.
So, I'm basically solving a matrix equation with how many unknowns,
in this case.
With just a single unknown.
Right.
So, this is probably an exact solution after 10 Gauss-Seidel.
I mean, this is, this must be an exact solution,
even with one Gauss-Seidel iteration.
Because I'm solving an equation with only one unknown.
And then, I'm interpolating this to the finer grid.
And adding the solution to the previous,
previous solution after,
after the pre-smooth.
So, what I have gone is,
I have gone through here.
And sometimes, people use a direct solver on the Causs-Seidel grid.
Because on the Causs-Seidel grid,
the matrix is so small that usually a direct solver beats an iterative solver.