And one of the things I asked you to do which actually has nothing to do with numerical PDE's per se
but like is used a lot in numerical methods is I was asking you to
look at how uniform
the temperature is and I want to also minimize how much water you are using
So the amount of water you're using is a integration
from let's say 0 to T and by the way if you want to compute the average amount of water per unit time you would be
dividing that by 1 over T times U of T dt
So if you have a function either analytical or numerical
You can you should also be computing the integral
So I want to I want to get a sense of how many people already know how to integrate
numerically functions
up
, so I want to get a sense of how many people already know how to integrate numerically functions
like that
It's like half of the class so I'll say a little bit on that
The I
would only teach one way of doing numerical integration for now that is a
trapezoidal rule so if this is UT and this is T equal to 0 this is T equal to big T
if you use a
Something like finite difference you have you did you can discretize the function at
grid points
so 2 Delta T
etc up to T is equal to n times Delta T and
You have a function like this and the value of the function is known at these grid points
The trapezoidal rule is very simple it is approximating the integral of the function
which is the area under this curve
by many small trapezoids
So basically that means linking the every pair of grid points using a straight line
Okay, and count how much area is beneath this straight line and this straight line
So for example if you have u0 and u1 and u2 here
What is the area?
behind
This trapezoid where this is 0 Delta T. This is u0 u1
Yes
Exactly so that's how much area is under this curve, so how much area is under the summation of all these
all these uh all these uh all these uh
Linear lines, what is the summation of all the areas?
It's basically a summation over you can pull Delta T out
it's going to be a summation of I goes from 1 to n of
Ui minus 1 plus ui so that's a very good approximation of this integral
And if you want you can go back and do Taylor series analysis and convince yourself
This is actually
second-order approximation
Yeah
At least the second-order approximation depends on how smooth the function is right so so this is a
This is what you can use to do the projects. I
Don't think today. I have time to go to intuitive methods so the rest of 10 minutes. I will see if
Anybody wants to ask additional questions on the project?
I want to say about this one. Yeah, we just focus on continuous functions. So no impulse functions are like periodic ones.
Like as they turn the water on, then it turns off, then it turns back on.
Like you do not have like that at all.
It's up to you. It's up to you. So even if you do piecewise continuous functions
It's also pretty easy to use this to integrate if you let's say turn this off at this point and turn it on again
You can just focus on integrating this part of the solution.
Right?
So there is there is nothing that prevents you to do piecewise continuous functions
And also it also allows you to do non-uniform
spacing in time so for example if you use ODE45 to integrate your ODE
ODE45 is going to return you an array of time steps or time points, right?
And there is no guarantee it will return you a uniform array of time points
so instead of having
a constant delta t the modification would be
non constant
Delta t would be summation of i goes from 1 to n of delta t i
ui plus 1 or ui minus 1 plus ui over 2 so this would be a
same integral with non-uniform time steps