Let's now start talking about what if I'm not happy with just the energy norm?
What if I want a more general norm?
How can I say that the finite element solution, how good is the finite element solution in some other norm?
It turns out in some other norm I can no longer say that, so for example, if I look at the H1 norm, so u minus uh.
I can no longer say that this is optimal.
In fact, this is not going to be optimal in all possible finite dimensional, in all possible members of the finite dimensional space.
But I can bound this.
I can bound this to be some number times u minus wh.
For all possible wh's in this finite dimensional space.
So I can do that by the following.
So first of all, let's define what is u minus uh in the H1 norm.
So u minus uh in the H1 norm is the summation of two parts.
Right?
One is the integration of u minus uh squared plus the derivative of u minus uh squared dx.
No, no, I actually don't need that because I can just start.
I don't need to use the Poincare inequality again.
I can just start by saying that.
The energy norm is coercive.
The bilinear form is coercive.
So what I can say is that u minus uh in the H1 norm squared is less or equal to 1 over b times the energy norm.
And we know that the energy norm is the energy norm is the minimizer.
So this is less or equal to 1 over b of u.
So we can just write u minus wh.
u minus wh.
For all the possible wh's in xh.
And also, let's use the continuity of this bilinear form here.
So by continuity, this is less than c times the norm of u minus uh squared.
And also, this is less than c times the norm of u minus wh.
So the error in H1 norm is not exactly minimized.
But it is close to minimum in a certain sense.
It is close to minimum in that the error is not going to be greater than a certain finite constant times the minimum error you can achieve.
So the error in H1 norm is not going to be greater than a certain finite constant times the minimum error you can achieve.
So the error in H2 norm is not going to be greater than a certain finite constant times the minimum error you can achieve.
Right?
So because this can be for any wh, the same inequality also is true for the wh that minimizes the norm.
So it is less than this times the infinimum or the minimum of wh in xh.
u minus wh.
Okay, now with that, we can start looking at what rate of convergence do we have.
So infinite difference, we can analyze the order of accuracy of the differential operator.
Right?
So if we use a central difference to approximate a first order derivative, we know the error goes down like delta x squared.
If you use a forward difference, you can see that the error goes down like delta x squared.
If you use a forward difference or backward difference, we know the error goes down only with delta x.
So here we can do the same analysis here, infinite element, once we have that inequality.
Because this inequality holds for any wh.
So we can easily construct a delta h, construct a wh for which we know the order of accuracy.
And we know that the same order of accuracy is going to apply for the same order of accuracy.
And we do that even if you are only sure that the
And this is because if you look at the c and b here, the c and b here are the properties of this a, of this bilinear form, right?
It has nothing to do with h, it has nothing to do with what kind of approximation we are making.
It has nothing to do with the specific x-h, right?
So, if we can construct a w, which is anyway a deeper string, minus a one culture, which is anyway a developer code,
So that also means as we refine the mesh, as we refine the mesh, which also makes the XH to be richer and richer,
has more and more approximation power, the C over B is not going to change.
Okay, that allows us to build specific WHs.
For example, what the WHs we are using here is an interpolant.
So let's say we have a U, so that is the green one is U.
And we have a finite element mesh over here that restricts our approximation UH to be piecewise linear functions.
So why don't we construct WHs that actually goes through these grid points.
So this is going to be our WH.
So WH.
Is just connecting the dots on the function.
Of course, the WH is in the space, right?
We are trying to approximate.
And so let's start to analyze what is the, what is this approximation error in H1?
So the approximation error in H1.
So let's, let's call this WH.
Uh, this is particular.
Let's call the interpolant of U.
So I begot interpolant.
It's with the H because it's on the particular mesh.
So let's figure out what is this U minus interpolant?
What is this approximation error?
Of course, it has two terms.
It has one term that is the L2 error of the interpolant.
And also another term that is the L2 error of the derivative of the interpolant.
So let's figure out these two terms one by one.
And the point here is to see how does this error decrease as my refine my mesh.
If I know, for example, the error decreases like delta X square as a refined mesh.
Then I know that the U minus UH is also going to decrease like delta X square as a refined mesh.
Because this, this C over B doesn't change as I refine the mesh.
Right.
Okay.
So, so, so here we go back to Taylor series analysis.
So we look at first, we need to analyze how big.
Is this approximately how, what is the maximum difference between the red line and the green line?
So let's first look at the maximum difference between the derivatives.
And in order to do that, I need to use.
So, so first of all, the derivative of the interpolant over a interval is going to be constant, right?
It's going to be.
You add grid point.
I plus one minus you.
I divided by X I plus one minus X I.
So that's the slope of these curve over that interval over the element.
Now what we need to do is we need to use what's called the mean value theorem.
Okay.
So.
is how the mark equals a point.
Of course, if you have.
If you have some slight depression.
Then I think we can let Dimidex out and find the maximum on thecity level here.
Dad with no problem.
Thank you guys.
Yeah.
Thank you.
here. The proof is pretty simple. So if all the du, dx's are above that value, then you cannot
average to this value. If all the du, dx's below that value, you cannot also average to that value,
right? So that means you have to have a certain point du, dx's greater or equal, another point
du, dx's less or equal. And because du, dx's a continuous function, so you have to have some
point where du, dx's is exactly equal to this value, where xi is somewhere between xi and xi plus 1.
All right. So now we have this. Then du, dx's at any point in eta, that is within the space,
now has to equal to du, dx's at xi
plus xi.
So last Taylor series analysis again is going to be the second order derivative of u to x
times eta minus xi. Well, this is at xi plus o eta minus xi squared.
And this whole term I claim is order
delta x or order x.
So let's say h is the maximum where h is the maximum of xi plus 1 minus xi.
All right. So this is order h because eta and xi are both in the interval xi and xi plus 1.
So the difference between eta and xi has to be o h.
All right. Any questions so far?
All right.
So we are done with this.
We already know that the derivative term in the Sobolev norm has to be order h.
And it turns out the same thing happens for the value.
The value is actually a lot easier.
So u minus...
u minus...
the interpolant of u at a particular xi is going to be the integral of the difference from xi to xi of du dx minus dih u dx dx.
Right.
We already know this term is o h.
So this whole thing because xi minus xi is also o h.
So this guy is o h squared.
So the Sobolev norm of u minus interpolant of u.
Square.
Well.
It's going to be equal to...
integration of u minus ih of u squared and this term before square is oh h
square plus d dx of u minus interpolant of u squared and this thing before I
square is oh so this is whole thing should be oh so after I square this is
all h square this is all h force so this is oh h squared and what I know is that
you minus my finite element solution is less or equal to C over B times u minus
any wh and in this case I just substitute the wh with this
interpolant and so it is going to be less or equal
to
oh h square so that gives us a bond on this Sobolev norm and of course the
bond on L2 norm is even is once we have the Sobolev norm the bonding L2 norm is
pretty easy so the L2 norm is basically the L2 norm is one component of this H1
norm right so it is
also so if I square it is also oh squared and