So last lecture we discussed characteristics of systems of conservation laws.
It turns out if we express the system of conservation laws in its primitive forms,
we write partial u partial x plus the derivative of the flux to the solution vector u.
So now everything is a vector.
So this is partial f partial u is the Jacobian matrix of the flux.
Because the flux is a multivariate, multidimensional function.
If we have a system of two conservation laws, there are two u's, there are two f's.
So df du is going to be a two by two matrix.
Right.
So we have this matrix.
Dot with the gradient of u.
So this is going to be equal to zero.
And if we perform eigenvalue analysis of that matrix, we get the characteristic speeds.
And thebeing igual to right.
As opposed to scalar conservation laws where- in which there is a single characteristic.
In a system of conservation laws, there are multiple characteristics usually corresponding to the dimension or of that matrix.
If we draw t in the y axis and x in the x axis in a scalar conservation law,
the characteristics determine the slope of the line on which the solutions are constant.
But for system of conservation laws, for example, in shallow water equation,
we derived two characteristic lines.
And on each characteristic line, a particular linear combination of the solution is preserved.
And that particular linear combination actually does not stay constant.
It doesn't stay, the linear combination coefficients of the solution doesn't stay constant.
It only stays constant for linear equations.
Whenever we have a nonlinear equation, dF du changes as the solution u changes.
Therefore, the characteristic speeds changes and the eigenvectors of the matrix changes as the solution evolves.
So along that line, even along that single characteristic line,
we no longer have a constant linear combination.
The linear combination itself actually changes.
And also, the line, the characteristic lines, at every point, we can compute its speed.
But the speed is no longer going to be staying constant.
Because the solution no longer stays constant.
Right.
Only particular linear combination of the solution stays constant for a small range.
And then the linear combination itself changes.
And everything, the solution is going to change.
So these characteristics, they, first of all, they are going to overlap each other because there are two characteristics.
Okay.
And also, they may curve even in smooth regions of the space.
And,
because the linear combination, they change its value,
if you make a small perturbation here, the small perturbation is going to propagate not only according to the characteristic speeds,
but also, they are going to influence every solution that is bounded by these two characteristic lines.
The region of influence of any small perturbation is going to be like a cone.
Okay.
Because this curve, we are going to have to take the
portion that goes from E to 1.
Okay.
So E to 1 is equal to E.
Right.
Because of the Hmmmm.
In this case, this Yeah.
Correct.
flow plus and minus square root of gh. What I was drawing corresponds to the
situation where the absolute value of u is smaller than square root of gh and the
other situation is when the absolute value of u exceeds square root of gh.
Then both characteristics are going in one direction. If we make a small
perturbation here, the region of influence of the perturbation is going to
be a cone like that, which means something interesting. That is, if you
look at a spatial point where x is smaller than the location of the
perturbation, that spatial point has absolutely no influence by the small
perturbation.
No matter how long you go ahead in time.
So this is a supersonic situation where if you fly a supersonic airplane,
the region of space ahead of you is never going to feel your
influence.
The only influence you have is on the space behind you.
That's why you create shock waves. The shock wave is
because before the shock wave hits you, the air never feels the presence of the
airplane. Only after the shock wave sweeps through that point, the air
feels the presence. This is the supersonic situation over here.
Alright, so now given these characteristics, we can now draw a new
equation.
So we can draw a new equation.
But as a result, we can now draw a new equation.
We now start to study what is the appropriate upwind, what is the appropriate upwinding
strategy for a system of conservation laws.
In scalar conservation laws, we know very well what is the upwind direction because
there is only one characteristic.
And depending on if the characteristic species is positive or negative,
if it's positive, we look towards the left.
If it's negative,
we look towards the right. Now we have multiple characteristics and in the
supersonic regions we still know what to do, right? We still know what to do
because there are other characteristics despite having multiple of them, the r
goes towards the same direction. In this case if u is greater than gh we should
all upwind towards the left. If minus u is greater than square root of gh we should
all upwind towards the right, but in the blue case it is not obvious how to
upwind it. It looks like depending on which characteristic are you talking
about my upwind direction can either be left or right. How to deal with this
situation? One very elegant way to deal with the situation where there are
multiple characteristics is to use the upwind direction. Now the upwind direction is
characteristics going in different directions is something is using
something we studied before that is the equivalence of up winding scheme to
numerical dissipation right so when we started a linear advection equation and
discretizing the spatial operator using upwind is going to give us a equation
that is du IDT plus in this case upwind is towards the left so you are minus ui
minus 1 over Delta X is equal to 0 the upwind discretization although it is a
first-order consistent discretization of the differential equation but it is
actually a more accurate
discretization of the differential equation but it is actually a more
accurate
I think a third order discretization of a different equation so that's so this
is a first order discretization of the original equation but it is a higher
order discretization of the equation with some numerical dissipation this is
equal to Delta X times partial square u
partial square u partial x square and this situation is the same for upwinding
in a different direction so if we are looking at the equation that is partial
u partial t plus any let me write C times partial u partial x equal to 0 no
matter what the sign of C is the upwinding is going to either give you
this scheme or
this is going to give you the upwinding of the differential equation so if C is
less than 0 it's going to give me du IDT plus ui plus 1 minus ui over Delta X is
equal to 0 but no matter if we have there is a C here no matter if C is
greater than 0 which we get the green case or C is less than 0 we get the blue case the upwind
is equal to delta x times the absolute value of C times the second derivative
of X of you upwinding no matter left or right is going to introduce a numerical
dissipation proportional to the grid size delta x and to the absolute value
of the characteristics characteristic speed
so that gives us motivation that if we have multiple characteristics a good way
to achieve the same effect of upwinding is by introducing a numerical
dissipation that is proportional to Delta X and also that is big enough for
the fastest characteristics in the system of equations