So everybody should see a screen like that right now, right? So you can look
at the project description here. So solve the differential equation partial t
partial time equal to a times partial square t partial x square plus a right
hand side. So that's basically our project while we're removing one of the
terms. And use a, b, and c as specified also tc is here. Initial condition is t
equal to 325 for all x. Boundary condition is t at times at x equal to 0
is equal to the same 325 and the right hand side is going to be a
Newman boundary condition. The derivative is equal to 10.
And given the solution at t equal to 300 start by writing a function mini
project 1 where n is the number of grid points which include x equal to 0 and x
equal to 1 and t is the final time at which the solution is sought. All right.
So here we are supposed to write a
solution. So we are supposed to write a solution. So we are supposed to write a
function.
function result is equal to mini project 1, n is the number of grid points
and what is 300. Oh and t, t is the time. So you are going to code up a functions
basically assign result to t.
And then you are going to write a function. So you are going to write a