We have essential boundary conditions, and we have natural boundary conditions.
Essential boundary conditions work by restricting the space for which we can have the solution.
Natural boundary conditions don't restrict the space. It comes out naturally from the weak form.
What type of boundary conditions did we set in the two-dimensional example we just went through?
Essential, because we are restricting the space. We're removing degrees of freedoms on the boundary.
So let's also discuss what we can do for natural boundary conditions.
So we have the divergence of gradient of u plus f equal to zero.
We cannot have the numerous boundary conditions everywhere.
So let's say we have split the domain into two parts.
This is partial omega 1, partial omega 2.
So let's say u at partial omega 1 is equal to zero, and how do we set the Newman boundary condition?
The other domain, we set it as the normal dot with the gradient of u equal to zero.
Okay.
So this is usually, for example, if you are solving a heat transfer problem,
this is saying that u is the solution of the temperature.
This is saying that I'm fixing the temperature in this part of the domain.
For example, I'm having this in contact with a heat source or heat sink
that maintains that boundary to be a constant temperature.
While on partial omega 2,
I have the gradient of the heat dot with the normal equal to zero.
What does that mean?
If I have a heat transfer problem?
Yes?
The flux is equal to zero, which means no heat goes through the boundary.
It's insulated on the other side.
Right?
So these are the two types of boundary conditions we can set,
Dirichlet and Newman boundary conditions.
Of course, you can set these two types of boundary conditions.
Okay.
So I set this to be non-zero to a certain other value.
That means I'm giving a fixed heat flux through the boundary.
Okay.
So how do we set this type of boundary conditions?
It turns out if we derive the weak form, it'll come out naturally.
So the weak form works by integrating the equation with the product of a test function.
And through integration by parts,
this came out to be V times n dot with the grad of U.
Right?
At the boundaries minus the weak form we had before.
Okay.
So we have the weak form.
We have the non-zero.
Okay.
So we have the non-zero.
And this boundary term is, it is zero for partial omega 1 because we restrict the space.
And therefore, V is going to be zero at the boundary.
It is going to be zero at partial omega 2 because the grad U dot n should satisfy the Newman boundary condition.
Right?
So that means we don't need to do anything at partial omega 2 other than not restricting the space to set it to zero.
Okay.
In order for you to satisfy that Newman boundary condition.
So, for example, in the code, let's do a very simple thing.
Remember I said this E, the boundary E, is,
has a flag at the very end.
So here, this 5, I think it corresponds to which edge it is.
So, for example, if I plot the P of x direction, E of, so, 0 to 5.
E of 1, 1 to 5.
So this is the first edge.
And, is that right?
Second dimension.
So this is 1 by, okay.
So then I should do P of 1 and E of 2, 1 to 5.
So this is the x direction of the boundary.
This is the x direction of, I'm just plotting the first 5 edges corresponding to the flag 5 equal to 1.
And the y direction, what I'm going to get is this.
That's weird.
Oh, I have another bunch of 1s over there.
So instead of 1 to 5, I should be setting,
setting E of 5 equal to 1.
So I'm just going to remove this 1 to 5 by this flag.
I have one more thing I need to replace, I guess.
Right, so that's one of the straight edges.
So let's take an example of setting one of these straight edges to,
to a Newman boundary condition.
Okay.
The only thing we have to do,
is to remove this, is to do a little bit trick on the IB, right?
So we did, we figured out IB was equal to all these,
all these edges, right?
So now we want to remove a certain set of points from IB.
So we want to remove the,
okay.
So let's only,
so let's only keep,
so to make it easier, let's only,
let's do Newman boundary condition to all the edges except for one of the edges.
So we are going to set it to E of 5 star equal to 1.
So we are going to,
we are going to set IB,
which is the value, which is the basic functions we restrict to 0,
only for the points along the first edge.
So now IB is going to be a much lower dimension,
it's much less number of points.
It only has 11 points.
So we are going to set 0,
this is bounded condition, only on these 11 points.
And all the other bounded conditions, we just don't do anything to it.
And according to our analysis on the natural bounded condition,
the bounded condition is naturally satisfied on the other points should be what?
Should be a 0 Newman boundary condition, right?
So now we have modified the IB and let's run this again.
And this obviously ran.
And let's do a try serve of this time.
All right.
So that's the solution we get.
Obviously, we are satisfying a 0 Dirichlet bounded condition on this particular edge, right?
So that's the edge that we set, still included in the set of IBs.
And all the other bounded conditions, let's actually look at the edge on
to make it a little bit more obvious that.
So we are, for example, we are looking at the left edge over here, right?
So from this particular point of view,
we are actually satisfying the normal derivative equal to 0 condition.
The derivative in normal to this edge should be on the horizontal direction
when I view it at this angle, right?
The horizontal direction, the derivative is equal to 0.
If I rotate it again, look at this edge from edge on,
the normal derivative is also going to be equal to 0.
So for any of these other edges, if you look at the normal,
the derivative normal to that edge, it's going to be 0.
So that's how we are satisfying a natural bounded condition.
Right?
Questions on this one?
Yes?
In the non-square-thick thing, there's a minus,
I can't remember what it comes from.
So the second equation on this page, where does that minus come from?
Oh, the minus comes from integration by parts.
So the minus comes from the fact that
if, so the integration by parts comes from taking v times gradient of u.
So v is a scalar, gradient of u is a vector, right?
So this is a vector.
So let's define this as a vector.
So let's define this as a w.
It's a vector, right?
So if I apply Gauss's theorem on this vector,
which is Gauss,
Gauss's theorem on this vector,
which means that the divergence of the vector
integrated over the whole domain should be equal to
the normal, output normal times the vector integrated over the boundary of the domain.
Right?
Oh, by the way, thanks for notifying this.
This is,
as opposed to the one-dimensional integration by parts,
the two-dimensional integration by parts is going to give me a boundary integral.
So this term needs to be integrated not in the interior, but over the boundary.
So this is ds, over the edge of the boundary.
So the interior divergence integral is equal to the boundary normal dot vector integral.
And then if I substitute,
the particular form of w into both left and right hand side,
the left hand side becomes
the divergence of the product of a scalar and the vector
is equal to two terms.
This is equal to the gradient of the vector,
dot product with the vector that is already inside,
which is grad of u,
plus v,
which is the scalar,
times the divergence of the vector that is already inside,
which is grad of u.
Alright, so this is just a chain rule for vector calculus.
And so this is the left hand side,
and the right hand side is,
we also substitute this w,
and that becomes v,
v is a scalar,
so I put it in front,
and dot with grad of u, ds.
So this is becoming our formula for integration by parsing 2D,
which is basically taking this on the left hand side,
and this on the right hand side,
and this on the right hand side.
Okay, so it says that the left hand side,
the integration of v times the Laplacian of a scalar u,
is going to be the boundary integral,
the first term on the right hand side,
v, n dot grad u, ds,
minus integration over the whole domain,
so that's the first term on the left hand side,
grad v dot grad u, dx.
So that's our formula for integration,
by parsing 2D.
That is going to help us derive all these equations.