How to analyze stability. So last time we touched a little bit on how to do
stability analysis looking at the norm of a matrix. Today we'll learn the
most powerful method of doing stability analysis for PDEs. It's called the
von Neumann stability analysis. I'm gonna start with a very simple example.
Still we are solving this equation partial u partial t equal to a kappa
times partial square u partial x square. And von Neumann stability analysis is
not just for any domain. It's for domains without a boundary. So what does that
mean? It means von Neumann stability analysis cannot analyze the effect of
complex boundary conditions.
It doesn't mean that the boundary conditions are not
stable. It can only analyze the stability of your discretization
itself. The discretization of the differential equation itself instead of
the boundary. So when you look at the differential equation and you want
to know if it's stable or not, you want to both make sure the discretization of
the PDE is stable and also the boundary condition is well-posed.
The discrete boundary condition is well posed. So for von Neumann stability analysis
analysis takes care of the first part. Alright, so remember in our first lecture
we did Fourier analysis, right? We split u into a summation of different
Fourier modes. k goes from minus infinity to infinity. u hat of k times e to the j
which is the square root of minus 1 times k times x. Alright, so this is, this
can be done for periodic domain of x goes from 0 to 2 pi, right? So domains
without a boundary means
the best way to think of a domain without boundary is periodic. So if you
go out of one end you come back to the other. In two dimensions you can do a
doubly periodic domain. It's like a computer screen. If you go out of the
right hand side you come back from the left hand side like playing a video game.
Mathematically that domain, periodic domain in two dimensions is officially
called a torus.
Why?
Because a one dimensional periodic domain is like a circle, right? So you go out
of one end, you come back from the other. A torus is like, it's like, it's
like, it's like that. So, so it's, there are two periodic dimensions one periodic
is along the ring and the other periodic is around it's a wrong, it's like a dot.
so you have a double periodic domain.
But in this case,
the Newman stability analysis applies both to 1D, 2D, and 3D.
So let's first look at this problem in 1D.
So when we express a function on the periodic domain
as a Fourier series,
that essentially decouples
the different Fourier modes for a linear PDE.
Because when I plug this into the equation,
we get the left-hand side becomes a summation of
d u hat k dt
e to the ijx.
So that is the left-hand side.
And the right-hand side becomes
kappa times summation of u hat k
when you take twice derivative.
The jk comes out of the exponential two times.
So jk squared is minus k squared
times e to the jkx.
Both are summation over k
goes from minus infinity to infinity.
So if you match the coefficients,
the coefficients on this side is this,
on that side is this.
What you get is,
d u hat k dt
equal to kappa
times minus k squared
times u hat of k.
So you know all the coefficients are decaying
except for the k equal to 0, 1.
And the bigger the k is,
the bigger the magnitude of k is,
the faster the coefficient decays.
That is voluminous stability analysis
for the continuous differential equation.
But we can apply exactly the same thing
for the discrete differential equation.
All right.
Let's look at after discretization.
So after discretization,
we have...