Today we are going to be starting to talk about finite difference in 1D.
The three main questions we want to answer in this class is how to approximate a
partial differential equation in a form that a computer can implement and solve.
And this is an approximation, it's not an exact solution. So how accurate or how
inaccurate, which is the same question, is our approximation? Well how do we find
out? And a part of this question is how do we construct approximations that are
as accurate as possible in some sense while as easy to implement and easy for
the computer to solve as possible. And the third question is how does the
approximation affect our solution?
So this looks like a very simple problem.
It looks like a weird question, but it is not. There is a difference between how
much error is it in the approximation of the PDE and when you solve it how much
error is in the solution. So these are two different things. We're going to look
at why they are two different things and how one, the approximation error, affects
the solution error. What's the link between them?
So first of all let's discuss, find a difference for the heat equation. The heat
equation is again partial u, partial t equal to a kappa times partial square u
partial x square. And this equation is both of the terms appears in the project
you have to do. So the behavior of this equation is going to be reflected in your numerical system.
So the behavior of this equation is going to be reflected in your numerical system.
And for the heat equation, the main thing we want to approximate is the spatial derivative
term. Because if we can discretize the spatial derivative term and remove the spatial derivative,
partial x, from the equation, what do we get?
We get an OD because we only have one derivative, we only have time derivative.
And for that OD, if we are given an initial condition, we can put it in any OD solver and solve it.
So for most of you who prefers MATLAB, you probably know OD45.
So for those of you who prefers Python, if you import scipy, there is scipy.integrate, and it has pretty good OD integrators.
Alright, if you don't know that, you should reconsider your option of choosing Python.
But the main goal is to get rid of the spatial derivative.
Okay, so how do we get rid of the spatial derivative?
We first need to approximate the solution, u as a function of x and t.
We want to approximate it as something of just a function of t.
And let's look at what are the options of doing that.
Going to MATLAB.
So I'm going to run two demos.
And the two demos is going to illustrate two different options of approximating a function of x
and t.
And the two demos is going to illustrate two different options of approximating a function of x and t.
So first of all, I'm going to tell you how a finite difference approximates a function.
And then I'm going to tell you how a finite volume, which is the second method of discretization, is going to approximate a function.
So here we go.
And again, I will ask somebody to draw a function.
And we'll see how on this 11-grid graph, we can get the final result.
So if you have 11 grid points, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11 grid points and 10 intervals,
how a finite difference is going to approximate your function?
All right.
Please.
By the way, I have uploaded my script for letting you draw a function.
So if you have any questions, please feel free to ask me.
And I will also be happy to answer any questions you may have.
Thank you.
What's your name?
Zach.
OK.
Zach's function is nice and smooth.
All right.
So that's good.
And his function is still shown in the thin red line on screen.
But the computer is going to find a difference.
It's going to forget about the whole function Zach has drawn.
And the computer only remembers the same thing.
It remembers the circles.
What are the circles?
They are just the values of the function at these grid points at the set of spatial locations.
That's how finite difference approximates a function.
It's basically the most straightforward way of approximating a continuous function.
Right?
And we are going to see a little bit later on
that finite volume is going to do things differently.
OK.
So let's actually run the demo here.
And I'm trying to reproduce the function Zach has drawn.
Maybe I'm doing that not so good.
This is actually how finite volume approximates roughly the same function.
Instead of circles, we get lines.
And what are these lines?
Anybody take a guess?
Yes?
Average value of the function in the intervals.
So finite volume has nothing to do with the grid points.
It looks at intervals.
It decomposes the domain into small intervals
and approximates the function using the average values inside these intervals.
That's how finite volume discretizes function.
But this class, we are going to discuss finite difference.
Which is approximating a function using the values at the grid points.
OK.
So we'll see advantages and disadvantages.
The advantage, of course, is simplicity.
It's a lot simpler to just think of the function value at individual grid points.