So remember in our finite difference if we draw a function we are discretizing
the function by storing the values of the function at the grid points and then
we use Taylor series a manipulation that is intrinsically differential to
approximate the differential operators just using these points now you should
understand finite volume in finite volume if I draw the same function I do
a function like that
if I draw a similar function
this is what I have in the computer what I have is the average over these finite
volumes these are intervals in 1D but they are going to be truly volumes in 3D
they are areas in 2D they are the average values of the function inside these
volumes
why is that?
the case well two things one is that now I'm really representing the function I
have a complete form of the function but piecewise constant and
that form actually does respect that the function can be discontinuous
right actually it even represents a continuous and smooth function as
piecewise discontinuous functions
and I think that is perfect in there and there we are all set thereī governed by
linear
series
all right let's see if you done that
did you mix them up well let's try actually show the difference I'm gonna try to show
volume averages, how does it relate to one of the forms we discussed?
It does relate to only the integral form.
Because if you look at the integral of the value over a and b, and think of this a and
b as the boundary of one of the intervals, how does the integral relate to the average
over the interval?
So how does average relate to the integral?
What is the correct way to average a function over a continuous domain?
Yes?
Just the integral of the function over the x?
Over the domain size, yes.
Just the integral of the function over the size of the domain is just the value, is the
average, is the mathematical definition of the average of the function over that small
interval.
So it is a direct representation, not even an approximation.
This is exact, that the left-hand side infinite volume can be exactly written as the time
derivative of the volume size, which is constant, times the volume average.
Right?
So d dt of u dx is exactly equal to the size of the volume, b minus a, times d u bar a b
dt.
And this u bar over a and b is exactly what we saw.
So we can write the derivative of the volume size, which is constant, times the volume
average.
Right?
This is exactly what we saw in the infinite volume.
Okay?
Now what are we missing to get the derivative?
This is equal to flux at a minus flux of b.
Right?
We need to somehow compute the flux of the function at the left and right of each interval,
at the boundaries of these discrete small volumes.
And we actually don't have the information here, because if you look at the continuous
function, the value of the function is here.
And the flux can be computed by evaluating the flux function, which is an analytic function,
at this value of u, which is last.
We only know that the value is somehow at the end of the function.
So we can write the derivative of the function at the end of the function.
And we can also compute the flux function at the end of the function.
It's somehow in between this average and this average.
We don't know what the value is.
Is that necessary to know that the very next interval is not in between the two?
Exactly.
That may not even be true, because over the next interval, the value of the function at
the interval is right here.
It lies even outside the range of the left domain average and right domain average.
So the final volume involves the flux.
And it involves approximation not on the differential operator, but on the function itself.
You have to somehow interpolate the function, not in the classical sense of interpolating
from some points to some other points.
It is interpolating the function from the averages of the function over domains to values
of the function on the domain boundaries.
To the limit, to the extension.
OK.
to the pointwise values is the approximation
we need to invoke in a finite volume approximation
for solving differential equations.