I will demonstrate this with an example. Is it clear so far?
Yeah?
You can make it non-dimensional.
Yeah.
For the conversion, which one is better?
If you normalize the data, it's not because the conversion or it's because the T is too
hard or something?
OK.
So if I get your question properly, you're asking if you don't non-dimensionalize in
the convergence, the quantity of the error it's calculating is going to be dimensional.
And how is that then going to be handled?
Yeah.
OK.
That's a good question.
So how it is handled is if you don't dimensionalize.
In the solver sequence, you pick a scaling for your independent file.
So you can specify a scaling, how it should scale it.
So it will actually divide the solver when it calculates the error before it puts it
into a tolerance.
It will divide it by the scaling you provide.
Then I don't need to change my equation, right?
No.
Just use the, all of them in the term of the habit dimensions?
Yeah.
You have dimensions and you can change it.
OK.
And then in the convergence check, you would put a scaling.
Yeah.
Does that answer the question?
OK.
So let's say we want to model the Poisson equation to start simple with a boundary
condition 0, a boundary condition 0 everywhere.
Now the way you use this template is by just matching the templates with the equation you
have.
What is the template?
The template is this, what we have in the domain.
But what is your equation?
Your equation.
It's the first equation.
So you don't have all these terms.
What do we have?
If you have c is equal to 1 and f is equal to 1 and everything else 0 in that equation,
you get the Poisson equation, right?
With the source term being 1.
So then you have your set in the domain.
Then now you want to pick what happens in the boundary.
So for what happens in the boundary, this is going to be a Drischli boundary condition.
The template is going to be u is equal to 1.
So you have the first equation.
If you have a set of 2, you have the second one.
So if you have r is equal to 0, then you get the Poisson equation.
Thank you.
So what happens is that you get r is equal to 0.
But then if you don't have it, for what?
If you had r is equal to r, then here what we have is r is equal to 0.
So just put r is equal to 0 and you are done.
So I will now go into the software and show how to enter this.
Is it clear so far?
Okay.
So if I start the software here, when you start a new model, as you would have seen
on Monday, you can start with a model wizard or a blank wizard.
If you started with a model wizard, you can becomes a model wizard on Monday.
It's pretty easy.
The first thing is you have to select your special dimension.
Let's say we are going to do a 2D problem.
Then you pick 2D.
Then you pick your physics, but in this case, you're not going to use any of the pre-built physics-based interfaces.
You are going to use the mathematics interface.
And you come here, you come to PDE.
We're going to use the coefficient form now.
I'll show you the general form later.
So you use the coefficient form, add that.
And here you can decide what to call the independent variable.
So by default, it wants to call it U.
But if you're, for example, solving a temperature problem,
and you want this to be similar to the variable name you are using often, then you can rename it.
And here you specify the units for the dimension and for the source there.
So let's leave this as it is now.
Study.
Then you pick your study type.
Are you doing a stationary study?
Is this an equilibrium problem where the time derivatives are all zero now?
Or is this a time-dependent problem, an eigenvalue problem?
So let's say this is a stationary problem.
Yes?
The equation is stationary, but it's not finding.
I just can call it a function.
Yeah.
But at this point, we haven't really specified the equation.
All we have said is we want to use equation-based modeling.
Right?
Yeah.
But that's a good concern.
I'll show you what happens.
So here you would define your geometry.
Let's say we just want to solve this on a unit square.
And I right-click on geometry, pick square, pick the dimensions, one by one.
Let's say the default was one.
So this is my domain.
Now the next thing is if I, there are three nodes here.
Your equation, your default boundary condition, and your initial condition.
Now let's go to the equation.
This is the equation.
And if you expand this equation section here, you will see the template.
So it's saying it wants to solve this.
Now you have to specify what is c.
C is in our case one.
So we keep c is equal to one.
If we had no source term, we will come back and put this f to zero.
Then, okay, now I have ea set to zero by default, ba to one.
But these values are zero, right?
I can type zero, but I can also not type them.
Because in a stationary study, it will ignore the time derivatives.
So let's say I actually had a non-zero mass term.
First, I want to solve it.
For a stationary case.
Next, I want to solve it for a time-dependent case.
So instead of putting the equation twice, I can just add another study, but make that study time-dependent.
So the stationary study will ignore the time derivative.
The transient study will keep the time derivative.
Does that address your question?
So, yes, I can put this to zero, but the time derivatives are ignored anyway in a stationary study.
And then you can check this other coefficient.
They are all zero.
What we want is this.
Now, actually, we're just solving the Laplace equation since I put f is equal to zero.
Then the next thing is the boundary condition.
The boundary conditions are setting the Neumann boundary condition to zero.
That's the default.
So basically, physics-wise, that's no flux of the quantity you are conserving.
So in a chemical reaction problem, this would be no concentration,
cross-division, no flux.
So in the boundary, in a structural mechanics problem, the momentum flux being stress, it would mean free of stress.
But if your boundary conditions are different from the default, you specify them.
So if I right-click here, right, on the physics or on the equation, these ones are things I could do on the domain.
But these ones are boundary condition.
So in our case, we have a Richelieu boundary condition.
I click that.
Then you choose where to apply this.
I could keep clicking, but if you are applying them for all boundary, you can also use this all boundaries.
Then what is this?
What is your solution outside?
We are using here u is equal to zero.
So if I specify that, that is already zero.
Then you build your mesh, and now you solve.
Now this is going to give me a zero solution back.
I'm solving the Laplace equation with zero boundary conditions.
But what we wanted to do was the Poisson equation.
So if I go back to the coefficient form and put f is equal to one and solve that.
What?
I put the boundary condition.
Oh, I put constraints.
I should have put the Richelieu boundary condition.
All boundaries.
Okay.
So this is Poisson equation with source terms equal to one.
I mean, here I can post-process it for other quantities, maybe make a contour plot
or maybe here instead of just surface.
Okay.
So I can do that.
So I can do the surface, add a height expression.
This would be my solution.
But the idea is if you're using the coefficient form, you just come here in the equations template,
and then you fill in these terms so that the template matches the equation you have.
Here I have initial values.
In the time-dependent, in a time-dependent problem, those are physically meaningful quantities
of where did you start?
Where are you starting?
What was the state of your problem at t is equal to zero or whenever you start solving
this problem?
But for a stationary problem, they don't have any physical meaning.
But can you think of a way they can be useful?
Any guess?
Yeah, can you make it more, can you elaborate more?
Convergence and next configuration?
Exactly.
So these equations are potentially nonlinear, right?
In this case, you win the first time.
In this case, we are solving a linear problem but think of solving this nonlinear problem.
What happens?
The weak form will convert this and then when you add the finite element it's going to tell
this.
So what happens?
at the end what you will have is a system of nonlinear algebraic equations for the nodal
values.
So when you have nonlinear algebraic equations, you're going to solve them using a Newton-Raphson
or other method like that.
And there, you are going to start with an initial value and iteratively try to get to
your solution.
So even though this initial value is not, it's physically meaningless for a stationary
problem, you can nudge it.
If you have any a priori information, if you have some estimate about your solution, you
can type that in and then it will help the solver converge faster.
Or this is assuming you have a unique solution.
In cases where you have multiple solutions, you can also use this initial value to sort
of bias, right?
It will most likely converge to the solution closer to the initial value you are putting
in.
Okay.