Now we have the discrete Fourier series. How do we apply von Neumann stability analysis?
Let's plug this series into the differential equation and see what happens.
So again, the exponential term has nothing to do with time derivative.
The only term that has to do with time derivative is the u hat k term.
So we have a d u hat k dt times e to the jk i delta x.
So that's the left-hand side. And the right-hand side is different from the continuous case.
What's amazing, at least to me, is that
when we plug this in,
we plug the Fourier series into the continuous derivative,
we get rid of the coupling between different exponentials.
That actually also happens for discrete differential operators on a uniform grid.
So we look at the right-hand side. We have a kappa of something long divided by delta x squared.
And let's take a look at what this something long is.
So first of all, all the terms u of i plus 1,
u of i plus 1,
u of i minus 1,
and u of i,
they are summation of k over the same space.
And all of them are u hat of k.
That we don't have anything to do.
I mean, they are different only with i.
So the parenthesis is the following.
e to the jk i plus 1 delta x, right?
So that's the u i plus 1 term.
Plus e to the jk of i minus 1 delta x.
That's the u i minus 1 term.
Minus e to the jk i delta x.
So that's the effect of plugging in the discrete Fourier series
into the discretized differential equation. Yeah?
Ah, we need the two. Thank you.
So we have the discrete operator.
And now the key question is,
what is this thing in the parenthesis?
Right?
So let's, on the next page,
figure out what is this thing on the parenthesis.
Can I just...
I can still write here, but, uh, anyway.
So the parenthesis is j to the j plus...
Not j plus 1.
Ah...
jk i plus 1.
jk i plus 1 delta x.
Plus e to the jk i minus 1 delta x.
Minus 2 e jk i delta x.
So, the first thing to do is to expand this
as e to the jk i delta x
plus jk delta x.
And this to e to the jk i delta x
minus jk delta x.
Right?
And then, the summation...
the exponential of summations
is equal to the product of exponentials.
And same thing as here,
except for there is a minus sign.
And now we can collect the terms.
We all have this term, this term, and this term.
It becomes e to the jk i delta x
times e to the jk delta x
plus e to the minus jk delta x
minus 2.
All right?
So now, this is something that does not depend on i.
It only depends on k.
So now we plug this back into the equation we started.
We have summation of k.
Ah...
du hat k.
dt e to the jk i delta x
is going to be equal to the same summation
u hat of k.
Ah...
Okay, I missed a kappa here.
There is a kappa here.
Ah... u hat of k.
This thing divided by delta x squared.
So we have e to the jk i delta x.
Okay, so let me first write...
So what we are going to be doing is plug what we derived earlier into the equation.
All right, so this is...
This is the equation we finally got.
After manipulating the discrete Fourier series.
Again, we can match terms.
On the left-hand side, we have this.
On the right-hand side, we have kappa times u hat of k
times this thing we just derived.
All right?
What is left is basically summation of the same co...
the coefficient times e to the jk i delta x.
It's the same here. It's the same here.
So that means
du hat of k dt
would be equal to kappa times u hat of k
times...
Let me just write u hat of k later.
Times this weird long thing we just derived.
Times u hat of k.
But no matter how weird this thing is,
it is the time derivative of u hat of k
equal to something times u hat of k.
That's a differential equation we know the analytical solution of.
Right?
So it's just u hat of k equal to exponential of this whole thing times t.
And what determines the stability of this equation?
Yes, the real part of this whole thing has to be negative.
This number, it can be a complex number.
In this case, it happens to be a real number.
But if it's a complex number,
we only need to make sure the real part of this
or the number is on the left-hand side of the complex plane.
Compare this to the analytical.
So this is the discrete.
And compare to the analytical case.
Let's use blue.
We have du hat of k dt equal to,
in this case, analytically,
we had kappa minus k squared.
Right?
Kappa minus k squared.
u hat of k.
The continuous and discrete case,
they look slightly different.
And this is the effect of discretization.
All right.
And let's figure out what this is.
So,
so e to the jk delta x
is equal to cosine of j,
no j,
cosine of k delta x
plus i sine of k delta x.
e to the minus jk delta x
is equal to the same cosine,
but minus i times sine of k delta x.
And therefore, the summation of them
turns out to be positive.
And if I minus another 2,
this 3, which is here,
would be equal to
2 times cosine k delta x
minus 2.
Right?
So that's what we get.
Okay.
And if you look at the cosine function,
and remember, we're also dividing this by delta x squared.
and if you remember the Taylor series expansion
of this cosine function at 0,
the first derivative is 0.
The second derivative is minus half.
So, when k times delta x is small,
when delta x is small enough compared to k,
what you get is,
this is actually a good approximation of minus k squared.
So,
so 2 times cosine k delta x
minus 2 over delta x squared
approximates minus k,
right,
minus k squared,
when delta x times k is small.
Alright.
And also, another good thing is that,
what is the sign of this number?
Positive or negative?
It's always negative, right?
That's another good thing.
That means this differential equation,
if the time derivative is solved exactly,
it is going to be always stable.
That's a hallmark of a good discretization,
is something always stable is great.