Yeah, right? You will basically get something like a singularity, right?
All right, is it clear so far? So these are the kind of things you will be thinking when you are
adding this. So the final item example I want to talk here is, it's in the blog so you can read
that for more details I'll show you, but thermal curing. So in thermal curing what you have is
these two equations. Now the first one is a heat transfer equation where you have a source term
coming from the curing process if alpha is the curing rate. So then in the second one you have
just an equation for the curing rate. So this is a heat transfer equation, and I'll give you a
little bit of a summary of this. So this is a heat transfer equation. So this is a heat transfer
equation. This is the Arrhenius equation. A lot of chemical kinetics kind of problems take that
form. Now the first question is what interfaces are we going to use to solve this? Normally you
would use the heat transfer interface for the first equation since we have already implemented
that. But assume you are going to use equation-based modeling entirely. What would you use
for the first one? What interface would you use?
Any of the PDE interfaces would work, right? Let's say coefficient-borne PDE. How about the second equation?
The ODE interface, right? Because there is no special derivative there. So if you don't have special
derivatives you have to use the ODE interfaces. But we have two ODE interfaces. Domain ODE and Global ODE.
Which one should you use?
The domain ODE.
Domain? Global? Which one?
.
Why would you say domain ODE?
Because alpha can be a functional spatial.
Why can alpha be a function of space? In that equation, in the second equation, is there anything that
would make alpha a function of space?
Initial value.
Let's say, okay, let's say, that's a good way. Let's say initial values are fixed. Let's say that value A is
fixed, EA is fixed, all parameters in that equation are fixed. Is it still a domain
or a global ODE? Are you sure? T is a function, it's coupled right? So on its own yes it
would it was almost a global ODE, a domain ODE if everything was constant
but we are coupling this to temperature and the temperature is a PDE which can
have different solutions so the fact that the temperature is affecting the
curing rate would necessarily we use the domain ODE feature. Is it clear? So if we
are doing that here you can add this will also revisit the coupling. How do
you now couple because there is a coupling term right? Here in the
coefficient form we just specify in this equation EA these are the diffusion
coefficients.
from the first equation, no source terms originally or we can write the source
term here. There is a source term right that there is this term but the way to
add that then is to your coefficient form or EA you can add a
source term if you right click this and say source and that source term you see
this declaration d alpha t make it a function of the other variable now you
have coupled it and then in the second domain ODE, you can add this to the coefficient form.
So if you have coupled this to the coefficient form and then in the third
domain ODE then this source term that you have to type make it a function of
temperature. So now you have coupled both. Is it clear? Questions? So then I
will skip through this verification and validation and give you the homework.