How costly is multigrid?
And here, we are going to look at one-dimensional, two-dimensional, and three-dimensional problems.
So, this is the multigrid cycle we have performed.
We perform a smoothing on the fine grid.
So, let's say the cost is proportional on a one-dimensional grid.
And this is proportional to n, right?
So, let's say alpha n is the pre-smoothing on the fine grid.
And interpolation cost is very similar to the smoothing iterations.
It's basically proportional to the number of grid points.
And this is proportional to n over 2 for a one-dimensional grid.
This is proportional to n over 4.
And this is proportional to n over 8.
And coming back, this is also n.
n over 4, n over 2, and n, right?
So, one multigrid cycle is going to have a cost of a constant times n,
plus half n, plus a fourth n, plus n over 8.
If you have more grids, it will be n over 16, etc., etc.
If you add all these up,
and you want to approximate it by something,
what would it look like?
n of 1 plus half plus a fourth plus 8.
Do you recognize this series?
What's the summation of the series?
About 2, right?
So, that's approximately twice the cost
of only doing...
the fine-grid iterations.
If you don't go to the cost grid,
you just perform the iterations you would do on the fine-grid.
You would be saving only half of the computation cost.
And if we only do these 10 Jacobi or Gauss-Seidel iterations on the finest grid,
you probably see the solution not converging at all.
Like, you only get a few lines.
So,
so, that's the solution.
So, that's not the whole story yet,
if you look at it on the two-dimensional problem.
So, this is 1b.
On the two-dimensional problem, just like what we just solved.
And imagine n is the total number of grid points on the finest grid.
The series is different.
So, this is still n.
When you go to a cost grid, the grid is four times smaller.
Right?
So,
n over 4 and n over 16, etc.
So, what we would get in the 2D is 1 over 4, 1 over 16, plus etc.
Well, it's n times 1 over 1 minus 1 fourth.
So, that's about 4 over 3 times n.
So, this is only a little bit more expensive than doing this thing,
doing only the fine grid operations.
Right?
Okay.
So, furthermore, as you can imagine, if I go to 3D, that'll be even more cheaper.
So, the next grid is an eighth as expensive.
And the next one is 64 as expensive.
And this is going to be 1 minus eighth.
And that'll be 8 over 7 times n.
So, again, a little bit more expensive.
More expensive than doing this only on the fine grid.